Hi, in this lecture, I'm going to
tell you about the minimum you should
know about testing.
So the goal of this lecture is that
you learn, you understand what is
the benefit of having tests.
So how can you trust that you made
a change in some big system?
So you have your big system here
and you make a change here.
How can you know that you didn't
break anything?
Yeah?
Imagine that you work in a financial
system and you want that your clients
don't lose any money.
So in those critical places,
you should know that you didn't
break anything.
So how can you trust that your change
didn't break anything?
How can you trust also that the
system is working properly,
even if you didn't make any changes?
We are going to see how unit testing
can help us to do that and how you
write tests.
So what are the main points of testing?
So if you make a change in your system,
I have my system here,
I make a change, so what is a test?
So a test will verify.
It's a piece of code that will verify
automatically that everything that
was depending on this piece of code
that changed is still working.
Yeah?
And it will tell you,
yeah, it's okay, it's okay,
it's okay.
So in this sense, tests are like
life insurance.
You can become aware of a regression
or a side effect in the system that
you were not expecting.
So you can go over and change stuff
here and there.
And you know that if your tests are okay,
then you should be at least confident
that you didn't break anything.
So it actually removes pressure
from development.
In that sense, also tests will enable
future evolution because that means
that we can freely go and change
things in the system knowing that
we didn't break anything and it
removes fear of change.
So you're not going to fear that,
ah, what are the possible things
that may be broken if I change
something?
So you can just change something
and see if your tests are broken or not.
So of course, tests will not prevent
bugs, but they can help you detect
unnoticed problems in the system.
I'm going to insist very hard here
that an automated test actually
does not exist.
So what is important about the test
is that it can be executed many,
many times automatically and without
any human intervention.
The main goal of a test,
of an automated test,
is that you can make it run,
for example, in a robot,
in a continuous integration environment.
We can make them run in a loop every
time that there is a new change
that comes into the system.
So we can integrate something,
a new change.
And if something breaks,
we are going to automatically be
notified of something that happened.
Unit tests will ensure that also
you can correctly specify the behavior
of a class.
You can not only try to check that
everything is working okay but you
can use them to document the behavior
of your system.
What we're going to say is that
a unit test will test a single feature.
That is why it is called a unit test.
So it doesn't test a big part of
the system.
So we're going to split our system
into many small pieces.
Usually, each part, each one of
these pieces is either a module
or a feature, feature one,
feature two, and then each test
is going to test one of these features.
You have to think that tests are
like scaffolding.
So they are actually surrounding
your feature to make sure that it
will work.
If you make one test per scenario,
this also will make sure that you
will identify really clearly when
there is one feature that is broken
and you will not get polluted results.
So if this feature is broken,
you want to know that this feature
is broken and not all the dependent
ones.
So being able to identify each feature
installation helps you to detect
the causes of the problems before.
So what is a test?
So a test has three main parts.
First, it will have a context,
which is the main description of
the scenario.
Then we have a stimulus,
so something that we do on top of
that context to provoke a change.
And finally, we have a check of
how that stimulus should have,
what that stimulus should have provoked.
That we're going to check with
assertions.
So we have something,
we have a scenario, we're going
to make a change, and then we're
going to observe what happened and
test that our observations of the
system satisfy what we expected.
Let's go with a concrete example.
Here, for example, we can apply
this template of a test to testing set.
Yeah, a set is a collection of objects
that doesn't support duplicate elements.
So in this case, our set,
if we try to add a duplicate element,
it will only add the first one.
And the second time we add the same
element, it will just ignore it.
Yeah?
So in this case, what is our context?
So we create an `empty` set,
or first, we create a set that doesn't
have any elements.
Our stimulus is that we're going
to add twice the same element to
that set.
So the first time that we add the
element to a set, the set is going
to store it.
The second time, the set is going
to ignore it.
Or that is what we expect.
In the third part of our test,
we're going to check exactly those
expectations.
So we are going to check that the
set contains exactly one element
and not two.
So it should have ignored the second
element.
Translating that to code in Pharo
gives us something like this.
So here we have one class,
which is a subclass of TestCase
and is where we are going to store
all the tests for sets.
And then each of the tests is going
to be written as a method.
So here, for example,
we have the testAdd is our method
that is going to express our testing
scenario.
So here, our test, we have divided
it in three parts using comments.
So here, for example,
we have the "Context",
then the "Stimulus", and then the
"Check".
So the "Context" is doing exactly
what we said before.
We are going to instantiate the
sets and store it in a variable.
Then we're going to add two times
the same object.
And then we're going to assert that
the size of our set is equal to one.
The same test can be written in
Java using, for example,
(Junit40) in this way.
So in Java, we can inherit from
object directly.
And then to mark a test as a test,
we need to use the test annotation.
And then the test goes exactly as
it was before in Pharo.
So we need a //Context,
//Stimulus, and a //Check with an
assertion.
When we run a test, three main things
can happen.
We can have a success,
which means that the tests run okay,
and all our expectations work correctly.
Second, we can have a failure if
one of our assertions did not work
as expected.
So for example, our assert:
collection size equals:1.
This didn't return 1,
it returned 2.
So we will have a failure if an
assertion doesn't work as expected.
Third, we're going to have an error
if there is an unexpected condition,
such as, for example,
an exception at runtime.
For example, here, if our set
implementation is not correct,
and we have two elements,
two times the element 5 inside the
collection, and this returns 2,
here we're going to have a failure.
Usually these in testing frameworks,
they are set with the yellow color.
We can have an error when,
for example, we have an unexpected
exception inside the test.
So for example, here,
we have a test that is asserting
something.
In this case, we are asserting the
same thing as before,
but we are sending this message
that is an unknown message.
The `foobar` method is not in the
set hierarchy.
So here, this will rise,
it does not understand the exception.
And since our test was not written
to expect an exception,
this is an unexpected failure and
also called an error.
Now, what happens if we have many
tests that have the same context?
There is one way that is provided
by many testing frameworks to reuse
the test context.
So why do we want to do that?
Because duplicating the test context
will probably cause problems in
the future if we want to evolve
our tests.
So if we want to change the context
for all our tests, then we have
to change all the potential repeated
code.
So duplication is never a good idea.
So this means also that changing
the test will be more complicated.
So people will think twice before
changing something, and that is not good.
So we want to be able to change
the code much more easily;
not only the code of the application,
but also the code of the test.
So most of the frameworks offer
then this `setUp` method that you
can redefine to create a context
that will be executed before each test.
So in this case, what will happen
is that imagine that we have four
different test methods:
so the Test 1, the Test 2,
the Test 3, and the Test 4.
So if we have a #`setUp` method
and a #tearDown method,
the #setUp method and the #tearDown
method will be executed before and
after each Test method.
So in this case, we are going to
execute the #setUp,
the Test, then the #tearDown,
then the #setUp again,
the Test, the #tearDown,
the #setUp, the Test,
the #tearDown, and so on.
So this 'setUp' will allow us to
reuse the context.
So we are going to be able to initialize
our context only once in the code,
and this will be executed many times
by the framework automatically.
And the 'tearDown' will help us to
clean up the system.
So this is also useful.
For example, if the `setUp` is creating
a file, usually the tearDown can
tear down or destroy the file to
avoid that our test leaves a dirty
system behind.
To do this, for example,
one thing that we can do to refer
to our previous test is that we
can define `empty`.
Instead of using a temporary variable
we can use an instance variable,
an attribute of the class,
and the `setUp` method can set that
variable that we can then use in
the test.
Remember, tests help us to trust
the system.
So you don't need to build all of
them at once.
You can build them incrementally
and on demand.
So every time, for example,
one strategy to manage the writing
of tests is that every time that
we find the bug, we can write the
test for the bug.
And later, if that bug reappears,
if we have a regression,
our test will actually detect that
problem.
One way also to develop the system
that will be handled in a separate
lecture is that we can write the
test before the code as a specification.
So you want that your system behaves
like this, and then you can implement
the behavior for that test.
So this is going to be talked about
in the lecture of TDD.
Also, since tests then can be thought
about as an active documentation
that is going to be executable,
it's always in sync with your code
because if you run your test and
you make sure that your tests are green,
then those tests are actually specifying
what should happen with your system.
However, be careful because writing
tests, they have a cost.
So you have to write them,
you have to maintain them,
you have to run them,
maybe in a continuous integration
`setUp`, so they consume also energy
and runtime.
So be sure that you make them
worthwhile.
But the payoff is huge if you can
ensure that.
Of course, you cannot cover everything
with just tests, so nobody can.
Really complicated.
So some strategies that you can
use to define tests is that write
tests when you find a bug,
instead of trying to write tests
for all your code at once.
You can then, once you have the
test that is breaking,
either with a failure or with an
error showing the defect,
then you can fix your code until
the test succeeds.
Taking this to the extreme,
you can use TDD that will be treated
more in detail in another lecture,
but the idea is that you are going
to start with the test.
You are going to use the test not
for testing, but actually to describe
the behavior of your system.
So the test is actually you start
from writing the specification in
an executable way, and then you
are going to implement the specification
written in your test.
So tests are going to be written
step-by-step as you develop and
as you increment the features in
your system for every new piece
of functionality.
What makes a good test?
So if you want to have some rules
of thumb, the first thing that is
important is that tests should be
repeatable.
So you should be able to run them many,
many times without any human
intervention.
So why?
Because you want that to run,
in a CI setting, for example,
in an automatic way.
You would want that your tests don't
write files that are not deleted later,
because maybe if you write a file
and you don't delete it,
maybe a later test will fail because
a previous test wrote the file.
So you want that somehow the `setUp`
and the tearDown ensure that that
test doesn't leave anything dirty
in the system.
You don't want any human intervention.
You want that the test automatically
tells you if everything was wrong or not.
And if something went wrong,
you want that the test automatically
tells you what was wrong in the system.
You want that the tests are
self-described and easy to read,
because tests are not only for the
machines, but also for the people
that are going to use them as
documentation.
And you have to make sure that tests
change less often than the system
otherwise, they don't pay off.
So that is why the test should be
more about the specification than
the implementation.
Like that, you can change the
implementation as much as you want
without changing the actual
specification.
In conclusion, so invest in writing
tests.
They are the best scaffolding and
they let you trust the system that
you're writing.
You can use TDD, an Xtreme TDD,
starting by writing a test and then
making that test pass and making
it green and be sure that tests
are a good investment.