Hi, in this lecture, we are going
to discuss again about tests and
why they are important.
The goals of this lecture is to
discuss why tests are important,
what are their advantages and what
are the many techniques or some
of the many techniques that are
there available to write good tests.
Now, before going into the detail
of how to write good tests,
it's good to review why testing
is beneficial.
So the first thing is that we need
to understand that tests are like
life insurance.
So every time that we are going
to change something in a system,
the test will allow us to detect
if we introduce a problem or not.
So in that way, they allow us to
have trust in the system and trust
in our changes.
We can go and modify things more
freely without having fear that
we did or not break something.
So we are not afraid of changing.
Also, they will help us in understanding
code.
That's something that we're going
to discuss later in some of the slides.
And of course, they will not avoid
breaking the system.
We can still go inside the system,
change stuff and break it.
But tests can help us detect early
if a problem was introduced or not,
instead of detecting it very,
very late during the development
process.
So remember that the unit test that
is not automated doesn't exist.
What does it mean?
That if I have to manually go and
write the test and if I have to
go manually and check the results,
they are taking so much time that
actually what will happen is that
nobody will ever run them or verify
them.
So automation is something that
will help us to do it more and more
often.
So this is important also because
once we wrote the test,
we can forget about it and run it again.
So we can have hundreds or thousands
of tests that will run maybe every
night or maybe every couple of hours.
Like that, we don't need to remember
everything that we did in the past.
We have already a set of tests that
we wrote in the past and we can
reuse them.
It's important that you remember
that usually we are able to keep
seven plus minus two ideas in our
head at the same time.
So having the writing the test,
reusing it later is something that
is actually a way to flush information.
So of course, the other thing that
is important is that programming
is about modeling the world and
the world is changing.
So we need a way to cope with changes
and to trust the way we are doing
the changes.
So tests will give us some way to
structure our way to change the system.
So tests will, as I said before,
help you to not fear changes.
This has many flavors.
In one side, if you have a system
and you change it, of course,
tests will detect if you introduce
a problem in the system.
In that sense, you can go and try
different implementations for already
existing code.
And if you have tests for that part
of the system, tests can already
tell you if the new implementation
satisfies the existing specification
that is in the tests.
Another thing is that you can write
new tests about the already existing
system to test that your understanding
of the system is correct.
So you can actually extend your
specification of the test to see
if it actually describes the
implementation.
What is a good thing about tests?
So on one side, they will help you
find bugs when they appear.
So a test that turns red or turns
yellow, so a failing test or a test
with an error, it is telling you
that there is something wrong about
the specification of the system.
On the other side, if you have lots
of tests, you can yourself as a
developer, or as a team,
you can trust your code base and
also transmit that trust to your
customers and clients.
Tests will also help you to reproduce
complex scenarios.
So you can, once you have a complex bug,
you can write it in a test,
even if it is a complex test and
reproducing the test will help you
to understand the bug and find a
solution to fix it.
Also, once you find a bug,
you can also write the test for it.
So and then that already existing
test will make sure that if in the
future you find the regression and
that bug appears again in the code base,
you will be able to detect it.
Finally, a test helps in isolating
a problem.
Instead of running a test on a really
big complex application,
you can create small scenarios that
reproduce the test with the minimal
dependencies.
Reducing the dependencies is something
that actually will help you to not
only find the bug, the actual cause
of the problem, but also to fix
it much faster.
When you're writing a test suite,
one of the things that you must
ensure is that you are checking,
for example, extreme cases that
you're checking for null,
zero, empty collections.
So for example, you need to check
that a collection has the maximum
elements, the no elements at all,
and so on.
You should also check complex cases
or error cases like exceptions,
network issues.
These things actually happen in reality.
So the system should not only test them,
but it should acknowledge that they
will happen and be prepared for it.
One thing that I think is pretty
useful is to write one test for each bug,
at least.
So every time that you find a bug,
you can write at least one test
for it to be able to know that in
the future you are going to be able
to detect that bug if it happens again.
Of course, a good test suite has
in general a good coverage.
So if you have a system and you
know that your test covers 80% of
your code, you have some trust that
there will be less bugs in this
part than in this part of the system.
Of course, a good test suite will
check for abstractions and not for
implementations.
Implementations will change in the
future, but abstractions and
specifications are there to stay.
Also, one of the things that make
a good test suite is that you are
going to write many unit tests that
test different parts of the system
independently.
Like that, if one test is failing,
it is telling you that some part
of the system is breaking and not
the other parts of the system.
Let's check how all of those good
properties of test translate into
an example.
Here there is a test that checks
how color objects are translated
into strings, hexadecimal strings,
using the convert method.
So here we can see that a white
color is converted to the FFFFFF,
the red color is translated to FF
followed by zeros, and the color
black is translated to all zeros.
So what we can see from here and
what we can understand from the
code without actually looking at
the implementation is that the convert
method, it will take any color and
it will translate it to a hexadecimal
representation where the first two
digits are the red, the second two
digits are the green component,
and the third digits are the blue
component.
So actually, without looking at
the implementation, this test is
telling us that color green should
return zero for red, FF for green,
and zero for blue.
And we could actually know this
by just looking at this specification
and without looking at the
implementation.
In the same venue, we can actually
look at this other test that is
checking that converting from an
R00000 string will actually yield
us the correct color.
So what this test is doing is that
it is taking all the digits from
zero to F to take all the potential
possibilities here.
And for each of these,
it is creating a string that will
have this form.
So it will be this plus parameter,
parameter, 0000, yeah.
So, and then it's taking this string
and it's creating a color from the
string.
We expect, of course,
that creating a color from this string,
so we get a color, and converting
it back to the string representation,
it should give the same string.
So this should be equals to the
original string.
What this is checking is that from
string and the convert method are
symmetric in some way.
So everything that is given as input
to the fromString method should
be also the output of the convert
method.
Now, if we take a look also at some
tests that check the `bitShift`
implementation in Pharo,
we can again look at these tests
and understand how this `bitShift`
implementation works without actually
looking at the implementation details.
Two key parts make this test readable.
First is that they are actually
based on how this works and how
it is implemented, of course,
because we are just executing it
and comparing the result.
But also the writer of this test
made really sure to write these
examples in binary.
Like that, since `bitShift` is a
binary operation, we can actually,
just by reading it, understand what
this is doing.
So if we take a number,
so here is 1, 1 in binary,
so the 2r is here to indicate the base.
So for example, in Pharo,
you can do 2r 1 1.
It's 1 1 in binary, and you can
say 16r to put hexadecimal numbers.
So here, if we take 1,
1and we shift it two to the left,
this will actually put two zeros
and put the ones to the left.
So the result should be 1,
1, 0, 0.
Likewise, if we `bitShift` instead
of to the left, to the right,
using a negative shift,
that will cut these two numbers
and remove them from the number.
So here, for example,
shifting 1, 0, 1, 1 to the right by two,
it will discard the one,
one that are to the right,
and it will keep only the 1,
0.
Again, here we can check the same
thing as before, as it happened
with numbers.
We can check that `bitShift`ing
to the left and to the right,
they are symmetric.
And we can understand that property
by just reading the test and without
looking at implementation.
So what does this test do?
It takes 100 numbers and it will
just take the number one and shift
it n to the left and then n to the
right.
And at the end, we should have the
same number.
So if I take one and I shift it
n to the left and then I shift it
n negated, so this returns the negative
number for i, that should return one.
Now, of course, I told you before
that we can understand implementation
and how it works without looking
at the code.
Of course, sometimes reading the
code is complicated.
Some implementations can be tricky
and even can be really difficult
to read because of even performance
reasons.
In this case, for example,
the convert method that we were
looking before, it is defined like this.
So it takes first a string,
it makes a copy of it.
So like that, we have a new string
every time that the convert method
is executed.
And then, it is replacing by hand
each of the characters,
so the second, third,
fourth, fifth, sixth,
and seventh, so each of these after
the numeral character.
And it is replacing each of them
by a character computed automatically
by doing bit operations.
So of course, if we had to read
this code, it wouldn't be actually
clear what this code is doing.
It is much more easily actually
to understand this code by just
reading the test.
So one of the important points to
understand the test and to manage
the test is that we need to limit
the dependency to other components.
So imagine, for example,
that we want to write the test that
transforms some piece of code,
so some code here, and we want to
transform that code into some other
code.
So our test is actually managing
this translation.
Now, if this input can only be obtained
by calling a compiler on something,
that means that our test is going
to be dependent on this compiler.
So which means that actually our
test can break if our conversion breaks,
but also if the compiler breaks.
So that means that we have two points
of failure for our tests.
One possible solution to cope with
this problem is to make our test
independent from the compiler.
So removing all this part from the
test at all.
So what we can do is to extract
this piece before the writing of
the test, so the input and reuse
that input already generated once
and reuse it many, many times in
our test.
So like that, our test,
it can only perform the conversion.
When you write test, think about
testing not only the positive,
but also the negative properties
of the behavior you are testing.
So for example, when I'm talking
about positive testing,
I mean, if you do the normal stuff,
it passes, everything is okay.
So we are, for example,
if we have a collection,
we add an element, now we have that
element in the collection.
Or in a more complex case,
that you can, for example,
login in an application if you use
the correct credentials.
Now, if you think about also the
negative properties of a test,
you should test that if you do not
behave correctly, the test breaks
as expected.
So for example, you should not be
able to load, log in with the incorrect
credentials.
And not only that, it should raise,
for example, an exception with a
given code and like that in the UI,
you can catch it and show a proper
message to the user.
If it just breaks and then it closes
your browser, for example,
then that is not an expected error.
Some other positive properties of test.
Test, as we saw before,
they give simple and reproducible
examples.
Just by looking at the examples
in the test, you understand how
the code works.
Many tests have this property.
They also give you executable snippets
and examples of code that you can
reuse in many other applications.
Every time that, for example,
you want to use a library that is,
for example, an open source library
that is online, you can take a look
at the test to understand how that
library can be used.
So then in that sense,
tests do not only give you executable
snippets, but they also illustrate
the API.
So how is the way to use that library?
Also, tests will be the most up-to-date
documentation because they are actually
connected with the code and they
are going to be executed.
If the tests are broken,
you are going to notice.
If the documentation is outdated
and it's broken, it's more difficult
to know.
Tests will also check the conformity
of new code.
If you introduce new code and new
variations in the code or you modify
the existing code, tests will actually
detect if you broke something.
So think about tests as a first
client to the code.
So you have some code and instead
of thinking about the actual people
that is going to use it,
think about how you would use it
with your test.
So your test can be a good first
client for your code.
And they also allow you to force
a customizable design.
So they will force you to maintain
a clean design that can be executed
in a repeated way that will not
dirty an environment with files
that are created automatically and so on.
So the test will actually force
you to add a lot of properties that
are inherent to the test in your code.
Of course, a good test fit should
be deterministic.
That means that every time that
you run the test, they should give
you the same results.
That is in contrast with what we
call flaky test.
Flaky test is something that we
are not going to cover in this MOOC,
but flaky tests are those tests
that actually will randomly have
different results.
For example, they will sometimes
fail because of random conditions.
For example, the network had problems
and then they will fail.
Having flaky tests or non-deterministic
tests actually will minimize the
trust that you have in your test
because if you have tests that are
failing from time to time,
suddenly you will start not trusting
your test suite anymore.
So keeping a deterministic test
suite is important to keep trust.
Also, tests are self-explained because
when you want to evolve your source
code, you want to evolve not only
your application but also the tests
because the tests are the specification
of your source code.
So the more easily and more
self-explained your tests are,
the easier they are to evolve.
Also, it is important to keep them
simple or short or unit,
as unit as possible, with as few
assertions as possible because they
are easier to maintain.
Take into account that tests will
change less frequently than the
code because tests will ideally
test the API, test the specification
and not the implementation.
Like that, you can change the
implementation of your source code
and keep the same test implementation.
And try to limit the dependency
to other elements.
This is also key to avoid ripple
effects in the changes.
In conclusion, you should know by
now that tests are important,
in particularly in dynamically typed
languages where actually we get
the most guarantees from them.
And also, not only in dynamically
typed languages, but in any kind
of project, actually tests will
help you to deliver complex projects.