Pablo Tesone - Hello and welcome
to this lecture about parametrized
tests.
The idea of this lecture is to show
how we can reuse test logic with
a lot of different values,
how we can run our test with all
possible combinations of these values,
and doing so, to present the
parametrized test, we are going
to use a naïve example that shows
the power on how we can complete
these two goals.
Let's start with a simple problem.
We have a simple test that asserts
assuming two different fractions
give us the correct number.
But this test only tests this specific
case with these specific values.
So we need to have a way of generalizing
it to make it more powerful and
to cover more cases, so we are more
sure that our code is good and we
can continue implementing new parts
of the system and having always
the assurance that this test will work.
So, how we can reuse this test to
execute for more values?
Well, this is the idea that we will
want to have different values for
executing.
The first attempt that we can do
is using a collection with two
collections inside where we have
the two operands of our test.
So we are going to, in the first
iteration of this collection,
we are going to take the first operand,
the second operand, and their result.
And for each of these triplet,
we are going to execute the assert
and we are going to test that our
zoom is working as we want.
But if we want to have more tests
that reuse the same idea,
we will have to repeat the same
code pattern everywhere.
And also, we will have to repeat
the values that we are given and
the configuration that we are given
to all the tests where we want to
reuse it.
And as we always say,
we don't want to duplicate code.
We don't want to duplicate,
in this case, the loop.
Also, as you see, the complexity
of this test has raised a lot.
We passed from a single line test
to a loop and a collection and values
and this test started gaining complexity
easily.
So what is the solution that we
are proposing in this lecture is
the idea of using parametrized tests.
Basically, a parametrized test is
a test case where we can put from
outside different set of parameters
to execute more and more cases.
Basically, what we are going to
come back is to having our test
method in the same sense that we
had before.
Just in this case, we are going
to replace the constant with instance
variables.
We are going to have a number one,
a second number and the result.
And we are going to sum the two
numbers and compare it with the result.
We are going to define our test
case class extending,
inheriting from parametrized test case.
You should remember that when we
define a test case class,
we extend from test case.
In this case, we are going to use
parametrized test case and we are
going to define the instance variables
that we need for this test.
So once we have the test written
and the instance variable that will
collect our values, we have to give
the different values that we want
to have for these cases.
We are going to come to the class
side of our test class and define
the method testParameters.
These method testParameters will
return a ParametrizedTestMatrix.
Basically, this object is the one
that has the responsibility to contain
all the cases that we are going
to execute.
In this first example,
we are going to add the cases one by one.
You see in this, we are adding the
first case for our test,
where we have the first number will
be a two, the second number will
be a float one, 1.0 and the result
should be a three.
And then we added a second case
with the fractions as they were before.
So we have extended our test cases
with these two cases,
one for the integers and float and
one for the fractions.
If we added more and more cases,
the cases will be added in this method.
Well, what are the benefits of this?
Well, basically that our test continues
being the simplest one that we can
write.
We can reuse this by accessing to
the variables and we can rewrite
different tests.
In this case, we are going to write
a test for testing in a different way,
but we can reuse it.
We should recall, we call this test minus.
And the idea is that we can use
these instance variables with the
different cases in different tests
and reuse them.
So every time we add a new case,
it will affect to all the test method
that we have.
So we can execute our test with
different configurations and we
always add new configurations to
cover more and more cases in a more
clean way than adding it to a
collection.
Let's see another problem,
another variation.
Let's see if we have tests to testing
collections, to testing an object
where we can enclose different objects
inside.
In this case, we are going to write
the simplest one.
We are starting testing first a
collection of the class bag and
we are adding, yes, the string 'a'.
Once we add the string 'a',
we can ask the collection if it
includes this object and we can
ask the collection its size and
it should be one.
We have the assert written for our test.
This test is perfect.
It has exactly what we want,
but the problem is that this test
is limited just to one kind of
collection and one kind of element
inside.
So let's try to do it a little more
generic.
And the first change we can do is
to introduce an instance variable
holding the collectionClass that
we are testing.
We are going to execute this test
with many collection classes.
We are going to create many kinds
of different collections and we
are all testing them with the string
to see if we can put in a string
inside and if the size is correct.
So we do exactly the same.
We have to extend from parametrized
test case and add the instance variable
collectionClass.
Up to here is normal development
as we were doing before.
And the idea now is that we are
going to provide the test parameters
with different cases.
In this case, we are going to say
a little more complex,
but more flexible message to take
a test matrix is that we are going
to say for the selector for the
instance variable that we are going
to access through collectionClass,
we are going to give different options.
In this case, we are going to give set,
bag and OrderedCollection.
What we will do is that it will
run all the tests, first with set,
then with bag and then with
OrderedCollection.
In this case, we have extended our
test case from only testing with
bag to include other kinds of
collections.
But what if we want more?
What if we want also to change the
kind of object that we are storing
in the collection?
In this case, we are only using strings,
but we want to test also with numbers,
other objects and different elements
inside.
So we can test that the collection,
the implementation of collection
can support more than strings.
So let's do exactly the same.
Now we are going to keep the item
as an instance variable and we are
going to create a setter for it.
And we are going to use this instance
variable in the test instead of
the constant value as we had before.
So once we added the new instance
variable and we are using in the test,
we have to declare in the test
parameters that we need to add different
options for this new instance variable.
We do it in the same way that we
have done it before, configuring
the test matrix, the ParametrizedTestMatrix
object with saying that
for the given selector,
in this case, item, we are going
to add three different options.
The number one, the string 'a' and
the character c.
In this case, the test will execute
for all the combinations that we
have in this test matrix will produce
the combinations to execute the
test in all the possible values.
It will take a set and it will test
it with a number one and a string
'a' and a character c.
Then we'll take the bag and we'll
do the same with the three others.
And then we'll take the other collection
doing the same for the three.
So it will execute nine cases.
It will generate the nine possible
cases.
It will run all possible combinations
of these options.
In this case, we'll combine the
three of items and the three of
collectionClass having nine tests
in total.
So as a conclusion, parametrized
tests are handy when we want to
repeat the same test for different
values, when we can generate all
possible values and explore better
the space of our solution.
So we cover more and more cases
and we are safe that our code is
working for more and more cases.
Also, it's a good way of organizing
all these cases, organizing all
these different values and combinations
in a way that is more flexible and
that we can maintain easily in the
future.