Hello, in this sequence,
we will speak about test-driven
development, so we will revisit
testing that we already saw in a
previous lecture.
So the outline of this lecture is
the following.
We will focus on test-driven development
and what it means.
Then, we will exemplify it on a
simple code, and it will allow us
to revisit and to rethink the notion
of testing.
So, write test first.
Yes, the idea is to write the test
before writing the business code
or the model code.
So there is a famous quote from
Martin Fowler, which is the following:
"Whenever you attempt to type something
into a print statement or debugger
expression, write it as a test instead."
And this is exactly the essence
of test-driven development.
But in fact, TDD is about the flow,
the workflow.
You should work in a specific manner
that is in different forms,
that comes in different flavors,
and this is one of these flavors here.
So usually you start by loading code,
you start here.
And then, when you load code,
it could be one of your packages
that you are working on,
or it could be an external package.
You will run all the tests,
and if they are green,
it's okay, but if one of the tests
is broken, is red or yellow,
you should fix the test first and
then rerun all the tests.
You will rerun everything,
you are there, okay?
And when everything is green,
perfect, you did it correctly,
and you might commit your code,
and perhaps you can take a break.
So this is the next step.
Or now that you've committed your
code and everything is green,
you can clean or refactor your code,
and you will rerun all the tests
again to see if you didn't introduce
a side effect that broke something.
And now, we are here.
At this point, all the tests are green,
and you want to introduce a new
test or a new feature in your code,
and you will start by writing the
test first, or modify an existing test.
And then, you will run this test.
Probably, it will be red the first time,
but it might be green if the
functionality already exists in
the code base.
But if it is red, if it is wrong,
it means that you need to write the code.
So now it comes to writing the code
of the functionality,
and then you will rerun the test
until it is green, and you will
work like that in this loop.
I write the code, I test,
and if the test is not green,
I write more code, etc.,
etc.
Once this loop is finished,
so you have a green test,
so now it's time for refactoring
your code.
So it means that you can refactor
your code, you can clean the code.
And once it's done, you should rerun
all the tests.
And this is an important step.
And when all tests are green,
again, you can commit.
So this is the workflow that you
should do when you are doing test-driven
development.
Let's see this on an example.
So imagine you just created a ‘Counter‘
class, which is completely empty.
And you will write a test,
so I create a ‘Counter‘ test class.
Inside this class, I added a method,
testCount, and in this method,
I can test the basic functionality
of a ‘Counter‘.
So I will set up the context,
‘Counter‘ new.
I could isolate this expression
in a setup method of the test,
but here I put everything in the
test method.
And then, I can exercise,
I will set the ‘Counter‘ value here
to 10, and here I will assert that
the ‘Counter‘ value is correctly set,
is 10.
So now, first, what I should do
when I wrote the test,
I should execute the test.
And most probably, it will be red.
This is normal because we just defined
the ‘Counter‘ class, but it's completely
empty, and there are no accessor
inside this class.
So, so far, so good.
The test is red.
So now, it's time to implement the
functionality, and then you will
rerun the test, and you will work
like that until the test is green.
Once the test is green,
you should run, you must run all
the tests of the system,
because you might introduce some
side effects while coding on the
code base, and you probably broke
or you might break existing tests,
or perhaps this new functionality
broke some code, or either all tests
are now wrong because their new
functionality is it's completely
different.
In both cases, you should now fix
all of them.
This is the basis of TDD.
So now that all tests are green,
it's a good time to clean and refactor
your code.
And when you are okay with your code,
you should rerun all the tests and
then you can commit, because you
will commit a completely clean code
base.
What's the point of writing tests first?
You specify what you want in tests.
So the important part is that when
you are writing a test,
you are writing an executable
specification.
And this specification is,
while you are writing the test,
you are describing what you want,
what you want the code to do.
And then, when the test is written,
it means that you can build or assemble
existing functionality of the code
base to build your code.
Another good part of writing tests
first is that you are your first client,
meaning that you will exercise your API,
so API, this is Application Programming
Interface, before all others.
So it means that you are designing
your API and using your API before
it is even implemented.
So it will be better.
You are exercising it.
And of course, you will exercise
it in a clear context,
the context of the test,
and you can debug it directly.
As a conclusion, TDD is a powerful
feature.
It means that you are writing tests
first.
It makes sure that you will write
a more solid code base with fewer
regression because you are re-exercising
all tests again and again.
And you are your first client.
So you will design cleaner API.
By the way, do not miss the next
lecture on Xtrem TDD,
which is the TDD flavor that we
are using in the Pharo community.