Hello and welcome to this lecture.
In this lecture, we are going to
talk about Xtreme Test Driven
Development.
The outline of this lecture will
be the presentation of Xtreme Test
Driven Development.
Basically, it is a reversion of
TDD but with steroids.
We are going to do much more and
win much more.
We are going to see how this new
technique is integrated in a live
programming environment and how
to get the best of it.
We are going to show how the smart
tools in our programming environment
provide us with the support for
doing Xtreme TDD.
And also we are going to see how
to do it (by real).
The idea of Xtreme TDD is to always
keep the flow, to never break the flow.
We want to write a test,
execute the test and when we have
an error, we are going to fix the
error in the debugger.
We are going to define methods,
modify methods on the debugger.
The idea is that we can continue
always executing the test until
we have a green test.
That is our main objective,
having always green tests.
We are going to start with a really
simple example.
But this example will give us a
lot of space to apply the technique
and will show us how powerful it is.
There is nothing simpler in this
example.
It's just that it has little code.
We are going to implement a simple
counter.
We are going to focus on the process,
on the different steps that we are
going to do.
And we are showing that this can
be done in all our daily work.
We are going to start with an empty
package, with an empty package in Pharo.
In this empty package,
first we are going to do is to create
a test.
The test is our main unit in the
Xtreme TDD.
We work always creating first a test.
We are going to create an empty
test case class or we can start
from an existing test case class
where we are going to add a new test.
In this case, we are creating an
empty one.
So we start writing our first test.
Remember that always in our test,
we are going to have an action that
we are going to execute.
And the most important is that we
are going to have some asserts that
will validate that that action is
correct.
In this case, we are writing a simple
test where we are creating a new
object of the class counter.
And we are going to send the message
count 22.
So once we send this message,
the actual value inside the counter
that we are accessing with the message
count will return 22.
And this is our test.
This is what we want that our program
to do.
We are going to write this in our
class browser, and we are going
to see that already, when we write
this code, the counter class name,
the name of the counter class in
our code is marked different because
this class does not exist.
We didn't create it yet.
And we are going to compile this
method as it is.
So the system already knows that
the class does not exist.
So when we compile the method,
we are going to define a new class.
It says clearly that there is a
known variable, in this case,
the class counter, and we are going
to define it a new class,
so we can start implementing our
program.
Once we select to define a new class,
we see that we are offered with
a template or a simple class definition.
In this case, for following the
Xtreme TDD as we should,
we are going to create it in the
most simple default class that we have.
We are going to create our class
counter as a subclass of object
and we are not going to add any
instance variable as they will emerge
as we are making our test green.
Remember that all the objective
of Xtreme TDD is to have green test.
We are going to implement the code
that is necessary to have our test
green.
So we click on OK and we are going
to generate the class.
We see that now, in our browser,
we have our class with the test
and we are also having our new class
counter.
And now, the code in our method
is painted correctly.
It has the nice color showing that
the class exists in the system.
So we have defined the test,
but still we didn't execute it.
Remember that in Xtreme TDD,
we were creating the test,
executing it and then working out
to make the test green.
So what we are going to do is run
the test.
The easiest way to run a single
test case is to click on the little
ball that we have next to the test
method.
We are going to click there and,
of course, we are going to have
a debugger.
This is really cool.
The debugger is your friend.
Don't panic.
Don't close the debugger.
The debugger is the most powerful
tool in Xtreme TDD.
We need to work with the debugger.
The first thing in a debugger is
always reading the message,
reading the problem.
We have to read because if not,
we don't understand what is happening.
So in this case, it's clearly saying
that an instance of counter did
not understand the message count colon.
Why?
Because we have never implemented
any method in the class counter.
So any instance of counter will
never have this method.
And we see in the debugger important
information that we see the message
that is trying to send and where
in the code it's sending this message.
So what we are going to do without
closing the debugger is to create
the method on the fly.
So we can continue implementing
our solution and making our test green.
So we are going to click on the
button Create to create a new method.
In this case, in the class counter
that is the one that is missing
the method count colon.
Once we click in the button,
the system will create a new method
for us and it will install it in
the counter class.
Also, we'll restart the execution
in the debugger and will bring us
to the execution point where this
method should be executed.
We see that the implementation that
the debugger provides us is basically
a default implementation that says well,
we have a method that will receive
an integer and it should be implemented.
We don't have the actual code.
So we came here and we are going
to write the code that we want to
happen or we want to be executed
when this method is executed.
In this case, what we want to do
is take the value of the argument
and store it in an instance variable
of name count.
We are going to write the assignation
here and before writing before saving
the method we can see again that
count is marked in red showing off
that we don't have this instance
variable.
But we don't need to panic,
we don't need to go away,
we don't need to close the debugger.
We are going to save the method
and once we save the method with
command s or the right button Accept,
a new pop-up will appear asking
us what we want to do with the unknown
variable count.
Remember always to read the messages,
always to read what the system is
proposing us before closing and
panicking.
It's so easy, just reading and following
and doing what we want.
In this case, as there is an unknown
variable we want to declare it as
a new instance variable and we select
the second option.
In this case, the tool,
the debugger will compile the new
method and we create the missing
instance variable.
And now we see that our method is
correctly colored, showing us that
the variable exists and is defined
in the class count.
Well, we have our method correctly
written, we have the variable that
has been created with some little
clicks and now what we have to do
is to continue executing our test.
For doing so, we can tell our debugger
to proceed and continue executing
our code.
We click on the button 'Proceed' and
the execution of the test will continue.
Let's recall what happened at this
point.
We see that the system when there
is an error show us the ability
to create a new method for us.
When we click on Create a New Method,
the system will create a new method
for us, will remove all the error
in the message not understood and
will replace it in the stack in
the call stack with our method just
to be executed.
We can then edit and modify or not
the method and then we can continue
the execution of our test.
Like this, we are going to start
adding the methods and the instance
variable and the classes and all
the elements that are needed for
making our test green.
This process allows us to keep always
a green test or our objective is
always to have a green test.
To talk a little more in technical
detail, when we create a new method,
the system OK will create the new
method that is easy to see because
it's what we asked, but also will
remove from the stack all the error
of the message not understood and
will replace the call to the error
with the call to our new method.
When the system propose us a new method,
it will be created using the message
'self shouldBeImplemented'.
This message has two important
responsibility.
First, 'shouldBeImplemented' is just
an exception that will be raised
so the debugger will stop again
and we can continue editing our method.
But also is really good because
it's a documentation that this method
has not been yet implemented.
So if we find in our class method
that sending should be implemented,
is a clear point to see what is
the next thing to do or the next
thing to implement.
So if we continue executing our example,
if we return to the moment that
I click on 'Proceed', we can see that
this error will continue this cycle
of executing, finding an error and
modifying the methods and continue
will execute because that is the
procedure in Xtreme TDD.
And we will find that in this case
we are going to have another error,
but this one is that the instance
of counter did not understand count.
This is a different method and this
is a different message,
but is the same idea.
We are going to create it again
clicking on 'Create', but in this case,
the debugger will help us a lot
because it will realize that the
method count follows the convention
that it is named as an instance
variable.
It follows the convention of being
a getter of an instance variable.
So it proposes us with a better
initial proposal for the new method.
In this case, just implemented it
as return of the count instance
variable.
If this method that is proposed
by the debugger is good enough we
can always click on 'Proceed',
but if it's not we can have here
the moment to modify it and change
it and change the code that we want
for our method count.
Once we click on 'Proceed',
in this case because it's a good
solution, it's a good method for
the implementation for count just
right on the instance variable,
we will see that now our test is
green and we can be happy about that.
We can have green test and that
makes us happy because we know that
this little functionality that we
have implemented in our program
is working.
This is one cycle of Xtreme TDD.
What we have done is run all the tests.
When this, all the tests are green,
it's important that all the tests
are green, we are ready to commit.
We are ready to save our work and
put a point that we can always return
to.
Once we commit and we are safe that
our code is stored correctly,
we can write a new test testing
another functionality of our program
and this test, of course,
will start being read will start
producing errors and then we are
going to fix the minimal to make
it green.
Why Xtreme TDD is so powerful and
why we are talking about it in this
lecture is because when we are doing
Xtreme TDD, we have more information
than when we are just developing.
We are not guessing about the context
when we are coding the methods because
basically, we have the context in
our debugger.
We can see the method that we are
executing.
We can see the object that we are using,
all the arguments, all the objects
that are accessible and we can have
all the information of the context.
This is a much better context.
As I say, we have all access to
the instance state that we are
executing, we are accessing the
objects that we have access to and
we don't need to think a lot because
the debugger is helping us with
the correct context.
And also, in a live programming
environment, we can always interact
with all the objects that we have
in the debugger.
Like this, it's quite easy to find
what is the better solution and
the minimal code that we need to
write to make our test green again.
The idea is that our tests are always
guiding us really guiding and driving
us to find the nice and good solution.
When you are working with Xtreme
TDD that is one of the tools one
of the techniques that we do all
the time, the recommendations we
can do for you is always try to
get an object as fast as possible,
is the easy way because having an
object give us context about the
problem, context about the solution
and give us a better way of thinking.
Always try to write a test that
test the scenario that you are using,
that you are developing.
Remember that the test as we are
writing unit test should test a
little part of our program and it
will always focus on a little scenario.
And the idea is that we make that
scenario work and we make that test
green.
Of course, the idea is that we do
a cycle of Xtreme TDD and then another,
and another and another,
we loop.
Remember, we write a test,
we make it green, we commit and
then we repeat until we have all
our cases covered with tests.