- Hello everybody.
In this lecture, I will talk about
shared variables.
This is one of the four lectures
that is really specific to Pharo.
That's why we call it a code idiom.
In this lecture, what are the goals?
We will revisit the concept of shared
variables - ClassVariables in Smalltalk
jargon, or SharedVariables in Pharo
jargon - and think about the scope
of sharing and what it means.
We will have two other lectures
that are somehow related to this
lecture, plus the flyweight design
pattern.
Let's start with the basic things first.
Instance variables are just local
to one object.
There is nothing new here,
this is something that you should
have learned in any object-oriented
lecture.
I don't want to spend time,
but this means that if you have
an object and it has a value,
it is specific to this,
and I have another one that will
have a value.
For example, imagine that this is
a rectangle here and I have a height,
the class defines the variable,
and each object has its own value.
If I modify this value,
if I empty it, then only this object
is impacted and not this one.
So, nothing new normally.
This is just to remind you of this.
Now, in addition, we have shared
variables.
Shared variables are shared by all
the instances of a class and in
addition to a hierarchy.
We will look at that.
This means that there is only one
value that all the instances of
this hierarchy will share.
So, if you modify one,
all the instances get impacted.
Usually, the shared variable is
initialized at load time because
they use lazy initialization sometimes.
If you don't know what lazy
initialization is, there is a lecture
in one of the modules.
But usually, the shared variable
initializes at load time in a class
initialize method.
This is what I said: in Smalltalk,
this is called ClassVariables,
and in Pharo, we call that
SharedVariables.
We call that SharedVariables because
they are shared.
Let's look at an example.
If we look at the class `Color`,
which you can see in Pharo,
the class `Color` inherits from
`Object`.
It has `rgb`, which means that each
color has a red, green,
and blue element, and `alpha`.
But you have also constants that
are basically defined as
`sharedVariables`.
Let's look at it.
Visually, what does it mean?
It means that I have the class `Color`
with the instance variables `rgb`
and `alpha`.
This class `Color` also defines
shared variables.
These ones are shared and what you
see is that the metaclass,
the `Color` class, has an initialized
method that will initialize the
value of this shared variable.
All the objects or instances of
the subclass of `Color` are using
this value.
And now, once the class declares
that it defines a shared variable,
then we can use it either in the
class part, like here,
or in the instance part,
like here.
This means that `privateBlue`,
for example, is `rgb bitAnd` on a mask.
If we look at the code,
for example, in these kinds of `set`
methods - `setRed`, `green` and
`blue` - we get an instance variable
here, and here we can directly access
the shared variable that contains
certain information so we can do
the `bitAnd` and `bitShift` and
(trickery) for the encoding of the
colors.
Similarly, this is what I show in
the UML diagram, the initialized
method on the class side will just
set the constants that are used
by the compiler once and for all.
Let's take another example:
String.
The class `String` defines one shared
variable which is called
`CaseSensitiveOrder`.
This means that if you want to compare
strings, you can say,
"Do you care about the case or not?"
And what you see is that in the
instance methods, the class `String`
uses this shared variable,
and of course, the `String` class,
the metaclass, initialize.
So, it will initialize the `Type` class,
`TypeTable` - I don't know exactly
what it is.
But I wanted to show you that this
shared variable that is used in
the instance method is initialized
at the class level.
What you can also see is that `Symbol`,
which is a subclass of `String`,
can use this shared variable at
the class level, but it also could
be at the instance level.
This is how the class `String` is
defined.
It used several shared variables.
I don't want to go into detail,
but this is just to show you that
aspect.
Here, this wasn't on the UML,
but if you look at `ByteSymbol`,
for example, which is a subclass
of `Symbol`, which is a subclass
of `String`, you have the instance
method that will use directly the
shared variable.
In the end, shared variables are
accessible from instance methods
and class methods of the complete
hierarchy and the subclasses of
the hierarchy from the class that
defines the shared variable.
This is what we have here in the
`Symbol` class, on the class side.
Then we can use this.
So, this is completely transparent
for you, and after you just use it.
It's like your constant gets access
everywhere from within this hierarchy.
There is an implication or there
are implications.
There is a difference between shared
variables and instance variables
of the metaclass.
Look at this.
If I have `BorderStyle` that inherits
from `Object` and defines a `#Default`
shared variable, this is not the
same as saying that I can have an
instance variable of the metaclass.
What is the difference?
Let's look at that.
This is a bit subtle.
When you use a shared variable,
there is only one instance of
`BorderStyle` for the complete
sub-hierarchy.
So, if I drew it, it means that
I have `BorderStyle` and here there
will be one instance of `aBorderStyle`
because the `#Default` is for the
singleton pattern.
And all this hierarchy,
which can be quite deep,
will share this class variable.
There is only one in the system.
Now, in this case, it means that
I have `BorderStyle` - let me draw
it like that - and I have one instance
of the class.
This means that I have `BorderStyle`,
which is an instance of the
`BorderStyle` class, and here I
have `#Default`.
What does it mean?
It means that every class has its
own instance because the metaclass
describes the class.
So, this class is an instance of
this metaclass, which means that
this class has an instance variable
value that will be specific to this one.
Let's draw it like this is an object
and it has a value.
You remember at the beginning,
I said that every object can have
its own value.
This is the same for…
within all your hierarchy,
those guys are classes,
but I drew them as rounds to stress
that they are objects.
So, every class in the hierarchy,
and this one won't have the same
visual effect, but this class,
that class, and this one has different
values in the instance variable
`#Default` that they have because
they are objects.
`BorderStyle` is an instance of
the `BorderStyle` class,
so it has the value of the instance
variable of the metaclass.
If you want to check,
there is a lecture on the Pharo
MOOC on metaclasses, and this is
really interesting if you want to
deeply understand this mechanism.
But what you should remember is
that there is a difference between
a shared variable and an instance
variable of the metaclass.
There is only one shared variable
for the complete hierarchy and one
per class of the hierarchy.
So, this means that they have different
scopes and share semantics.
As a conclusion, pay attention when
you modify a shared variable because
you will impact many objects.
What is interesting is that shared
variables can be used to perform
different sharing optimization,
and we will present some of them
in the following lecture.