Welcome to this lecture on sharing.
In fact, during this lecture,
I would like to present yet another
variation on sharing.
If you remember what we saw previously
is that we have shared variables.
Shared variables or static variables
allows to share an information or
an object between all the instances
of a class and the subclasses.
We also saw that we could mix instance
variable and shared variable to
support a solution that will offer
sharing by default and instance-based
customization when we want.
And there is also a design pattern
flyweight that will go back to this
topic.
And in this lecture, we will present
a variation that was taken from
the Bloc graphical framework.
So basically, in the Bloc graphical
framework, you have a ‘BlElement‘.
So this is the really basic graphical
element.
It has many properties,
like ‘background‘, ‘border‘,
‘clipChildren‘, ‘elevation‘,
‘geometry‘, ‘compositingMode‘,
‘visibility‘, ‘opacity‘…
So plenty of them.
How those properties are managed?
They are managed this way.
In fact, the properties are grouped
in an instance of ‘BlElementVisuals‘,
with an S, which is strange from
a domain perspective.
And you see that for example,
when I ask the border of an element,
the methods in the class ‘BlElement‘
will delegate to the visual instance.
The same with 'clipChildren' and this
is the same for all the properties
that we showed previously.
So in fact, these Default visuals,
they are shared between all the
instances.
Now in Bloc, the property can be
modified.
You have an element, it should be
displayed, it should be clipped
or things like that, you can do
it dynamically.
So in the design that I will show,
the developer really wanted to see
if they can support property
modification without paying the
price of adding an instance variable
for all the shared default.
In fact, they wanted to see:
can we have the same than with the
mixing sharing lecture that we saw
before, but without having to have
this extra instance variable.
What you see here is that this is
the overview of the design.
So you have ‘BlElementVisuals‘,
which is the super class of the system.
It defines shared variable here
and there and multiples of them.
And then you have two subclasses,
‘BlDefaultVisuals‘ and
‘BLCustomVisuals‘.
And this one will be shared by default.
And based on the modification,
when we modify a property,
it will create an instance of this
one and this is what we will see.
So as I said, you see here,
you have the super class
‘BlElementVisuals‘.
It has some shared variable,
DefaultBackground, DefaultBorder,
DefaultGeometry, DefaultVisibility.
The 'defaultBackground' method just
returned the shared variable.
And then some other methods are
abstract and the subclass will define
them.
Now the ‘DefaultVisuals‘ will basically
use a singleton pattern to initialize
the visuals.
So this means that each instance
of the Bl classes will have via
the visual instance variable access
to the unique instance of the Default.
So this way, all the shared variables,
all the shared states,
the shared properties are shared
among all the instances of the class
‘BlElement‘.
And now, what you have is you have
for example the accessor like 'background'
that will access the default value
that accesses…
returns the shared variable.
Now there is a catch in the system.
This is that when you want to modify
a property, in fact you don't want
to modify the property of the complete
system, of all the instances,
because suddenly, all the ‘BlElements‘
that were hidden could be visible.
And you just want to have one of those.
So since they cannot do instance,
or they can do, but since they don't
do it the same way as in the previous
lecture, what they do here is that
the setter will create an instance
of the other class.
You remember there was this hierarchy.
I showed the hierarchy with the
two classes with this one that was
shared.
And at this moment, this setter
is basically creating an instance
of this class.
And this is what we are doing here.
So this means that when the system
invokes the background setter,
it will not modify the shared variable
or the shared instance.
It will create a new instance and
then modify the property of this
new instance.
This is an instance that is made
to be modified, in fact.
So this means that at the level
of the 'CustomVisuals' classes,
we will have instance variable for
geometry, border, background,
outskirts, effect.
And then, in that case,
we have a normal setter.
What it means, it means that for
a specific instance, an instance
of ‘BLCustomVisuals‘ will be stored
in the place of the singleton.
And like that, it will keep the
accumulation.
So this means that what you see
is that as soon as I got one setter,
a new instance of custom will be
put in the visual instance variable
and then all the following methods
will just continue to access the
instance variable multiple times.
So what I want to say here is that
this happens only once per instance.
Because if you change the color
or if you change the 'outskirts',
that will be the same.
An instance of BLCustomVisuals will
be created, and then in that case,
this is this setter that will be
executed.
So now what is really…
there is a catch in fact,
is that in this design,
this design kind of hijacked the
setter semantic.
Because usually, as a programmer,
I don't expect to have to store
the result of a setter,
typically.
If I don't know, I will write something
like that and the system will not
change and will not behave the right
way.
And this is because on the
'BLDefaultVisuals', the setter returns
this new instance.
So here, this is really returning
the new instance.
So that's why I really need to have
this assignment.
And this is really surprising when
you first encounter it because it's
always strange to ask ourselves,
"Oh, why do I need to store the
result of a setter?
Because normally I just modify the
receiver." But no, in this design,
let me go back here.
You see, here I'm returning a new
instance for a setter.
And then, in that case,
I have to store it.
Now we can ask ourselves what is
the difference with the previous
design that I showed in the other
lecture, where we had two variables,
a shared variable and an instance
variable with the same name.
If you remember, we initialized
the table and we could share the
table by default via the instance
variable.
Or we could copy the table in the
instance variable and in that case
have instance-specific behavior.
In fact, first, in this design,
they grouped the different values
into a single object.
So this means that ‘BLElementVisuals‘
and 'BLCustomization', or 'Custom',
I don't remember, 'Visuals',
they are a group of objects.
But from that perspective,
they are nearly similar to the type
table because the type table is
also a group of dictionaries.
But here this is not just a table.
This is a group of attributes.
Now with this design,
you are not forced to have this
instance variable.
So this means that you can remove
the instance variable from the solution.
But we still have the instance-based
and sharing.
So that's why this is an interesting
alternative to what we show in the
previous lecture.
Now, as a conclusion and analysis,
the question that we can ask ourselves
is that is this complexity needed?
I mean, is it worth to really hijack
the default setter patterns?
It could be.
Now, when I look at the design,
I was always thinking,
okay, is it so costly to have this
extra instance variable per instance
so that we could have the shared
by default and the instance specific?
I don't know what it means.
It means that memory analysis should
be done.
If you have millions of objects,
then maybe, yes, getting one instance
more for multiple millions of objects,
then it means that you will consume
space for nothing.
Just in case one object would not
share the default.
Then there is also the question of:
are the default well chosen?
Because maybe you will have a
statistical distribution that is
completely not good because all
your objects, they will say,
"No, I'm always a visible object.
Do not hide me." So in that case,
it should not be the default.
As this is a message that is implicit
in this MOOC, this is that design
decisions, they always should take
into account the context.
And usually, it can happen that
in your software, you will have
a design decision at a given moment
in time of your software and then
you will have a new requirement
or a new scenario that will make
you change the design and consider,
"Okay, the decision that I took
previously was working well at that
time and now I have to change it."
So this is also why, from that
perspective, you should also invest
in tests because the tests,
they will let you change your design
and make your system evolve.