Hello, in this short lecture,
we'll discuss about magic literals.
This is small numbers that you may
introduce in all your codes,
but that are important in fact.
So the idea is to think about setters
and getters, of course,
and customization of these little
numbers or little constants in your
code.
Let's have a look at this case study.
For example, here, in this code,
in the Node class, I have a specific
number there.
And the idea is how can I provide
a mean for programmers to change
this number in subclasses or outside
of this code, how can I provide
a way to customize this value.
So the simple solution could be
to introduce a new instance variable,
`percent`.
And now, use it directly in the code.
And then, I need to provide an
initialization for this variable.
So in the `initialize` method,
I can directly `initialize` the
`percent` value to 55.
It was the value that was there before.
I can also add a setter method.
And now, what I have is that I provide
a way for clients to directly customize
this value from the external of
the subject.
I can create a new node and set
this value to 55 or 70.
But how can we provide a way for
subclasses to provide a default
value for this percentage?
And the idea is to define a hook
one time again.
So I can provide a default `percent`
and I can refactor now my initialization
of my object and say,
okay, the default value is computed
by a self-send.
And the good properties of this
solution is that now in subclasses,
I can override the value by redefining
the `initialize`.
I can override just the default
value by overriding the default
`percent`, but also clients.
It means that code that will instantiate
this class can use the setter to
define its own value and I can also
reuse the default value if I want.
So this is a really nice solution
that combines both the initialization,
the setter and the default hook
for the default value.
As a conclusion, what is important
and the key message is that you
should not add code constants in
your code.
You should extract them at least
in hooks and then you should let
clients customize these values in
setters or redefine default values
in hooks in subclasses.
Another solution would be to use
shared pool, for example,
in Pharo, because it allows you
to reuse these values among the
hierarchy.