Hi.
In this lecture, we are going to
discuss about the flyweight design
pattern.
The objective of this short lecture
is to understand the flyweight pattern
and to study two case studies.
First, we are going to talk about
symbols in Pharo and the second
one is `Colors`, so how we can use
flyweights in the case of `Color`.
So what is the objective of the
flyweight pattern?
So the intent if you read the book
is to use sharing to support a large
number of fine-grained objects
efficiently.
So what does it mean is that sometimes
we are going to create a lot of
objects that are similar,
for example characters.
So in the character 1 and the character
2 and we are going to reuse them
all over.
So why to create many different
characters when we can actually
reuse them because the character
1 is going to be always the same
kind of object.
So the flyweight pattern will actually
tell us to create, for example,
a map where we are going to store
or cache those well-known objects
to be able to only create them once,
store them and reuse them.
So at the end, it's actually just
a cache.
Let's see an example with the symbol
instances in Pharo.
So what is a symbol in Pharo?
A symbol is like a string.
It will behave as a string.
So we are going to be able to
concatenate symbols and so on,
but they will be unique.
So in that sense, we are going to
be able to compare symbols using
the identity operator.
So two symbols, regardless of when
and how they were created,
if they have the same number of
characters and the same characters,
they will be identical.
So that means that the system is
going to ensure that when creating
a symbol, we are going to reuse
the same symbol that existed before.
One of the objectives of reusing
symbols is that we are going to
reuse memory footprints.
So instead of allocating a lot of
different symbols that actually
have the same value, we are going
to reuse them when they have the
same value.
So in this case, when we are going
to use symbols, we can be sure that
they are referring to the same object.
So that is what this piece of code
ensures.
So how does it work in the case of Pharo?
So if we check how symbols are created,
there is in the symbol class,
there is a method that is intern.
So that takes as parameter string
or symbol.
What this method is going to do
is to check if this string or symbol
is already in the internal flyweight
implementation.
And if it is not there,
it will create a corresponding symbol
and install it in the table.
So first, we check if that symbol
or string is already internal.
If it is not there, we're going
to add it into the table.
Now the symbol implementation here
is a symbol, it's an implementation
of the flyweight pattern that will
create new objects dynamically.
So we don't know all the potential
symbols that we're going to use
beforehand.
So that is why, every time that
we need a new symbol,
we need to be able to support the
creation and addition of new symbols
in the internal table.
A separate case study is the case
of `Colors`.
So for example, in Pharo,
we have the UITheme class that
represents the themes,
so for example, the dark theme or
the light theme, and you can change
how Pharo looks like.
And the UITheme is going to actually
create a lot of `Colors`.
So it will, for example,
dark theme is going to create a
lot of `Colors` in the dark with
dark nuance or the light theme will
create whiter or similar `Colors`.
We have solarized themes that will
be more yellowish and so on.
And every time that we are going
to paint something in the screen,
we're going to use a lot of `Colors`.
So the question is, do we create lot,
thousands of similar `Colors` or not?
And so, if we look at the code of
UITheme, we see, for example,
we have this kind of method,
so background `Color` and text `Color`
that say, okay, I'm going to use
the `Color` white as the background
`Color`, and I'm going to use a
`Color` black as a text `Color`.
So this is for example,
the case of a default theme that
will be white.
The question that we can ask ourselves
is, should we turn `Color` into
a flyweight?
Because if we see the code as we
had it before, we have background
`Color` that is returning `Color` white.
So in this method `Color` white
always returning a new `Color` or
is going to reuse the same white
`Color`?
So the thing that we should take
into account to decide if we should
intern an object or not,
is first the cost of interning it.
So how expensive would it be to
add it to a table or to hash this
object to look for it in an efficient
way?
Also, one thing to see is that,
for example, in this case,
having a flyweight will save us
from allocating a lot of different
objects that represent the same value,
but it will not save us from having
a lot of requests.
So if we have here our flyweight
that has our white `Color` and our
red `Color`, still we could have
a client.
So this one will have one of each,
but the client can make maybe dozens
of requests.
So here, if we make a flyweight
for `Colors`, we are not solving
the cause of the problem,
which is actually a client that
is requesting dozens of times for
the same object.
So we need to check if actually
the cost in the execution time comes
from actually allocating objects
here or from actually a bad client
that is making a bad number of requests.
Also, some other questions that
we could ask ourselves.
So do we need to create always different
`Colors` dynamically or the number
of `Colors` will be fixed statically?
In that case, for example,
we could think about the table of
fixed `Colors` that we can reuse,
or otherwise we need to think about
the system, like in the symbols,
that will be able to grow dynamically
and where we are going to be able
to add new `Colors` dynamically.
The other thing that actually is
super important is that we are going
to be able to cache objects that
are value objects.
So objects do not need to change
or need to be immutable once in
the flyweight.
Otherwise, if we are going to be
able to mutate the white object
and turn it into a green object,
then all the users of the white
object will suddenly be a green object,
which will be a string.
So we're going to use a flyweight
to be able to return `Colors` to
a client without creating them
endlessly.
So that means that the flyweight
will save us from allocating objects.
So it will have less allocations.
We could implement a flyweight as,
for example, a palette of `Colors`,
which at the end is just a cache
at the level of the domain.
So we're going to provide a domain
object that is, for example,
a palette of `Colors` that will
somehow manage two things at the
same time.
First, provide a domain representation
for something that is useful.
For example, a palette of objects
that has different `Color` for
particular usage, like,
for example, the UITheme.
And at the same time,
it will serve as a cache to avoid
allocation.
So the flyweight is at the end,
just the case of a domain cache.
So what are the possible limitations
of such a palette implementation?
First, we can think about implicit
`Colors`.
So here, for example,
we can compare `Color` red,
darker, darker against self
`selectedBackgroundColor`.
So here, what we see on the left
piece of code is that we have a
`Color` red that if implemented
as a flyweight, it will return us
always the same red `Color`.
However, when we're asking darker,
darker to that `Color`,
that will create new objects,
new darker `Colors` every time.
So darker is a message that given
a `Color`, it will return a new
`Color` that is slightly different
from the receiver.
So here we will return a darker,
darker red.
We need to take care that our darker
methods or our modification methods
also goes through the flyweight
in order to respect the pattern.
Otherwise the darker,
darker methods are not under our
control.
And then, we are going to have the
same problem as before,
but now these methods are escaping
the flyweight.
Another thing is that just saying
`Color` red, darker, darker all
over our code is not actually
representing the domain problem.
So instead we could have,
for example, a method
`selectedBackgroundColor`, as in here,
that will return a `Color` red,
darker, darker, but it will also
give us a point of interception
where we will be able to cache the
`Color` that we're creating.
Now we have to really take care
of this because patterns like this
could be useful to creating `Colors`
as such, but they could be a bad
design practice when used wrongly.
As a conclusion, you can implement
a flyweight pattern to be sure that
you have unique objects and that
you're limiting the memory footprint
of the creation of such objects.
Be careful that the flyweight will
help you to limit memory footprint,
but it will not help you to reduce
the number of requests made to that
flyweight.
So be careful that you need to better
fix the cause than the consequences
sometimes.
So sometimes you will need to,
for example, profile your application
to understand when the problem is
in the allocation of objects or
in the client of those allocations.