Hello, welcome to this lecture.
In this presentation,
we are going to introduce the idea
of `TypeObject`.
The goal for this presentation is
to introduce the difference between
having information for a set of objects,
a family of objects, and some specific
for each of them.
We are going to see that this is
another way of sharing the information,
and we are going finally to introduce
`TypeObject`.
Let's start with an example.
Imagine that we have a collection
of cactus, and we have a family
of cactus of different kinds.
We will have different species of
cactus, but we are going to have
different cactus of each of these
species.
So we are going to have information
that is depending for each of the
plants and for each of the families.
We are going to have here the difference
between having information for each
of the elements, for each of the
individuals in our collection and
the description of all of them.
Because for each of them,
we can have different flowers,
different colors, different pest attack,
different dates of planting and
collecting.
And this information is different
from each of the individual plants,
but we are going to have common
information for each of the species.
Still, we are going to have,
as I say, common information for
all the plants of a given species.
For example, we are going to have
the name, the type, the origin,
and all the information that we
can have from them.
Let's see another example to make
it clear.
If we have a system to handle video
rental, we are going to have the
difference between each physical
movie and the movie itself.
We are going to have each object
representing a BluRay and a specific
instance of a BluRay.
And we are going to see there,
for example, if the BluRay is scratched
or if the box is broken.
And then we are going to have
information about the movie itself.
In this case, how we can implement
this dichotomy of having information
that is common to many objects and
information that is specific of
each instance?
Well, we can implement this by two
different solutions.
The first solution is that we can
have all the information in a given
class, in a given object.
So we can have in the instance of
the movie or in the instance of
the cactus, all the information
from the family and from itself,
or we can have them separate.
Let's see the first alternative.
Let's put them together all in a
single instance, in a single object.
So we will have in the same object
all the common information.
We are going to have the information,
for example, for the video,
we are going to have the information
if the box is okay, if this is scratched
or not.
But also, we are going to have the
title of the movie, the actors in
the movie, and all the information
that is common to all the instances.
The problem with this is that we
will not be able to change this
information dynamically in two senses.
One is that we cannot add new
information or we cannot change
the type of the movie.
We cannot say that now,
this movie is one or other.
And also our instance,
we are going to get really big because
we start having all the information
related to this movie.
Moreover, we are going to have
duplicated information in all instances.
For example, if we have,
again, the same example about movies,
if we have two objects,
two instances representing two different
BluRays of a single movie,
I don't know the movie Rambo III,
we are going to have the same duplicated
information about the actors,
about the movie, about the release
date and common information duplicated
in both objects.
So if we have to modify them because
we have to fix some information on this,
we are going to modify all the
instances.
And also, we have duplication of
this information.
So the idea is to introduce the
concept of `TypeObject`.
In `TypeObject`, we are going to
describe in a single object the
description of our initial object.
For example, we are going to separate
the `plant` and its `plantDescription`.
What we are going to put in each
of these objects, we are going to
have two different objects,
is that we are going to have in
the `plant` side all the information
that is specific to this `plant`.
And we are going to have,
for example, there the position,
what is in our collection physically
or the date we planted it or a lot
of the information that is specific
to this `plant`.
And then, in the description,
we are going to put the information
that is common to all the plants
of this same species.
We are going to have,
for example, the scientific name
of the species, the kind of species,
the origin of the species,
what are the specific features of
this family of plants.
In this case, we are going to share
the description between many instances.
We are going to have different objects
`plant`, that represent different
cacti in our collection.
And all of them will share the same
description representing the species
of our plants.
We are going to gather all the
description-specific properties
in a single object.
That is the objective of the
`TypeObject`, having an object that
describes the common information
of many of them.
In this way, we don't have repeated
information.
We don't have information in each
of the instances, but the common one,
we pass it all together in a single
point.
Remember that having a single point
is always better because if we want
to update the information here,
it's easy and we can change it only
once.
And also, we don't have a duplication
in memory.
More specific example,
we want to define the instance-specific
properties, the properties that
are specific for a single object.
We want to define properties that
are basically from the description
of that instance.
In this example, it's clearer.
We see that for the `plant`,
we are going to have specific
information for each of them.
For example, the size,
the age, when it was attacked by
a given pest.
And in the description,
we are going to have all the common
information for all the same species.
For example, in which set of countries
is it or what are the other names for it.
Like this, we can have divided what
is the instance-specific information
and we can have the kind or `TypeObject`
information.
Having the `TypeObject` as a separate
object of our instance is that we
can change depending on the domain,
we are now able to change the
`TypeObject` of a `plant` or of
a given instance.
In this case, it depends a lot on
the domain, but we can do that.
Our descriptions evolve while the
program executes.
We can have that our `plant` starts
having a given type, a given
description.
And then, in a part of our program,
in a part of the lifetime of our object,
we realize that this `plant` is
not from this species.
We can easily change to another
description.
Of course, in the example of the plants,
this is not normal because the `plant`
does not evolve from one species
to the other.
But this is a way of handling that.
We can have now a dynamic relationship
between the object itself,
the instance of representing our
object in the real life,
with the description of it.
And also, one important thing is
that as we have a single point where
the descriptions, this already we
have said, but it's important.
As we have a single point of description
for a given family, if we change
that single point, for example,
adding or changing one of the
attributes, it will affect all described
instances.
And this is what we want to have,
coherence between the plants because
the worst case scenario that we
can have in the other solution where
all the information is in a single
object, but is duplicated in different
instances, is that we rename or
we fix a typo in the scientific
name of the `plant` and we have
some plants with the typo and some
plants that are okay.
So this is a bad problem.
But fixing a typo in the `plant`
description, it only takes changing
it in a single point.
As a conclusion, the idea of
`TypeObject` is that we want to
reify the description of a given object.
We want to split the object in two
different parts.
One part that is specific for a
given instance and one part that
is common between many instances.
Like this, we can make explicit
this relationship.
As we do always when we create objects,
we are going to encapsulate the
state and the behavior.
In this case, we are going to extract
the behavior that is common to a
set of objects.
And in doing that, we can now have
a dynamic way of changing this
description and a more flexible
way to handle in a single point
all these descriptions.