Hello everybody, so welcome to this
new lecture on sharing.
In this lecture, I will show how
you can have sharing with possibility
to have instance specific values.
The goal of this lecture,
this is to think about sharing.
What we saw in the previous one,
this is that we could share a value
between different instances,
like when we have a shared variable.
Now here what we will focus,
this is really how can we share
a default resource and still be able to,
depending on the usage,
be able to have instance specific
values.
So if you remember, we have instance
versus class sharing.
So on the instance, for the instance
level, this is simple,
an instance variable most of the
time will hold instance specific values.
So this is values that are just
for this object.
And when you modify these values,
you don't modify, you don't have
an impact on the other object.
Then you have also shared values
that can be or shared object that
can be shared between different
instance.
For example, all the instance of a class,
this is what we saw with the shared
variable, or this is what we call
static variable in some language
or class variable in others.
In fact, in Pharo, you have a value
that is shared among all the instance
of a class and hierarchy.
So this means that within this
hierarchy, this is what we show
in the lecture, all the instance
of subclass will share the same value.
So this was the previous lecture.
And now, the point there of this
lecture is that usually before we
were thinking in terms of is it
shared or is it instance specific.
Now what we want, we want to show
that we can have both a share a
default value and still be able
to have this instance specific behavior.
So I will let you two seconds to
see if you can imagine a solution.
Now let's study a little example to see.
We will do it example-based.
So imagine that you have a scanner.
So the scanner, this is a class
that will take some string.
And based on an internal table,
we said, ah, okay, we will cut the
strings into pieces.
And based on the element,
it will return.
For example, we will say,
oh, yes, this is the start with hash.
So this is a symbol.
This is a symbol.
That's a number.
This is a number.
And ah, okay, the rest is a string.
So the symbol, the scanner basically
is taking a string and cut it into
different kinds of literal objects.
So if we look at the class,
a possible class for the scanner
implementation is as follows.
Scanner inherit from object.
It has some instance variable to
know where we are in the industry
and the kind of token that is currently
done.
A `typeTable`, so the `typeTable`,
this is a table that will contain
information like, okay,
if I have one, probably if I start
with one, probably that will be
a digit or one, two, three,
they are digits.
Or if I have a letter like a $a,
that will be a letter,
those kinds of things.
And here what we see is that this
class has also a shared variable
`TypeTable`.
How surprising!
Why do we have both?
Why do we have both a shared variable
`TypeTable` and an instance variable
`typeTable`?
It looks like a bug, no?
No, in fact, this is a really nice
design and this is what we will explore.
So let me explain a bit the key
aspect of the implementation.
So `TypeTable` is a shared variable.
It is only `initialized` only once
and it will hold a table of elements
and it is not used by any instance
method.
This is a key aspect of the solution.
And `typeTable`, the instance variable
with the same name, is used by every
instance or only by instance method.
It cannot be used by a class method
anyway.
And it is initialized by pointing
to the `TypeTable` shared variable.
Do you see where I want to go?
So let's look at it graphically.
So in fact, what we have is that
we have the `TypeTable` shared variable
that is pointing to our large table.
So usually, we will have an entry
for each character.
So we will have $a, that say,
okay, I'm a letter one,
this is a digit, a space,
this is a separator or something
like that.
And then every instance of this
scanner will have its instance variable
`typeTable` that point to what is
referred to this `TypeTable`.
So this means that by default,
every instance variable of the instance
scanner will point to this shared
variable.
So now you can ask why do we need
this instance variable `typeTable`?
And that's the trick.
So here with the `TypeTable` shared
variable, we have sharing by default.
So each time we will create a new
instances of a scanner,
the idea of this is oh,
simple.
We don't have to allocate a large table.
We can just share it.
And now what we will see is that
the instance variable will let us
know new instance specific
customization.
So let's look at it.
So imagine, if I want to have a
specific table for a given scanner,
what do I have to do?
I create a scanner and then I change,
I copy this table and then I patch
it inside this `typeTable`.
So this means that here,
maybe one will not be a digit anymore
because I don't want.
So I will say, okay, now in my scanner,
one is a letter.
And I can do that for another one.
I can say, oh for this scanner,
no, no, for this scanner curly brace
is something like a separator.
This is possible because all the
methods have access to the instance
specific and never access this shared
variable.
So this means that the code of the
class was only using the instance
variable.
And this instance variable was by
default shared, but on these two cases,
it is not shared.
It is specific to this instance.
So how do we use this setup?
So you see, so basically the scanner
class `initialize`.
So here, it will just create a temporary
variable, put a scanner table inside.
You see this is said,
okay, for all the digit put digit,
for all the separator put separator,
those kinds of things.
And at the end here, it is initializing
the `TypeTable` shared variable
to point to this class.
So basically, what we have at the
end of that execution,
we have the `TypeTable` shared variable
that is pointing to the table.
Now, the key aspect is that when
we will create a scanner instance,
here we `initialize` it and do all
kinds of things.
And in particular, we said,
oh, the instance variable is pointing
to the table.
So this means that, so if I redraw it,
so I have the large table here with
all the information.
So this is the `TypeTable`,
`TypeTable` of the class scanner.
And now, I have an instance,
a scanner and the value of this scanner,
the `typeTable` with a lower case,
this is an instance variable,
will point to this guy.
This is what this line is doing.
So like that, I have sharing by default.
And so far, I don't have an instance
specific customization.
How do I customize?
This is easy.
I can customize like that.
I can say, oh, I create my new scanner.
So I create a new scanner instance.
And I will say, oh, I want to take
the default.
For example, I take the default table,
I copy it and I customize it with
some special message that I sent to that.
So in this setup, what I will have,
I will have the scanner with the
`TypeTable`.
And here, I have a scanner.
And instead of pointing to this guy,
now he will point to a copy of the
table.
Here I have a copy.
And here I said, oh, you know,
here, this is my special case.
I want this red spot there and there
only for this instance.
So, what you see that now if I do
scanner new, then what will I get?
In this solution, I will have a
scanner with an instance variable
that is sharing the big,
but I can have one that is specific.
Now, if I want to have more instances,
what I can do, I can create a class
that will do it automatically for me.
So let's do it.
So now here, I just subclass my
scanner and I said, okay,
my scanner, basically I want to
`initialize`.
I want to copy the table and I want
to modify the table for me.
And now, the situation will be like
that.
So you will have the scanner class
with the `TypeTable`.
So I have the table.
And then, I will have a subclass
that basically said my scanner.
And for my instances,
automatically, when I have an instance,
I will have a copy because I do
`typeTable` copy.
So we'll have a copy.
And this means that I can have multiple,
all my classes here, all the instance
of these classes will have their
own table.
While the instance of the scanner
class here, so if I have an instance,
they will all share, they will all
share this one.
So the idea of the design,
it was to basically say,
okay, the most frequent scenario,
this is sharing.
So let's favor sharing.
But in case the developer want to
have instance specific or a subclass
with a special behavior,
it can do it and reuse all the methods
of the scanner.
So what I show in this lecture is
that we can get sharing by default,
but we can also get instance specific,
if we need.
So what you see that this lecture
is interesting because before we have,
oh, okay, an object as private state,
and the state is specific to a given
instance, or we had another lecture
that said, okay, we can share and
with different scope of sharing
and now we can mix the two.
So this lecture bridge the two world
and we can decide.