- Hello everybody.
Welcome to this lecture on sharing,
another one.
This is more specific to Pharo.
I will explain in this lecture what
are shared pools.
Shared pools, in essence,
are how we can do a static sharing
of state between different hierarchies.
The goal of the lecture is to revisit
sharing so that you understand shared
pools because this is something
that a few people know in fact.
We saw in the previous lecture that
we can share a state within a hierarchy
using shared variables.
The question now is, how can we
share the value between different
hierarchies?
Basically, if I do it graphically,
a shared variable can be accessed
in all this space.
Now the problem is that sometimes
I have another hierarchy here and
I want to access this value.
How do we do it, because we don't
want to repeat it here?
If you remember, a shared variable
can be accessed from instance methods
or class methods and all the subclasses
within a hierarchy.
This means that I have a class here
with a shared variable and all the
subclasses here and there can access
this shared variable.
If you remember, in the previous
lecture, I showed that in the `Color`
class.
The `Color` class initialized the
shared variable and the instance
variable methods, like `privateBlue`,
can access this in the `Color` methods
and the `Color` class can access
that by initializing the value.
It also could read the value.
This was what was in the previous
lecture.
Now the key point of this lecture
is that we can share within a hierarchy,
but how can we share between different
hierarchies?
For example, line feed and all
the constants, like carriage return,
that are related to `Text`,
we want to have them in the `String`
hierarchy, but we want to have them
in the `Text` hierarchy.
But a text is not a string and a
string is not a text.
So, how do we avoid repeating the
same code and the same constant
in these two or three hierarchies?
That's the point.
For that, Pharo uses shared pools.
What is a shared pool?
This is a group of shared variables
and the shared pool will define
the variables and will initialize
the value of its shared variables.
Then, users - the classes - will
just declare that they use a shared
pool to access its shared variables.
Let's look at it.
You see, for example,
for the `ChronologyConstants`,
like how many Nano Seconds you have
in a Second, the MonthNames or
how many seconds are in one hour,
the days in a month, and all these
kinds of things, those are defined
in a `ChronologyConstants` shared pool,
which inherits from the class
`SharedPool`, and it defines a set
of shared variables.
You see, for example,
the shared pool, the
`ChronologyConstants` class,
because a shared pool is a kind
of a class, has an `initialize` method,
and it will just say how many seconds
there are in a day, how many seconds
in a minute, how many minutes per hour,
how many hours per day,
etc.
It will initialize all these shared
variables that are grouped in a
shared pool.
Then, the users.
If `DateAndTime` wants to access
all this logic, it will just say,
"I want to use the shared pool
`ChronologyConstants`".
Notice that you can also define
some of its own instance variables,
there's no problem, `DateAndTime`
will have seconds, and all these
kinds of information: `#offset`,
`#julianDayNumber`, etc.
It can also define its own shared
variables and reuse this group of
shared variables.
They have been initialized so it
can use them.
Here, what you see is that as soon
as the class `DateAndTime` declares
that it is using the shared pool,
it will be able to access the class
variable of the shared pool as if
defined in the class.
So, `SecondsInDay`, which was in
the `ChronologyConstants` shared pool,
is a class variable defined in the
`ChronologyConstants` shared pool,
but we can access this directly
because the class `DateAndTime`
declared it wanted to use this shared
pool.
You can do the same at the class level.
For example, the `Duration` class
will use `SecondsInDay` because
it also wants to use
`ChronologyConstants`.
You see here, for example,
`Week`, which is a subclass of
`Timespan`, will have its own shared
variables and use the same shared pool,
and it will be able to use `DayNames`,
which is a shared variable of the
`ChronologyConstants` shared pool.
There is no problem, we can mix
everything, this is what I already
said before, we can mix shared
variables, instance variables,
and shared pools together.
In fact, the compiler will just
go and pick up the right information
in the right place.
I have one warning and I'm not sure
that I stressed it enough in the
shared variable lecture:
only put constant objects in shared
pools.
You can put objects that are changing,
but you should always consider that
if you change the value in a shared
pool or in a shared variable,
it will impact all the objects that
are using them.
They are shared, so a change impacts
everybody.
In general, we expect a shared variable
to be constant.
The conclusion is that shared pools
are really handy for sharing constants
between different hierarchies.
They are really nice for managing
constants for bindings.
For example, if you want to bind
a C-libraries, you will often have
to have a lot of constants and you
can group them.
Like that, from the user of such
a constant, this is easy,
it just uses a shared pool and not
thousands of class variables.
Pay attention that this is always
better to use constants in shared
variables and shared pools.