Hi, in this lecture, we are going
to discuss the singleton design pattern.
The goals of this lecture are to
discuss the singleton pattern,
to have some discussions of the
benefits and the disadvantages of it,
and to discuss a bit about the
misunderstandings around it.
Now, if you read the original book
from (Gangs of Four),
the singleton pattern is there to
ensure that the class has only one
instance, and to provide a global
access point to it.
So there is a single way to access
that single instance.
Now, a better way to look at that
is to see it as ensuring that a
class has only one instance at a
single point in time.
So that means that if in the program,
we are trying to access the same
instance in two different places,
but at the same time,
we are going to access the same
instance.
So what is the problem here?
So we need a way to keep some objects
around.
So we want to keep the same object
because we want to reuse that same
object.
So that is why it is persistent.
We want to store it, or we want
to save it somewhere.
The other way to see it is that
we need a class with a unique instance,
that we don't want two instances around,
because that could mess some stuff.
The solution that is proposed by
this pattern is that we are going
to allocate that instance,
we are going to instantiate it,
and we're going to store it the
first time we use it.
And then, every time that we are
going to use it again,
so instead of creating a new instance,
we are going to return the old one
that we have been storing before.
So most of the time, we need to
think twice about applying this
pattern because it has many drawbacks,
and it has really, really limited
application for real.
So here, for example,
let's imagine that you want to keep
only a single instance of a database
connection, because of course,
database connections are expensive,
and they are difficult to create,
and maybe there are even hardware
limitations for it, and so on.
So one way of applying this pattern
is to say, Okay, we're going to
use a singleton, a singleton to
keep the database connections.
For example here, we are going to
ask the database connection class
to give us the uniqueInstance.
So it's  only instance in the
system.
If we ask two times in different
places for the uniqueInstance of
the database connection,
we are going to get the same object.
So remember that equals equals is
the identity comparison.
It is telling us that db2 and db
are two variables, but they are
referencing the same object,
exactly the same object.
In this way, we are sure that we
are only creating one database
connection and not two.
One possible implementation for
this pattern is to store the instance
in a shared variable in the class,
and then we have our uniqueInstance
method that in each access,
it is checking if the uniqueInstance
variable is pointing to nil.
If it is nil, we are going to allocate
it, create the new instance,
and store it.
Otherwise, we're just returning
what has been storing there from before.
So that means that the first time,
we are going to execute this method,
the uniqueInstance will be nil.
It is going to be instantiated and
assigned and then returned.
The second time, the uniqueInstance
will not be nil, then the conditional
code will be avoided,
and then we are going just to return
the instance.
Now, a question could be,
should we overwrite `new` to always
return the uniqueInstance?
This is probably a bit controversial.
I particularly don't like it because
sending the message `new` conveys
that we are going to create a new
instance.
If instead of doing that,
we are just returning the same instance
all the time, then clients can be
confused.
People can actually try to use this API,
thinking that it is going to do
something and it is actually doing
something else.
So at the end, the API is not conveying
what it's actually doing and that
can create a lot of problems in
the future.
Let's see some variations of the
pattern with different namings also.
The one that we saw before is the
uniqueInstance, so we can implement
a singleton with the uniqueInstance
method.
In this case, we are just lazily
creating the uniqueInstance on the
first access and then returning
the value otherwise.
One way also to attack the problem
of the `new` is that instead of
making `new` calling uniqueInstance,
we can, for example, cancel it or
block it.
So for example, here what we are
doing is that if we want everybody
to use the uniqueInstance method
and not the new method,
what we're going to do is to write
an error every time that the new
method is being called.
Another variation of this is to
use the default version.
So these are some variations that
you are going to find in the Pharo code,
for example, if you take the (standard
live).
So default is a kind of a singleton,
but here there's no reason to stop
the user to create new instances.
So we have a default instance that
can be reused and it is a single
instance that can be passed around.
But we can create other kinds of
instances.
So this name conveys that it's not
the only one.
It is a default one.
It is a good one to use in general case,
but we are able to create new ones
if we want.
Another possibility is to,
for example, to implement a singleton
as a current instance.
This name conveys that this is the
current instance and it may change
in the future.
So there's only one right now,
but this one that is right now,
it can change and then later,
we can have another only one.
So that means that if we see it in time,
so maybe we have a singleton here
at some point, so we have object
one and then here it changes and
then we have some other object too.
So at each point in time,
we have a single object that will
be unique and then when it changes,
we have another object,
but always we have only one,
which is the current one.
Now, of course, you may be tempted
to say, Ah, I can implement this
just as a global variable.
Particularly, it is important to
avoid to use global variables first
because already classes work like
global variables.
They provide a global access point
to data.
So usually in Pharo through shared
variables or class variables,
but in Java also through static
variables.
But the main thing is that also,
classes, (since we have to act),
they let us access the singletons
through method, they can also allow
us to encapsulate behavior and to
change it more easily later.
If we put objects in global variables,
they make the system more difficult
to change in the future.
Now, in Pharo in particular,
we have two different variations
of the singleton pattern.
One using shared variables and another
one using class instance variables.
You may recall from a previous lecture
that in Pharo, we have shared variables,
which are variables that are shared
in the whole hierarchy.
So for example, here we have this
variable, uniqueInstance,
that is a shared variable and that
means that it is the same variable
that is shared by everybody in the
hierarchy.
So every time that we see uniqueInstance
in any piece of code around the
hierarchy, they are going to access
the same variable, which is this one.
A class instance variable is defined
in a class, but then,
implementation-wise,
a copy of this variable will exist
in each of the subclasses.
So here, for example,
we define uniqueInstance as a class
instance variable and then we are
going to have actually one variable
in here, but we are also going to
have one variable in each subclass.
How does it modify our singleton
pattern?
If we implement the singleton pattern
using a shared variable,
that means that we are going to
have a singleton shared by the whole
hierarchy.
Here is our uniqueInstance.
However, if we implement it using
a class instance variable,
we will have one singleton per class.
So depending on what kind of design
that you want, these two variations
can give you different possibilities.
Now, it's important to understand
that singleton, the singleton pattern,
is about time.
So we want to have only one instance
available at each single point in time.
It's not necessarily about access.
It's not the most important point.
So yeah, the singleton is more easily
accessible through a single point,
but the important point is that
we have only one at that point.
One way to test yourself to see
if you actually need to implement
a singleton or not is to check if
adding an instance variable in your
design and parameterising it with
an object is enough for your problem
or not.
In that case, maybe you don't need
a singleton.
Actually, just putting a variable
or parameter or even an instance
variable is enough and just
parameterising it correctly.
Otherwise, maybe it is more complicated
and the singleton could be an okay
solution.
One of the really negative points
of the singleton pattern is that
they really harm testing.
Since singletons work as global
variables because you have a single
instance that is accessible by the
whole program and they survive because
they are persistent, they make the
program more difficult to test because
maybe you want to change the singleton
by another kind of object only for
the time the tests are running.
So for example, when you're running
the test, you want to exchange that
singleton by another singleton object.
So in that case, maybe you want
to go to a lighter singleton pattern
like what we saw before,
the current variation or the default.
Like that, for example,
the current allows you to replace
a singleton during the run of the
test or the default one allows you to,
instead of using the singleton directly,
you can allocate your own objects
when you're using it in the test
without using the default general
and global.
Be careful also, since the singleton
is a shared object but that is shared
by all the system, it is also shared
by the process in the test.
So if many tests are going to share
the same singleton, it may happen
that one test can break the singleton
to another test.
It's the same thing as if you were
running a test that writes a file
or deletes a file.
So all other tests that were depending
on those files will be broken now.
So every kind of global state,
let them be files or global variables,
can break your tests.
Let's see an example with the
`RPackageOrganizer`, which is a
singleton in Pharo, and it should
not be destroyed when the tests are run.
So there is a singleton and the
tests need to be running and not
breaking the actual singleton instance.
So this is a bit of complicated code,
so I will explain it.
Every time that we want to run the
tests in the RPackage test,
what we're going to do is to call
this method `withOrganizer do`.
What we're going to do is to send
the organiser that we're going to
use for testing and a block of the
thing that we want to do in the test.
What this method is going to make
sure is that this NewOrganizer is
available globally during the execution
of a block and then, after the execution
of the block is done,
it is going to restore the previous
global singleton.
So here what happens is that first,
it is taking the previous singleton,
which is actually the default variable,
the default object, it's going to
unregister it and then it's going
to register the new singleton,
the one that is being coming as
parameter, the argument that comes
as parameter.
It is going to register it,
then it is executing the code,
the block, and then as a final step,
it is going to restore the old object,
the old organiser, and unregister
the one that was here,
the transient one.
So as a conclusion, singleton is
a design pattern that helps us to
have only one instance at a single time.
However, we should be careful to
avoid singleton as globals and in
general avoid singletons because
they act as a global variable and
it comes with all the negative
properties of global variables and
global states.
In particular, singletons make tests
difficult to write and they are
on themselves difficult to test.