- Hello, welcome to this lecture.
In this lecture, we are going to
present why Fat classes are bad.
We are going to present a dichotomy
between having a class hierarchy
and having a large class.
Basically, the goal for this class
is to present the Transform Self
Type Check Reengineering pattern.
It is good, if you don't remember,
to recheck the Implementing Not
lectures.
Let's start with an example.
We are going to create a program
to process BibTeX files.
BibTeX files are a way of representing
documents such as articles,
proceedings, and books,
and have information about their
authors, titles, the publisher,
the year, and much more information
for each of them.
As we can see, in this kind of file,
we have different kinds of entries.
We have inproceedings,
books, articles, techreports,
PhD, and a lot more.
And for each of them,
we will have different fields.
We will have a key to identify them
inside the file, but also we are
going to have the year,
the institution, the authors,
the book title, and the title,
and these fields change by the type
of entry that we have.
There are some that are common,
but some that are unique for each
kind of entry.
We have a little library that already
handles these kinds of files,
and it's called Citezen.
Well, in this one, we are representing
these entries as instances of the
class #CZEntry.
We can see that in this one,
we have instance variables to represent
all of the fields, keys,
types, and all the elements in any
given element inside the BibTeX.
We have one single class to represent
them all.
It's common that we will have this
kind of pattern of methods.
We have an `isArticle` method that
will return true if the element
that we are processing inside the
BibTeX file is an article and will
return false in all the other cases.
We have the same for our `isBook`.
It checks the type of the object
of the entry and returns true or
false if it's the correct type.
In this case, we are going to have
a lot of them, one for each of the
types of entries that we have in
our BibTeX file.
This same pattern is happening to
us in the field, in the representation
of each of the fields in the entries,
in the BibTeX entries.
In this case, we are going to have
one single class to represent all
the fields that we can have in a
BibTeX entry.
In this case, we have exactly the
same problem.
We were going to be able to identify
if a field is of a given type.
In this case, for example,
if `is Doi` of the document - the
DOI is an international unique code
given for each document in the academic
world - but it's the same for all
of them.
It could be `isDoi` or we can have
if `isTitle` or if `isURL` or whatever.
We are going to have many of them.
How is this impacting us?
Well, the consequence of having
all these methods to ask about the
type of field is that we have a
lot of repetition of this kind of
bad pattern.
Look what we have in this method.
First, the first thing that you
should see is that it's a really
long method.
And also that it has a lot of
conditional code.
We have different behaviors depending
on the type of the field.
If we have a field that is a PDF,
we will produce the output in a
single way.
If it's a URL, in another way,
and so on.
Because what this method is doing
is printing, and generating HTML code,
depending on the kind of field that
we have.
But we see that this pattern is
really evil because it generates
a long method that has a lot of
conditional code.
So, the consequences of having a
Fat class is basically that we are
taking all our naturally existing
hierarchy - we have a lot of types
of fields, a lot of types of entries
- and we are collapsing all of them
in a single class.
So, we don't have a class hierarchy,
we have a single Fat class.
As we have only one class,
we cannot use dispatch,
we cannot use polymorphism.
It's not possible to dispatch because
we only have one class and we have
to use all these methods that are
`isBook`, `isTitle`, `isURL`.
And we don't have a nice solution
where we use dispatch and we are
breaking the rule that we are always
saying is "Tell, don't ask".
We want to dispatch instead of having
a conditional code.
When we start adding new types in
the file or fields, we will have
to modify many of these methods.
We will have to modify many of these
long methods to add new conditional
codes.
Also, if we want to subclass these
really big classes with really complex
code, we are going to see that we
will be starting duplicating and
changing and adapting and doing
mostly hacks to go over this problem.
As I said before, every time that
we have a new behavior,
we will have to change exactly the
same methods, adding more and more
conditional code and making it more
complex.
This is a good example of a problem
that we have already talked about
in the Implementing Not lectures.
So, if you don't have it in mind,
please go back to that lecture and
see some of them.
In these kinds of questions,
conditional code that we do,
we can call it type checking because
we are asking all the time what
is the type of the object:
is it a book, is it an article?
Well, this is not bad per se,
but we have to take care when to use it.
This is good when we can encapsulate
this behavior inside our own class
and we can do self methods.
But it's really bad when the clients
start using them.
When these methods are used,
these messages are sent from outside
our class.
So, we have to take care of this
and this is a smell that we
are doing something wrong and we
have to refactor our code.
What we are suggesting in this lecture
is if we have the code in this shape,
where we have a client who sends
a message m() and this message is
implemented in a method where we
have different cases using a lot
of conditional code, and we are
executing different code for each
of these cases, we can refactor this,
delegating this behavior in a new class.
In this case, for example,
for case B, we are going to have
a new implementation and the idea
is that we are going to have a new
class B that handles that behavior
and only that behavior.
For example, B could be our class
representing the books,
and C could be for our articles,
and so on.
The client now will delegate these
objects through a new method.
In this case, we put a generic name
`hook()`, but it can be any name.
But the important thing is that
we are extracting this code that
is in each of the cases and putting
each in a separate class.
In this case, we can have or not
have a common superclass.
This depends if we have or have
not reused each of these real objects
implementing our behavior.
As a conclusion, we have to always
favor dispatch.
We have to prefer to use dispatch
before conditional code.
We can create little classes that
encapsulate little knowledge.
They are cheap to use,
they are cheap to maintain,
and they produce more clear code
than conditional code.
And remember, because this is a
mantra that justifies a lot of our
design decisions and that produces
a better code quality:
Do not ask, tell.
Basically, delegate before using
conditional code.
If you just want it in the same order,
do not use conditional code,
delegate to other options.