- Hi, in this lecture, we are going to
discuss about the Decorator design
pattern, which is a composable
alternative to subclassing.
So the goal of this lecture is to
think about the Decorator,
the Decorator pattern,
to discuss about the different
inconveniences and the benefits of it,
and to think about APIs in general,
and how actually APIs will have
an impact on the different designs
of the Decorator.
So from the book, the Decorator
will help you to attach new
responsibilities to an object dynamic.
What does it mean is that we are
going to have an object and then
we're going to attach some other
object that will extend the behavior
of this object.
So this is a way to actually attach
behavior by changing objects and
not by extending classes like in
inheritance.
So the main point is that dynamically,
we can decide if this Decorator
will be there or not at runtime.
That is why it said dynamically.
Now, if we look at the main drawing,
the main design of the Decorator in UML,
what we see is that we have a client,
the client is the object that is
going to use the Decorator,
and we have here the main Decorator
part.
So the Decorator is either what
we are going to say a decoree,
which is the main object.
It is the object that is going to
do the main operation.
And then we are going to have Decorators
that are going to wrap this decoree
to extend the behavior.
And by default, a Decorator will
know the decoree and delegate the
operation to the decoree.
So that means that every time that
we have a Decorator, a decoree and
we have a Decorator, the Decorator
knows the decoree and then every
time that we are going to say,
ah, do operation to the Decorator,
the Decorator will do something
and then eventually will tell the
decoree do operation.
So it's a pattern really based on
delegation.
Of course, you can mix this with
inheritance.
You can have many different ways
of Decorees and many different
Decorators.
So as many as you want.
And what will happen is that at the end,
the only objects in the dynamic
graph that no other objects here
will be the Decorators.
So the Decorators can be chained
in a way that we have a Decorator,
a Decorator, a Decorator,
but the Decorees will be leaves.
So they will be the end of the chains.
The Decorators will be the leaves here.
So here we are going to see the decoree.
So a Decorator, we say it wraps
an instance of a decoree.
It displays between the client and
the decoree.
So in my drawings before,
I didn't put the client,
but actually it is one of the most
important parts in the Decorator
pattern when taking the decision
of deploying it or not.
So here, for example,
we have a Decorator, a decoree,
a decoree that is going to be decorated
by some Decorator.
And the client is the one that is
going to be using the Decorator
here and the Decorator is going
to delegate something to the decoree
and the decoree is going to do its
operation.
So what is important here is that
the messages will actually flow
from the client to the decoree.
So the Decorator can do many things.
It can intercept messages.
It can decide, for example,
to do something before,
after, or instead the decoree.
So it can also, the Decorator can
decide to not delegate to the decoree.
One thing that happens is that
Decorators can be nested.
As we saw before, Decorator can
know another Decorator and all these
chain of Decorators are transparent
to the client.
So a client actually will have probably
some piece of code that we will
say object operation,
but here the object could be a Decorator
or it could be the decoree.
So actually the client is completely
independent of how the Decorator
chain is composed.
It could be just the simple decoree
or it could be actually a chain
of Decorators followed by the decoree.
What's important here is that there
is a really strong implication.
The decoree and the Decorator must
expose the same API because the
client should be agnostic of that.
It should be agnostic of the fact
that it's been talking to the decoree
or the Decorator.
So the decoree and Decorators should
have the same API.
If we see an example here with Streams,
so here what we see is that we have
a binary stream accessing the standard
input output.
So here it's a standard output.
The standard output, of course,
it's a binary stream.
So it just knows how to write binary
data in zeros and ones.
And if we want to put text in there,
we need to encode that in some encoding.
So what we're going to do is we
have our Stdio object.
And if we want to write text,
we need to decorate it with a character
stream.
What is the responsibility of the
character stream?
The responsibility of the character
stream, of course, is to receive
text and transform it into bytes.
Of course, we can again,
in this example, wrap this character
stream with another Decorator,
which is a Decorator that will add
new lines and it will manage how
they are printed, independent of
the platform.
Here, every time that we give text
to the new line Decorator,
it will transform the text to replace
the new lines for some platform
to maybe for the current platform.
There are many ways to wrap those
streams.
So here, for example,
there is another example in the
file class, the file reference class.
Every time that we want to read
a file in Pharo, we're going to
ask the file for a stream,
a readStream with an encoding.
Dynamically, the FileReference will
decide to create a binaryReadStream
and to wrap it with a new character
Decorator using the encoding that
we asked as parameter.
So, dynamically, it is the FileReference
that is deciding to create and wrap
the binaryReadStream.
If you want to check the implementation
of this, of course, here we have
the NewLineWriteStream that knows,
for example, the stream,
which is the decoree,
and it knows several data that it
uses to actually replace the new lines.
So, for example, here it knows the #cr,
the #lf characters, the #previous
character, and the #lineEnding that
is going to be replacing.
And then, it needs to implement
all the basic API of streams,
like, for example, close and flush,
to be able to be polymorphic with
the original stream that is going
to be wrapping.
So here, we see the close method
is going to just call the close
method in the stream,
or the flush method is going to
call the flush method in the stream.
Now, here what we see is a test
that is actually testing the behavior
of our new line stream.
What we're having here in this first
line is string composed by ab,
and in the middle we are going to
have a new line depending on the
current platform.
So, for example, if we are on Windows,
we are going to have a cr character
of return, and if we are in Linux,
we are going probably to have a
line feed followed by a character
return.
So depending on the platform we are on,
we are going to have different line
ending convention.
And then, what we're going to do
is to craft different strings using
different line endings.
So here we take three different
line endings, just cr,
lf, and crlf, we are going to craft
a string using that line ending,
and then we are going to write it
using the line ending write stream
to see that it actually matches
the string that we expect.
So here we are testing that our
NewLineWriterStream is actually
transforming the different line
ending conventions to the expected
string, which is the one of the
platform.
Now, if we take a look at
implementation, the NewLineWriterStream,
as I showed you before,
it will just redefine most of the
method to call the decoree.
But here it needs to manage what
happens when we try to put a character
in the string.
So when we want to write a character
So what it is doing here is that
every time that we're going to write
the character, it is checking first
the previous characters and the
current character to see if they
match the cr, crlf, or the lf pattern.
And in that case, if it matches
one of those, it will just write
a newLine.
Of course, this newLine will follow
the current platform newLine as
we saw before.
Otherwise, if it doesn't match any
of those, that means that it's probably
just a normal character like a.
And if it is the case,
it will just delegate the writing
to the decoree.
So calling the stream and saying,
okay, next put this character.
What we just saw before is that
all Decorators should have the same API.
So in this case, close,
flush should be redefined to just
delegate to the decoree.
But then nextPut, contents next,
probably need to be redefined and
specify specific behavior for our
Decorator.
Now, one of the benefits of this
Decorator implementation is that
the Decorators can be shared and
replaced by different kind of Decorator.
So we can compose different chains
in different ways and obtain different
behavior.
We say that Decorators attach additional
responsibilities to an object.
Yeah, so we have our objects,
the decoree that is going to be
wrapped by a Decorator.
And the Decorator will actually
delegate behavior to the decoree.
Now, as we saw before in the example
of the file reference,
it is the file reference that is
creating the pair or the chain of
Decorators.
So we should really control how
the Decorator chain is created because
the client actually doesn't know
if it is talking to the Decorator
or to the decoree.
So if we're actually giving the
reference of our object to the client,
we need to create the correct chain
with the correct configuration and
give it to him.
There is a strong implication from
this is that if we have a client here,
of course, the client doesn't know
which kind of object it is talking to.
But the Decorator, it doesn't know
either if it is being used by the
direct client or by another Decorator.
And it is also the case for the decoree.
The decoree doesn't know if it is
used by a Decorator or by another
client.
So this means that changing the
decoration chain or removing one
decoration in the middle of the
execution is not an easy task.
So that is the same pattern is actually
not made for that.
And doing that adds a lot of complexity
to the code.
So when you should not or maybe
it's difficult to use the Decorator.
When the decorations should have
different APIs.
So the main point of using the Decorator
is that both the Decorators and
the Decorees have the same API like
that the client doesn't need to
check anything.
It can just use them polymorphically.
If they have different APIs,
that is by construction impossible to do.
So we cannot apply the Decorator
pattern in that case.
Of course, if we need to change
the Decorator chain dynamically,
it also complexifies the task of
using Decorators.
So maybe we need to think twice
before doing this.
Maybe the Decorator is not the best
solution for the case.
Also, it happens that sometimes
APIs are huge.
Maybe you have hundreds of methods.
So that means that maintaining huge
APIs where Decorators will only
override one or two methods,
maybe it is not worth to have a
Decorator in that case.
In conclusion, today we saw that
Decorators can represent composable
facets of an object that can be
reusable and even dynamically
composable.
We should pay attention that all
the Decorators should implement
the same API.
And the Decorator pattern is a modular
pattern, but it expects us to have
a common API.