Welcome everybody.
This is a new lecture on global
variables.
It complements one of the lectures
that we saw in the previous module.
What we will see during this lecture
is that global variables can be
disguised, so sometimes we don't
see them at first but they still
exist and we will study several
cases that happen in Pharo or that
have been discussed in the mailing list.
So the idea is that we want to show
that globals are not nice because
they are globally shared.
We saw that in the previous lecture,
they are difficult to test.
And in this lecture, we really want
to show that they can have different
forms, and for that, we will really
study one by one four case studies
and we will show that when you don't
have global variables,
you can dispatch, and when you have
a global, you cannot.
So let's start.
So this is what I call the autopsy
of an error.
So in Pharo code, in the past,
we often had this expression,
`Smalltalk`, `icons`,
`iconNamed`, things like that.
So let me explain what it is.
`Smalltalk`, this is a global variable
that is a namespace that contains
all the classes of `Smalltalk` and
also some globals that point to
some objects.
So here, the expression `Smalltalk`
icons` refers to an icon manager,
and here, the code means,
Okay, global icon manager,
please give me the icon named #window.
So I'm stressing the fact that this
is a global variable.
Normally, you just read it like that.
Okay?
So what can we conclude from this?
First, this guy is a global variable.
What if I want to have a different
set of icons that is specific to
my specific application?
I cannot.
I will have to go and patch this
global icon provider.
And then, it means that any user
of the icon that I change will be
impacted.
So basically, I cannot compare,
for example, if I am doing a design,
often, you want to have a black
theme or white theme with different
icon sets: you cannot.
You cannot because there is only one.
In the community, some people proposed
the following solution.
They said, Oh, you know,
a better way is to do that.
So what does it mean?
It means that they send the message
asIcon to a `Symbol`.
So in fact, these people,
they propose to extend the class
`Symbol` with a new method.
That was basically doing the same
thing here.
So in Pharo, what I mean extend,
it means that in Pharo,
a package can add a method to another
class that is not packaged in this
package.
So this means that I said,
Oh, dear class there,
I want that you get this method,
but only when this package is loaded.
So that's why we can add methods
in kernel classes, because `Symbol`
is a kernel class.
So let's analyze the situation.
This solution does not duplicate
this expression everywhere.
So this is already something because
it means that there is only one
place in the system where I can
change it if I want.
But still, this is a global,
I still cannot have two icon states
in the system.
So what we will see is that a global
variable can be disguised,
but it is still there.
There is one place here where we
can edit it.
But fundamentally, this is still
one instance variable.
And this was based on message passing.
So you could say, Oh,
yes, I send a message.
This is okay.
No, there is only one icon table
in this system.
We cannot dispatch to a different
object.
There is no different object.
There is only here one `Symbol`.
So this means that my application
cannot extend or slightly change
icons because I will have impact
everywhere.
Still, I cannot have two icons set
at the same place.
So now, you should wonder what is
the solution.
So a better approach,
this is that the framework,
here, for example, the application
that is holding the menu propose
a method that is called `iconNamed`
that can be dispatched to this guy.
And then, this `iconNamed` method
will just do some things and it can ask,
Oh, I have an icon provider and
I will ask the icon to this provider.
So like that, every application can say,
Oh, I want to be configured with
a different icon set and manage that.
So this is the way it is done in
the spec framework to build application
in Pharo.
We don't use a global variable.
Every application has its own iconProvider
, and then we can dispatch
there.
So it is modular because every
application can decide what they
want to do, how they want to be
configured.
Each receiver may do something different
and they can be configured silently,
but still.
we will share the same common behavior.
So this is the reuse as it should
be done.
So when we want to access
programmatically a class for doing
a script or things that are a bit
strange in Pharo, we ask the namespace,
we say Namespace, give me all the
globals in the system.
This is a dictionary basically that
is holding a reference to classes,
and give me the class that is named
#point.
So people were saying,
Oh, this is too long.
I have to type this code and things
like that.
And they wanted to have a shorter
version for scripting.
So what they proposed,
they proposed something like that.
You know, we want again to extend
the `Symbol` with a new method and
do that.
And of course, this is shorter,
but this is not good.
So there is a difference between the two.
I hope that now you see it,
but let's look at the difference.
So I have the same limit as before.
global is an entry point.
And when I write #point asClasses,
I have only one `Symbol` in the system,
one class.
This is an instance of the class
`Symbol`.
So I cannot have multiple
implementations.
I cannot dispatch.
I have only one place.
So imagine that, for example,
I would like to access a class that
is remote.
asClass will only access the one
in the system.
I cannot dispatch.
I only have one object here,
this `Symbol`.
It could be, by the way,
it could be a rectangle.
That would be the same.
When I say that we have multiple,
let's be clear.
We have multiple instances,
but we have only one class.
So if you remember the first lecture
of this MOOC, then there is no way
that I can dispatch to a different
behavior.
Here, what this message implies,
this is that there is only one namespace
in the system.
There is no way that I can dispatch
to another place.
So you see, this is again a disguised
global variable.
And that's why we are really against
the introduction and the use of
asClass in Pharo.
People can use that if they want,
but we don't want to use it internally
in the system because we want to be able,
for example, to browse Pharo codes
that are running on other machines.
And if we do that, we cannot.
So the possible solution,
this is just to delegate to the system.
We could say, Oh, you know,
self-class environment.
Environment means, Okay,
to a class, go to your namespace
and look for a class.
And in that case, the class can
have different environments.
It can be configured differently.
So let's look at a fourth case study.
When you browse the Pharo code,
sometimes you see these kinds of code.
And you will start to understand
the pattern.
So this is the code when you want
to browse a method.
It says, Oh, for example,
here it said, Okay, what is the
currentClassOrMetaClass?
If this is not nil, I will invoke
the browser and open the class with
the currentMessage.
And then we will be able to see
all the implementers of that message.
Again, now you should know and you
should understand, Aha,
again, the ugly global variable.
Because here, `Smalltalk`,
`Smalltalk` tools.
This is pointing to a tool registry
mechanism.
So there is one in the system and
we will ask the browser in that.
So again, one single entry point.
Everybody will refer to this single
entry point.
And this is monolithic thinking.
So this means that you cannot exercise
code that will open this browser
and that you would get two different
browsers because you are trying
to see what is the best one that
will fit the scenario.
So you can have only one toolset
possible at the same time.
This could be okay.
But we should really understand
that this is what it means.
And you see, this is not because
I send a message to a global that,
in fact, I'm not manipulating
conceptually a global variable.
So what is the solution?
A possible solution, this is,
Okay, this means that the ID of
Pharo should be defined as an
application, and that this application
should, for example, have a
toolEnvironment instance variable,
instantiate the toolEnvironment.
And then after just do that,
which will be okay because it means
that each application will be able
to dispatch.
We could even have a different
toolEnvironment for a given application.
What we should consider here is
that there are still some points
to consider in this lecture.
So with a global variable,
when it changes, all its users are
updated for free, which is nice.
You don't have to go over and say,
Okay, you change, you change,
you change.
No, because there is only one place
centralized where everybody refer
to that.
So you get the sharing and you get
the update of the sharing for free.
Now, this is not modular.
So this means that when you have
another solution, we should think
about how do we handle the fact
that a tool may change.
So from that perspective,
it means that browsers may register
to the toolEnvironment.
So like that, they get notified
and updated when there is something
that changes.
In this way, if you have a registration
mechanism, it means that you can load,
for example, a new package containing
a new tool and it can declare and say,
Oh, you know, I'm an alternate browser.
I'm available if necessary,
or those kinds of things.
So it's open more possibility,
but we have to pay attention that
the solution should take into account
that the shared variable should
be updated.
So as a conclusion, yes,
try to avoid to use global.
And this is very important in
object-oriented design to think modular.
Give a chance also to objects to
specialize messages, because like
that you have a handle to variation.
And every object can decide how
to react to a specific message.