Hello.
In this lecture, we will discuss
something obvious, but probably
important to remember.
So methods are the elementary unit
of reuse.
Executing a method is reusing code,
obviously, but when you define a method,
it means that you enrich the API
of the object, the application
programming interface.
And calling this method,
this is the first level of reuse.
So let's have a look at this case study.
This is a long method,
and this method is defined on a PRTree,
that is a tree representing a document.
This is part of the Pillar package,
and we want to inspect this tree.
It will return a Presenter that
displays this tree of nodes,
and we have different kinds of nodes
inside this tree.
We might have some paragraphs,
some titles, headers,
whatever.
And now we can wonder why clients
of a document are forced to define
this behavior here.
Why should I test if the node that
I want to display is a header?
Why is it important that clients
test this?
In fact, it would be much better
to separate things.
And if I introduce correctly some
display on strings, I define a new
method on PRObject.
This is the root of the hierarchy
of all nodes.
And I said that by default,
when I want to transform a node
to a string, it just displays its
class name.
And if I want to display as a string
a header node, it means that I can
reuse, I can extend the default
behavior.
It means that displaying its class name,
but also I will concatenate the
level of the title.
So if you have trouble to understand
this part, I invite you to revise
the hooks and template lecture.
This is a direct application of it.
So now let's go back to our example.
Now I can refactor my method,
it's a little bit shorter,
and I can use directly the newly
defined displayStringOn.
And I can send it to all kinds of
nodes and it will correctly work.
It means that the right method will
be selected dynamically,
either it will be the default
implementation that displays the
class name, or if it is a header node,
the level of the header will be
correctly displayed also.
So this is much simpler.
And this is just because we enrich
the API of nodes with the fact that
they can display themselves as a string.
So let's have a look at another example.
This is a logic repetition.
If I want to convert an object to
a string, usually we are using this
kind of pattern.
I start by creating a stream,
and this string uses a string.
I can send a printOn method to the
object and say, OK, display yourself
on this string, and then I get the
content of the string.
So here, this is the kind of code
that I should repeat over and over
each time I want to convert any
kind of object as a string.
And the idea is, how can I avoid
this kind of logic repetition?
And in fact, this is implemented
in the Pharo library.
And the method is named streamContents.
And if you look at it,
this method takes as argument a
block there.
So this method encapsulates the
stream creation, so the string is
correctly created.
This method is optimized,
we will see how later.
It hides all the details,
so it means that from the client
point of view, I do not have to
take care about creating the string,
the stream, etc.
And it encapsulates termination,
as we will see.
Let's have a look at this
implementation.
So in fact, this is not implemented
in the string class.
This is implemented in the
SequenceableCollection.
And the first, so this is implemented
on class side.
And it will be inherited by stream
class.
So here, I can specify the default
size of the string that will be created.
And the important method is this one,
here.
So first, we are creating the stream,
and now, the important thing is
that I got a block as argument,
and I can execute this block here,
bypassing the newly created stream.
So it means that I can create the
stream, I give it to the block,
and the block is defined by the client.
And then at the end, what is important
there, there is a little optimization
there.
It means that if the stream position
is the same as the original content
size, so it means that if I inserted
100 characters, for example,
in the stream, I do not need to
copy the contents, the buffer of
the stream.
I have exactly the buffer that has
the right size, so I can directly
send it.
OK, this is a little optimization.
Another example of logic encapsulation
is the following: we want to read
from a file named 'tintin',
here using asFileReference,
and we are sending the message
readStreamDo, and we pass a block
to this method.
And here, in the implementation
of this method, what it does is
that it automatically creates the
stream, then the client block is
executed by passing the stream that
was just created before.
And the really interesting point
is that at the end of this method,
it automatically ensures that the
stream is closed.
So it means that from the client
point of view, we never deal with
the fact that we need to close the
file at the end of reading.
So if we step back a little bit,
in fact, what is really important
is to avoid spreading knowledge
in clients.
It means that you need to encapsulate
the logic inside the API.
You need to prevent clients from
forgetting something,
for example closing a file.
And one way to build this kind of
powerful API is to use block closure.
They are really useful to build
this kind of abstraction over complex
logic.
But be careful, if you abuse about
using blocks, it means that you
will have really complex API,
and I invite you to see the Blocks
vs Objects lecture.