Hello and welcome to this lecture.
In this lecture, we are going to
study the difference between having
objects and having data structures.
Yes, we are going to see how the
API exposed by a class and its instances
affects how the client uses them
and how our code is structured.
The goals for this lecture are to
see clearly the difference between
having an object and a data structure.
Because if you have an object,
you will have an API,
you will expose an API and we will
see the difference of having a poor
and a good API.
APIs are an important element in
object design and it encapsulates
how the objects are used and how
the client interacts with them.
And what are the responsibilities
that we can delegate to the objects
and what are the responsibilities
that remain in the client,
in the users of this object.
We are going to look at two concrete
examples.
We are going to analyze the
implementation of `Point` in Java
and in Pharo and how the difference
in their APIs, how it affects the
final user and the code that uses
these objects.
First, let's start seeing what we
have in the Java `Points`.
If we get this information from
the documentation of Java,
we see that `Points` understand
a series of messages.
Basically, they have a way of getting
a location.
Basically, a `Point` will return
itself as the location of a `Point`
is just a `Point`, so it returns itself.
There has a way of setting this
location, Java being a strong type
of language, we have different
implementations of this method,
depending on the type of the arguments,
but basically, we have a way of
setting the coordinates of the `Point`
using `doubles` or `int` or another
`Point`.
And also we have a way of accessing
these two coordinates.
If we see a little more of what
we have in the API, we see that
we can compare two `Points` to see
if they are equals and we can move
a "Point" to a given position.
We can set a new position to this
"Point" in the coordinate space,
and we can translate it by a distance.
Translate it will modify its x and
y coordinate, adding them the distance
in x and y that we passed as a
parameter.
Also we have implemented,
because we inherited it from the
superclass `Point2D`,
the `distance` and `clone` methods.
The distance tells us the distance
from a `Point` to another given `Point`.
As we can see, the implementations
of `Points` in Java is a super poor
data structure.
We have only method to access to
their contents, in this case,
the instance variable x and y,
and it only works to hold true integers.
It is super limited, the interface,
or what we can do with a `Point`.
What are the messages we can send
to a `Point` and what are the operations
that we can do with them?
Basically, Java `Points` are data
structures.
Let's see another example,
the `Points`, the implementations
of `Points` in Pharo.
We will see that it has a really
rich API.
We have selected some of the messages
that we can send to a `Point`,
but we can see that we have a selection
to operate on them, to normalize,
transpose or reflect about another
`Point`, different ways of calculating
distances.
We have the `crossProduct`and the
`dotProduct`.
We have a lot of mathematical operations
on top of `Points`.
We can `sum` to `Points`,
we can multiply a `Point` by a `scalar`
and we can calculate the `division`
between a `Point` and a `scalar`
so it will change its size.
And we have comparison messages,
so we can compare a `Point` to another
`Point` and we can compare `Points`.
Also, not only using absolute values,
but also using `closeTo` and different
levels of `precision`.
And we have a lot of operations
related with geometrical operations,
like calculating the `triangleArea`
or obtaining a rectangle from a
given `Point` or for a given pair
of `Points`.
So we have a really rich API.
And if we continue seeing,
this continues, they have operations
to calculate the angles that these
`Points` have with the origin,
or we calculate neighbor `Points`
or the directions or vectors in
the different directions from this
`Point`.
So we can see that we have a really
rich API that the client can use
and operate on `Points`.
Let's see a simple example that
shows why we want this great API
and rich operations from the client
`Point`.
Let's imagine we want to implement
the `crossProduct`.
It's quite easy, as we can see,
the implementation in Pharo,
it's quite easy.
It's a really simple implementation,
but it's still useful.
We can use it without knowing the
implementation.
The client does not know how to
implement it.
We don't need to duplicate it,
and more, when we see calculations
of the `crossProduct`, it's not
evident for the reader of the code
that this is the `crossProduct`,
but when we see the sending of the
message `crossProduct` column,
we see clearly that we are doing
this operation.
So it's really good not to duplicate
the code in client, but also as
a way of documentation is more clear
when we read the code.
The same happens when we are comparing
two `Points` in the implementation
that we have already in the class
`Point`, we are handling the case
of comparing the x and the y variable.
Again, it's simple to implement
in the client, but we don't want to.
And this case gets even more and
more interesting when we have an
implementation of an operation that
is more complicated.
In this case, like the degrees message
that will return us the angle that
the `Point` receiver in this message
do with the origin.
As you see, we have a lot of operations,
depending if the value of x has
different conditional code.
And also it has to handle the
conversions of radians to degrees.
And basically, it's quite an interesting
method that we don't want to implement
in the clients.
So let's see an example in Java
to make it more clear why having
a nice API, having a good API can
impact the client.
We want to make a little class that
represents a robot and it has a
position and we want to implement
in it a Go message.
We will implement the Go method
and we will pass an instance directly
to this Go method.
So the new position of the robot,
we will need to create a new `Point`
with the two values, because we
cannot have other ways of creating
`Points`, just we need to give the
x and y coordinates.
We cannot operate with `Points`.
So we have to do all the calculation
in the client side.
You can tell me that this code,
you can say that is simpler or complex,
but we have to do it all in the
client side, in the user of the `Point`.
As I say, we have to recreate this
`Point` explicitly using the distance
and the current position.
And we have to have all the arithmetic,
all the operations that we are using
with `Points` outside the `Point`.
We have to write it every time we
use a `Point`.
So this really, really,
really shallow API that exposed
in Java tends to generate the
duplication of code or logic duplication
in all the clients that are using them.
If we see it in a diagram,
we see that in the implementation
in Java, where we don't have the
degrees, we will have to implement
these method degrees in each of
the clients having not only four
times the same code, but also the
opportunity to implement it wrong.
What happens if one of the clients
does not cover all the cases for
implementing this operation?
So having a more complex or a more
rich API in `Point` as we have in
Pharo allows us to reuse this code
better and take responsibility out
from the client.
Even if they are simpler methods,
we want to take responsibility out
to ease the use of our option.
If you see now the implementation
or comparing the two implementations…
On top, we have the implementation
in Java and on bottom,
the implementation in Pharo,
we see that the implementation in Pharo,
as we have a rich operation in our
`Point`, we can take the initial
position and add another `Point`,
and this `Point`, we can create
it with the two angles with the
Cos and the Sin and scale it by
the distance and then round it to
make it an integer.
As we see, all the operations,
all the code is implemented using
operations that we delegate to `Point`,
to Number and with that,
we can implement the method much
simpler.
Of course, this difference in complexity
gets higher and higher when the
operation that we are creating is
more complex.
In the Pharo example,
we see that in Pharo `Points`,
we use the `Points` more than a
data structure.
We send a lot of messages to them
and we let them implement advanced
behavior.
This functionality is not needed
to be implemented in the client
and it's easy to reuse because our
`Points` are better units that we
want to use.
So as a conclusion, you have to
remember always that objects are
much more than data structure.
Yes, the part of the holding the
instance variable is just a part
of the object and usually is the
less important.
The most important is what are the
behavior and services the objects
do to their clients?
What is the API they expose?
The objects should give operations
that we use from upside and it should
encapsulate the logic and its internal
state.
So the client can reuse this code
that is implemented in the object,
the operation that is exposed by
the object directly without caring
how it is implemented.