Hello, in this lecture,
we will discuss something really
important.
This is that message sends are plans
for reuse.
And this lecture is related to a
previous lecture on sending a message
is making a choice.
And the self-semantics that you
already saw in the previous lecture.
This lecture is relevant to any
object-oriented language,
even if we will use Pharo as usual
in this MOOC.
And this is another essential aspect
of object-oriented design.
So what you will learn in this lecture,
this is that message sends are hooks
for subclasses.
And message sends are places where
code of subclasses can be invoked.
So let's dig into it.
Let's start with simple thinking.
Sometimes you may heard some anecdotes
like, I do not like, I like big
methods because like that,
I can see all the code in one place,
or I do not like small methods because
the code is scattered in different
methods.
And the questions are,
why large methods lead to under-optimal
design?
And why writing small methods is
a sign of good design?
And we will try to answer that by
looking at examples.
So remember, when you send a message
to an object, you are making a choice.
Because the system will select the
right method to execute,
given the receiver that will receive
the message.
You express as a programmer the
choices by adding classes in the
hierarchy: each class represents
one possible choice.
And self always represents the current
receiver.
This is the object that will receive
the message.
And the method lookup starts in
the class of the receiver.
This is automatic, except for (super)
that you already saw in another lecture.
So given all of that,
here is an example.
So we are in a Node class.
And in this class, there is a method
setWindowWithRatioForDisplay.
And the question is, what are the
possible solutions to change the
defaultNodeSize formula in subclasses?
If I want to define a new subclass
of node that changes this expression
and only this expression here,
what can I do?
Solution one, I can duplicate the code.
So for example, here,
I start by creating a new subclass,
#NodeWithMargins.
Okay, this is a new subclass of Node.
And now, I can redefine this method.
I will copy paste all the code and
I change this expression by adding
a margin.
So clearly, this is a bad solution.
So why is it bad?
This is a bad solution because when
you are duplicating code,
you are copying bugs.
So if there is a bug in the superclass
code, you will copy the bug inside
the subclass.
And if you want to change the code,
it means that you have multiple copies.
So you need to change everywhere.
In some languages such as Java,
using the private keyword prevents
duplicating the code because some
instance variables are not accessible
in the subclass.
So this is something that you should
take into account.
So what is the essence of a better
solution instead of duplicating code?
This is something that we already
saw in previous lectures.
So the idea is to define small methods
and to have a hierarchy of classes.
For example, if I define a new object,
this is an instance of C,
the C class, and I send it a bar
message.
So if you remember the lookup.
So it means that the method is lookup
in the hierarchy chain.
And then, we will find the bar method
in the A class.
It will be the code of this method
is doing a self-send here,
'self foo'.
And there is a default foo
implementation in A.
But foo is redefined in the C class
here.
And this message send will correctly
return 42.
Because the foo method will be correctly
resolved in the class of the receiver.
Now let's apply this to our example.
If I come back to my method here.
So this is the original method.
Now I can completely apply this pattern.
I can isolate the expression here
in a self-send ratio.
Okay.
And I can implement a ratio method
in the Node class here with a default
expression.
And now, what I'm able to do in
a subclass.
For example, if I have a node with
margin class, which is a subclass
of node.
And it means that I can redefine
the ratio method.
I can, using a super send,
call the super method to reuse the code,
the default implementation of the
ratio and add a margin of 10.
So in the general way,
there is no need to invoke the super
implementation.
This is just because,
in this case, we want to extend it.
So we reuse the default implementation
and we add a new margin.
Okay.
So now I have a new subclass that
can use the regular method
setWindowWithRatioForDisplay.
But it will use a different ratio
that has been refined in the subclass.
Another step.
Now, we have this version of the
method in the Node class.
And the question is, how to use
a different UINode in subclasses.
If I want to create a new subclass
that does not use an UINode instance,
but a new class, another node,
another kind of node,
how to do that?
You should think one minute on your
side.
And the answer is to use exactly
the same pattern.
So now, we can extract exactly the
same way this instance creation
into a self method, into another
method here, create UINode that
I can implement in the Node class.
And here, I have exactly the same
expression as before.
I instantiate a UINode.
But now, it opens the door to redefine
this method in a subclass.
For example, in a subclass,
I can redefine this create UINode
to change it.
But I can even do better.
What I can do is that I can here
isolate the name of the class in
another self-send, the UINode class
here.
So it means that I can directly
return the name, the class UINode.
So now subclasses just need to redefine
the UINode class and not the whole
expression.
It's not mandatory to redefine the
create UINode, the whole method.
So this is a good practice to define
methods of written classes.
It helps a lot extensibility in
subclasses by redefining it.
And it's really easy in Pharo because
classes are regular objects,
but this is not the case in all
languages.
So there are many takeaways in these
lectures.
So you should remember that small
methods are a good sign of good design.
Because we give name to the expressions.
We saw it with the ratio or with
the creation of a UINode.
They encapsulate some complexity.
And if we give a nice name to methods,
it means that it is easier to read
for the programmer.
It is testing because if I have
smaller methods, it is easier to
write tests, to test specific portions
of the code.
It supports self-send messages,
like that, it opens the door for
subclasses to redefine part of the
behavior.
So it means that there are potential
hooks for subclasses.
So if you look at it,
object-oriented programming is a
kind of Emmental-oriented programming.
This is a Swiss cheese in which
we have holes like that.
And holes are filled up by subclasses.
In fact, in superclasses,
we already create holes with self-send
messages that will be filled up
or will be adapted by subclasses.
So in conclusion, code can be reused
and refined by subclasses.
Sending a message to self in a class
defines a hook.
And subclasses can use this hook
to inject variations.
So at the end, prefer small methods
in your code.
It gives names to the expressions.
And each message to small method
is an extensibility point for
subclasses.