- Hello everyone.
In this MOOC, we have about four
lectures that are specific to Pharo
and this one is one of them.
This is what we call a code idiom.
Here, I want to look at how people
use `printString` and `asString`
and how to use them well.
So, the goal is to rethink what
is the creation of intermediary
objects and consequently,
how we avoid creating spurious objects.
We don't need to create objects
just for the sake of creating objects.
So, we should understand what we
are doing.
And sometimes what we see is that
we are doing things without thinking
too much.
I will show you some bad implementations
that were in Pharo that normally
we fixed.
So, let's look at it.
So, the context.
If we set the stage, in Java,
this is toString, in Pharo,
we call it `printString`.
If I create an object,
`Apple`, if I send a message
`printString` to this,
I will get an Apple.
If I have a date object and I send
a message `printString`,
it will tell me, "Okay,
we are `2nd April 2023`".
So, this means that `printString`
returns a textual representation
of the receiver.
That's why we have the quotes here.
This is not a date; this is a string.
So how this is implemented?
On the class object, the message
`printString` is implemented as
calling `printStringLimitedTo`.
This is to avoid having a too-large
string.
And what you see is that this method
calls `printOn`.
Basically, you will see that in
the Hook and Template lecture,
so I don't want to go into detail there.
But what you see is that we call
the `printOn` method on the receiver.
For example, the method `printOn`
in `MessageTally` is calling
`displayString` and this one is doing:
"Oh I want to first write something
on the stream.
After, on this stream,
I want to place a parenthesis and
a character to open something.
And after, I will do this,
and I will come back to that because
this is the problem.
And once I have finished,
I will close that with a parenthesis".
So, this piece of code looks normal,
but there is a problem.
The problem is that basically
`printString` here is doing a recursive
call and it's creating yet a new stream.
So, let's look at it.
When I have my `MessageTally` object,
so if I have my `MessageTally` object,
I have a `MessageTally` object,
it will receive a first message
`printString`.
This message `printString` will
create a stream.
So, let's imagine that a stream
is something like that,
where we can put elements inside.
So, in the first place,
it will put: "Oh yes,
I will put this…" Sorry,
it's not like that, this is like that.
"I will put a parenthesis.
And at the end, I will close my
parenthesis." And to compute the tally,
which is basically a number,
I send `printString` again.
So, this means that to be able to
fill up this stuff, the system is
creating yet another stream.
So, if my number is, I don't know,
2055, it will say 2055 as a string.
So, it will put the character two,
the character zero, the character five,
the character five.
And then, it will copy this into
this place.
And the idea is that why do we need
to create this stream?
It is completely useless because
the system could use this one instead.
Because here, the system creates
a stream.
Then to fill up this stream,
it creates another stream.
Then it copies the element from
this stream to that one,
while it could use this one.
So, what is the solution?
And it's a little mistake that we
often make.
Basically, it is much better to use that.
So, this means that I have my
`printString` that creates my stream.
I put my parenthesis here and I
call `print`.
And what is `print` doing?
First, `print` is implemented on
the stream.
So, this is the implementation.
It just said; "Oh, an object!" Meaning,
"I will ask the argument to print
itself on myself".
This means that here,
if `tally` is a number,
like 2055, then I will execute the
`printOn` method to say:
"Can you place your character on me?" So,
this means that suddenly I will
just put the character.
So, the object returned by `self tally`,
which is a number basically,
will just execute its own methods
and put the characters one by one
and close.
You see that in this solution,
there is only one stream because
what you should understand is that
a stream is like a basket.
And you say, "Oh, can you put your
eggs in my basket?" And then you
don't need to create another basket
to put your eggs in and then move
your eggs from that basket to the
other basket.
There is one, so let's use it.
Let's look at another example.
You see here again, in the method
printProtocol blah blah blah,
a stream is created.
Okay, so the system creates a stream.
We put things inside.
So, we have our stream,
we will write `protocol`,
P-R-O-T-O-C-O-L, and then again,
we will create another stream to
place something else inside,
like accessing, for example,
I imagine, because this is a protocol.
And then, we will return the contents
and move it there.
The right solution is just to do that.
Meaning, okay, you have a stream,
you write `protocol`,
they are placed in that,
and then you ask the object protocol:
"Hey, object protocol,
can you print yourself on that stream?
Please write yourself in my basket."
"Okay." And it will write accessing,
for example, here.
So, just by paying attention that
a method like this one,
`printString`, is actually creating
a stream, we can avoid creating
it because we know, "Oh yes,
I should work on this one,
not on the one that I created just
because I forgot, and I created
one that was not necessary." You
have the same with `asString`.
Each time you use `asString` inside
the `printOn` method,
you basically are creating yet another
stream and this is not necessary.
So, you should really pay attention
when you program, do I need or not
to use this method `asString`,
or can I just use the `printOn` method?
It's always good to check because
we don't need to create these
intermediate streams.
And you see here, we could say,
"Oh, yes, what is the problem?
This is just one stream." Yes,
but if you have a list with thousands
of objects and you want to get the
textual representation like in a
list or a browser, then you will
create thousands of objects for nothing.
You will create thousands of
intermediary streams for nothing.
So, that's why we wrote this little
lecture so that you can really
understand when you should use or
not `printString` and how to use
`printOn`.
The conclusion is that basically,
it's always nice to check a bit
the protocol, like `printString`
or `printOn`.
You see, I look at the implementation
in Pharo and then we fix many of
them because people were always
making the mistake.
So, I guess that now there are even
quality rules that check that.
What you should understand is that
streams are really powerful containers.
They are like baskets.
When you pass them around,
you don't have to create another one.
You can just write inside or place
objects inside a stream.
They are made for that.
And there is no need to create
intermediate streams from just basic
sub-processes.