Hello, in this lecture,
we will discuss about hooks and
templates.
So the goal or the outline of this
lecture is the following.
So we will look at hooks and template
methods and what are they.
We will exemplify them on two examples
from the Pharo code library,
the 'printString/printOn': case
and the 'copy' case.
First of all, remember,
when you send a message to an object,
there is a choice.
The system will select the right
method to execute according to the
receiver.
And then, each class you define
defines one possible choice.
Self-sends are plans for reuse and
self-sends defines hooks,
places where subclasses can inject
variations and this is what we will
revisit inside this lecture.
So what is a template method?
A template method specifies a skeleton
with hooks.
So here, you have an example in a class.
So this is an AbstractClass.
And inside this template method,
there are some self-send messages here.
And if you look at it,
the 'hookMethod1' is a concrete method.
So it means that there is a default
definition inside the 'AbstractClass'.
But the 'hookMethod2' is in italics.
So this is an abstract method.
Subclasses must redefine the
'hookMethod2'.
And self-send messages,
we already saw it in a previous lecture,
they are hooks, places where subclasses
can inject variation by redefining
those methods.
So this is the example that we already
discussed.
If I send the bar message to the obj,
and obj is an instance of the class C,
it means that here, it will correctly
return 42 because bar,
this is a kind of template method.
Foo is a hook, and it has been redefined
in the C class.
Let's study this on a real example,
a real code from the Pharo library.
And for example, we will look at
the `printString` implementation.
If I send a `printString` message
to an object, so here,
this is a delay, a delay for a certain
amount of seconds.
So here, for this delay,
the `printString` method will return
a string representation of the object.
So it means that here,
it says this is 'a Delay',
an instance of the Delay class,
and the duration of this delay is
this amount of milliseconds.
So how is this `printString` method
implemented?
So in fact, it is implemented in
the object class here,
and there is a self-send,
okay, that specifies the limit.
By default, the limit is 50,000
characters.
And if it is longer than that,
it will be truncated.
Okay, this is not really important.
What is important is this method.
And if you look at the code of this
method, do you see the hook where it is?
This is this self-send here,
'self printOn'.
And if we look at the implementation
of this `printOn` method,
but before looking at the default
implementation of it,
let's have a look of sending
`printString` to different instances.
If I send a `printString` message
to a node instance, what it displays
is a Node.
But if I send the `printString`
message to an Apple, it displays
an Apple.
So we can see that the article here
is different.
And now we can have a look at the
default implementation in the object
class.
So what does it do?
Is that basically it will get the
class name of the object,
and then it will test if the first
letter is a vowel or not,
and according to that,
it will display the correct article.
This is the default implementation
of `printOn` in object.
But now this default implementation
can be refined.
And let's have a look at the Delay
class.
Because the Delay class,
it displays the article,
the name of the class,
but also the duration.
And where does it come from?
It comes from the fact that the
`printOn` method, the hook,
has been redefined in the Delay class.
And this is an extension of the
default behavior because there is
a super call here.
So we reuse the default implementation
from object that displays the article
and class name, and then we extend
it by adding the duration of the
delay between parenthesis here.
Okay, so in the Delay class,
we extended the default implementations
of the hook `printOn`.
But we can go further.
We can completely redefine the behavior
of the `printOn`.
For example, for `Booleans` that
you already saw in a previous lecture,
if I send `printString` to a `Boolean`,
it directly writes a string
representation of the `Boolean`.
And since there are only two `Booleans`
in the system, for example,
for false, there is only one instance
of the False class, which is named
false, and on the False class,
there is a definition of the `printOn`
method.
And inside this method,
it directly prints 'false' with a
lower case because this is the name
of the unique instance of the False
class.
Let's have a look at another example.
For example, the `Interval` class.
Inside the `Interval` class,
the `printOn` method has been redefined
to display the start index of the
`Interval`, which is displayed there,
then the stop index of the `Interval`,
which is displayed there,
and maybe the step of the `Interval`
there, just by redefining the `printOn`
hook inside the `Interval` class.
Let's have a look at another example
of the hooks and templates mechanisms.
For example, copying objects.
Copying objects might be complex
because usually, there is a graph
of objects that are interconnected
all together, and there might be
some cycles between objects,
and each class may have a different
strategy to `copy` instances of
themselves.
A simple solution for that is to
use the template method and hooks
`copy` and post `copy` that we will
analyze now.
So let's have a look.
In the object class, I have the
`copy` method that is there.
And the implementation of the `copy`
method is this one.
So the shallow`copy` is another method,
which is a primitive.
And what does the primitive do is
that it just copies the receiver
and not its dependencies.
So all instance variables or all
things that are around this object
are not copied, they are shared
with the `copy`.
But we have a hook there,
another method, which is post`copy`.
And there is a default implementation
in object of post`copy` that just
returns self.
So we might think that it is useless.
Why having a post`copy` that just
resends self?
And now, we can analyze what we
can do with that by extension with
subclasses.
Let's have a look at the Bag class.
So a bag is a subclass of collection.
And a bag, here, if I have a bag B,
this is implemented by having a
`Dictionary` in the bag.
So here, I have a `Dictionary`.
And the `Dictionary` has some
associations.
For example, association one.
And an association has a key,
key one, and a value,
value one.
And it might have multiple associations,
etc.
If I want to duplicate this bag
B with another bag, B prime,
there, and I want to be able to
insert new elements or to remove
new elements, existing elements
from those two bags independently.
I don't want to have too much sharing
between them.
And for that, I will redefine the
'postCopy' inside the bag and I
will extend it.
So it means that I will copy the bag,
B will become B'.
But I will, I should also copy
the `Dictionary`.
Otherwise, they will be shared.
And I don't want that the `Dictionary`
is shared between the original bag
and the copy.
So it means that here I will recursively
send a copy to the `contents`,
which is a `Dictionary`.
So the `Dictionary` will be copied.
So my copy will have its own dict'
there.
And now, is it enough?
Because if I just do that,
it means that the association will
be shared.
And if I change the value at a key,
at a specific key, it means that
it will not work.
So we can have a look at the
implementation of 'postCopy' inside
the `Dictionary`.
And here, we can see that in
`Dictionary`, this is recursively
sent to 'association'.
So 'associations' are also copied
when I `copy` a `Dictionary`.
So coming back for my previous drawing,
it means that I will also have a
duplication of association.
And the only things that are shared
are the real objects.
So it means that my two bags,
B and B', are completely
independent.
I can insert new values and I can
remove values.
They will work independently.
The only things that are shared
are the real objects and the keys.
So in conclusion, Hooks and Templates
are a very common pattern.
The template method sets the context,
and Hooks specify some variations
that can be refined in subclasses.
Usually, this is done by self-send.
It means that we can provide a default
implementation in the class.
And this can be refined in subclasses.
But sometimes, this is not a self-send.
Sometimes, I can delegate by sending
a message to another object and
it opens the space for dispatch.
And this is related to Strategy
Design lecture that you will see
later on.