- Hello.
In this lecture, I want to give
you a little introduction to Design
Patterns.
So what will we see?
We will see what are Design Patterns,
why they are good.
We will also show an aspect that
is often not fully treated in lecture.
This is that design patterns are
not a panacea.
So this means that sometimes you
should not use them, and give some
examples.
So in fact, Design Pattern,
they come from this book that is
The Timeless Way of Building,
that has been written by Christopher
Alexander.
He was an architect, a real architect,
not a software architect,
that tried to write patterns so
that people can build their own
house and cities.
So he developed patterns and pattern
languages.
And then he applied, they try to
apply that, I guess that is in Mexico
or something like that,
where people could build their house.
It didn't really work.
So from that perspective,
I think that Christopher Alexander
is not very well known as an architect,
but in software and in particular
in object-oriented design,
it worked wonderfully.
And this is what I want to show
you with this little introduction.
So basically, design pattern are
recurrent solutions to design problems.
The idea is that a Design Pattern
will capture some similar problem
that you have at the design level,
and they are based on the idea that
experts in fact often solve the
same problems with the same solutions.
And basically, Design Patterns,
there are also pros and cons,
okay?
If you apply this pattern,
you will gain this, but you will
have this disadvantage.
And something that is more important
from my perspective, this is that
Design Patterns are literature.
So basically, teaching Design Pattern
is possible.
This is just painful usually for
the teacher and I really encourage
you to read them because originally,
they were written as knowledge that
should be read.
And I can say that because I've
wrote some Design Patterns in the
past and I saw that really when
I'm teaching.
So what are Design Patterns?
So in fact, Design Patterns,
they are elegant solutions that
usually a novice could not really
think about.
They should be generic because we
don't want to have something that
is super specific to a super small
language or something like that.
This is absolutely not interesting
because it should be language agnostic,
so they should be generic and
independent also of a type system
or reflective pictures or things
like that.
Usually, they are well proven.
So this means that you don't want
something that is totally ad-hoc
and that works on only one case,
but that is working most of the time.
When you have this problem,
you can apply this pattern.
They should be simple because most
of them are simple, but the cool
aspect of them is that they can
be composed together to be more
complex solutions.
So basically, over the MOOC,
we will show you some Design Patterns
that are building bricks that you
can assemble to produce nice design.
What you should pay attention is
that you should also always be skeptical
and take everything with a pinch of salt.
This means that there are stupid
patterns.
So in some books, you have,
for example, the supersuper,
which means that maybe one guy invented
that and he thought that this is
a Design Pattern, but this is not,
this is just a stupid pattern.
So the important point,
in fact, Design Pattern are names.
In fact, they create a vocabulary.
For example, you have Hook and Template,
Factory, Composite, Visitor…
Those are names.
And what I like is that when you
get this vocabulary, you can talk
at lunch or on the blackboard with
your colleagues and you all share
the same vocabulary, that is at
the same time abstract because this
is an abstraction, but very precise.
So, for example, it happened to us that,
for example, we discuss,
oh yes, I use composite,
and we all know what a composite means.
So again, read them because like
that you will really understand
the fine grained aspect of the pattern.
In this lecture, we will give you
a good basis and discuss sometimes
some advanced point, but read them,
this is the message, if you didn't
get it.
So what the Design Patterns are not?
So Design Patterns are not just
one implementation.
They are illustrated with one possible
implementation.
But what you should always consider
is that the implementation is less
important than the intent of the
Design Pattern.
This is what I will show you in a moment,
and that you can bend the implementation
to your own needs if you understand
what was the intent.
The element of a Design Pattern.
So usually, a pattern has a name
that is basically your vocabulary.
It has an intent that describes
the goal of the Design Pattern.
It has a problem description saying,
okay, we are in this context and
we would like to do that,
but we don't want to use condition
or we want variation or we want
something that is modular,
etc, etc.
So this is really the context.
And then after, you have a description
that is usually generic in terms
of what are the elements that compose
the Design Pattern and what are
the relationship and responsibility
between these elements and how do
they interact.
This is what is called collaboration.
And after, usually, we have the
consequences.
So this means, if you apply the pattern,
what are the results and what are
the trade-offs that you get.
So I just want to illustrate that
with the strategy Design Pattern.
We will see it again later in the
lecture.
But it's interesting to look at it now.
So the strategy Design Pattern,
the intent.
This is define a family of algorithms,
encapsulate each of these algorithms
in a separate class and define each
class with the same interface so
that we can interchange them.
So you see, this is the intention.
We do not discuss about the
implementation at this level.
Now a possible implementation,
this is that you have what we call
a user that defines a strategy.
So let's look at a possible
implementation.
Here, you have a user class that
has a field strategy.
This field, in fact, will hold an
instance of one of the subclasses
of this hierarchy.
What is important to see is that here,
the user class will have one operation
and that this operation delegates
to the operation of the strategy.
And what it means?
It means that at runtime,
I can put an instance.
So imagine that I have an instance here.
So this is strategy one.
And this one, this is strategy two.
At runtime, my instance of user
may have a pointer to this guy or
a pointer to this guy and change
dynamically.
In any case, the fact that I have
the same operation will make sure
that I can switch dynamically and
that when I switch, I get automatically
the correct operation that is invoked.
So strategies, for example,
are good to be able to encapsulate
different behavior.
So this means that I can have one
here and one there.
And they are based also on this
idea of delegation.
So this means that the user will
delegate to the strategy a part
of its behavior.
This is one implementation.
And then, there is the question
of do I pass or not the user?
This means that here,
with this, do I pass the user or
not to the strategy, the boundary
between the user and the strategy?
Because often, what you do is that
at the beginning of your design,
the user and the strategy code are
mixed together and then you cut
it and you separate and you said,
okay, I have the user on one end
and the strategy on the other end.
But this means that the strategy
may need to have access to the state
of the user and this is not always
possible.
So then, you will have really what
we call a design decision that says,
okay, should I pass or not?
And if I pass the user to the strategy,
what does it mean in terms of API
of the user?
So typically, if you look at a text
editor, you will have a text editor
with a formatter.
So usually, we will ask the editor,
oh, we want to format some text
and the editor will say,
oh, no problem, I will ask my formatter.
So what is this formatter?
That will be one instance of these
classes.
So maybe I will use the fast formatter
or maybe I will use the slow formatter
or a new formatter, or a formatter
that just does nothing and returns
the text.
And then, it means that what you
see that the editor will just forward
the message format to the formatter
and each of the strategy will implement
the message format, the method format
in its own way.
So this means that like that,
from the editor perspective,
I can say, oh, you know,
now I have a large code,
so I would like to use the
FastFormatter or I want for it to have
a beautiful code, so I will use,
for example, the SlowFormatter.
And internally, each of these classes
can have its own decision.
So what you see here is that in
the FastFormatter, the format method
will just invoke this protected method.
That's why we put this #,
the protected method formatFastColoring.
Andin the case of the SlowFormatter,
I will have the same with the format
slow, but precise coloring.
And the idea, this is really based
on this delegation.
So this link is really super important.
And what you see that the design
is really simple.
The user of the strategy delegates
to the strategy.
So let's step back.
So this was an illustration of the
Design Pattern.
In fact, if you look at the books,
they have different categories and
usually, the categories you have
Creational Design Patterns.
So they pay attention to how do
we instantiate object and configure
classes.
You have Structural Patterns.
This is how do we compose class
in larger structures and separate
interfaces and implementation,
or you have more Behavioral Design
Patterns, which are more like
algorithms, like the strategy,
for example, or division of
responsibility.
So if we look a bit at the list,
I put in bold the one that you will
see in the lecture later.
So the builder.
So the builder, this is how can
I create a complex object but in
a programmatic way, or the singleton,
this is how can I get a class with
only one instance.
And for this lecture,
you should pay attention because
most people believe that they get it,
but most people get it wrong.
So you will see that this lecture,
while the singleton is very simple,
there are some challenges that are
worth understanding.
From the structural point of view,
the Composite Pattern,
this is a really natural pattern
that is supporting nested data structure
like trees, document and things
like that.
We will look at the Decorator.
So the Decorator, this is how can
we dynamically attach a new behavior
to an object.
And we will go over the Flyweight.
So the Flyweight, what is interesting,
this is how can we share and manage
a lot of objects without duplicating
them and making sure that we optimize
a bit the space.
From the Behavioral Pattern,
we will look at Command.
So Command, this is a pattern that
is turning an action into an object.
So it reifies operation.
This is what you get behind do and
redo or undo and redo.
The State Pattern, this means that
if your domain can be really expressed
as a state machine, then we can
apply the State Pattern.
So we saw the strategy.
So this means that we delegate behavior
to objects that are responsible
to manage a part of a computation.
The Template Method,
that this is really the core of
object-oriented programming.
This is a Template Method.
This is also named Hook and Template.
So this is how can you make,
from a superclass, make sure that
the code of your subclass gets injected
and used instead of your code.
And this is really the extension.
This is the extension of object-oriented
programming when we use inheritance.
And we will go over Visitor.
So basically, Visitor,
this is, I want to have first class
operation that are expressed on
a Composite Pattern, but in a modular
way.
This is one of the most complex
Design Patterns that we will present
in this MOOC.
And what we will see is that it
is using Double Dispatch.
So we will do a Double Dispatch lecture,
so that you can understand a Double
Dispatch, but also how this is used
in the visitor.
In this MOOC, we will present also
some other Design Patterns.
One is called Null Object.
This is how can we turn a Null Behavior
into an object instead of having
condition in the code.
And Type Object, Type Object,
this is something that you get when
you want to separate,
for example, the kind of object
from the object itself.
So for example, if you want to represent
a DVD and the actual DVD.
So the DVD as okay, this is this
video that I want to watch,
from the actual physical DVD.
If you have a renting,
if you rent a DVD, physical object,
then you want to model that as a
type object.
So this is a bit abstract,
but you will see that in the lecture,
it is a lot clearer.
What you should pay attention is
that Design Patterns are not a panacea.
So what is important to understand
is that after this lecture and once
you have read the book also,
this is important to understand
when you do not want to apply a
Design Pattern.
So once, I saw a company that was
testimony and they said,
yes, we implemented in this application,
we implemented all the Design Patterns
from the catalog.
And for me, this is a big warning.
You don't want to implement all
the Design Patterns from the catalog
in your software.
You just want to use the one that
makes sense.
So it looks okay when I say it,
but I can tell you that when I was
discussing with this company,
I was really scared.
So this means that people think
like that and you should not.
So what you should pay attention
is that Design Patterns make your
software more complex.
You will have more classes,
you will have more indirections,
you have more messages.
So this is important to understand
when you don't want to apply them.
A second alert, this is that Design
Pattern is about intent and tradeoffs.
I need this goal and to reach this goal,
I will have to pay the price somehow.
And you should not confuse intent
and implementation.
This is what I try to show you with
the strategy.
You see the intention of the strategy.
This is to define a family of algorithms
that we can interchange.
There is nothing about the
implementation.
You can do it via delegation and
this is the good way to do it via
delegation.
But the implementation is not the
intention.
About the book.
So there are several books and the
one that I like, there is Design
Patterns.
So this one, this is the seminal one.
This is the first one by Gamma and
others.
This is called GoF, the Gang of Four,
because there were four authors.
And there is the one that I prefer.
This is the Design Patterns Smalltalk
Companion, because it is better.
Let's say it like that.
Of course, I am a guy that is doing
Pharo, so I'm biased.
Now I want to show you what I found
a long time ago on Amazon.
And there was this guy,
Nicolas Weidmann from Zurich.
He said, okay, I'm a C++ programmer.
I've been developing in C++.
for nine years.
And I work, I have the GoF book.
I've never liked it.
So and he said, the Smalltalk Companion
is much easier to read and to
understand.
So when I read that, I was like,
oh wow, that's cool that he is
mentioning that because I like the
Smalltalk one.
But I'm not a C++ programmer.
In any case, you can read both of them,
they are cool.
So in fact Design Patterns are reusable
solution to common problems that
are based on experience from real
systems.
That's really what is interesting,
this is that the design has been
validated and the pros and cons
has been discussed by people over
multiple years.
So this is very interesting to
understand them.
They are also names of abstractions
and they create these common vocabulary
so that we can go much faster to
discuss design on the blackboard.
And for me, this is the key aspect of it,
this is in the communication,
how can I discuss my design with
somebody else so that you can criticize
it.
And they often separate modularity.
So this means that you will have
the interface separation and
implementation.
And these Design Patterns,
they are really the basis of most
of the available frameworks and
toolkits that you have nowadays.
So they are really worth looking
at them.