Hello everybody.
So in this lecture, I want to show
you how we can go from the usage
of a global variable to a parameter.
This is basic, but this is really
an important point because it will
improve the testability of your
application.
So the goal of this lecture,
this is to show that globals,
in fact global variables are not
a fatality.
Some of them can be turned into
computational parameters such as
instance variable.
And then, during the process,
we should understand that as usual
they are pro and cons.
Sometimes you can do it,
sometimes you cannot.
At least this is interesting to
know the idea so that you can apply
it or not.
So what I will do is that I will
take a simple example with a
Transcript usage in Pharo.
People use that a lot and that
introduces some problems.
I will show you how we can cure
that and then step back and rethink
a bit the approach.
This is related to the bad usage
of the Singleton Design Pattern,
which I call a plague in fact.
So let's look at it.
So the `Transcript` in Pharo,
this is a kind of STD output where
this is a global variable that is
pointing to a log stream instance
and everybody can write on this stream.
So here for example, you see that
the compiler wrote that the class
counter has a count instance variable
that is undeclared.
So we don't care of what is written.
What we care is that this `Transcript`
is basically a global variable pointing
to a log file.
Usually, people write such kinds
of expressions, `Transcript` show foo,
cr for carriage return.
This means introduce a new line.
This is a bit outdated API and they
do something.
So that's okay.
When you do it like that in development,
it can give you some traces.
Usually, it can work.
Let's say it like that because if
you have too many of them you will
not see anything in your log at the end.
So maybe it's better to use a debugger,
but this is another discussion.
So now what is the core of the problem?
This is when you have `Transcript`
show expression like that in released
software.
Because if you have that in your domain,
it means that somehow you want to
have a specific log.
That this log is potentially part
of your domain or that you want
to do something with it.
Else, you would have removed it
when you deployed your software.
So now, there is also another related
issue.
This is, how do you make sure that
those logs are correct?
So what if we want to write tests
that the logging that you have in
your software is logging correctly
what it should log?
Because of course, you can write
your code like that and pray and
expect that it will work.
Or if you are a good software engineer,
what you want to do, you want to
make sure that yes, these traits
are super important for my domain
and I want to have the guarantee
that they are there and that they
contain the right information.
Because if you rely on this information,
then you should test it.
This is a problem because first,
maybe you don't want the extra
dependency to `Transcript` because
`Transcript` is a tool from the
Pharo IDE.
So why do you want to depend on
a tool from the Pharo IDE?
But why not?
More important, your log is mixed
with all the logs of the system.
Because everybody that use the
`Transcript` will just write logs there.
So you don't want to have your log
that are dirtied by other people
and you want to control this stuff,
especially if the logs are important
for your case, because you want
to analyze them or things like that.
You don't want to have to jump over
the log of other tools that maybe
only happen when you build on the
server or not.
And what is really more important
is that you cannot easily write
tests to be sure that your log is up,
is happening correctly.
And for me, this is really the key
aspect of using a global variable.
So the solution, basically,
this is to apply modern object-oriented
techniques.
Let's call them locality and
encapsulation.
So the idea, this is instead of
pointing to a global variable,
I will just introduce in my domain
an instance variable that I will
initialize and that I will control.
So this is what I am doing here.
So previously, if you see in this class,
make abstract block, there was this
log in the iterate.
And now, what we will do,
we just said, oh, you know,
I want in the initialize,
I will create, I will add a new
instance variable.
I initialize to a string that I control.
And so, in another place in the code,
for example, they were using closeMe.
Here, I use the logStream to put
information in that log string.
The side effect is that you can
get the butter and the money for
the butter.
So this means that if I introduce
a setter that will be able to let
people modify the stream in which
I will write, then you could pass
a `Transcript` there.
So this means that you can say,
oh, you know, you have this
MicAbstractBlock, now I want that
it uses the `Transcript` when I'm
in development mode.
But when I am testing,
I want not to use the `Transcript`,
but to use the default stream that
I have initialized.
The bonus, and for me,
this is the key aspect of that,
is that you can write your test
in isolation.
You can say, oh, for my test,
can you please use this stream?
And you will not have the information
of all the other people that are
writing in the log.
So if we look at it visually,
imagine that you have your object.
So this object refer to the `Transcript`
and write something in the `Transcript`.
This one write something in the
`Transcript`.
There will be another one that will
write something in the `Transcript`.
And I have no idea of the order
that will be the total mess.
Now what we can do is that basically
what we did is that we turn this
object using a global variable into
an object that have a state and said,
oh, you know, I want to use this state.
Oh, I want this one to use this state.
It is this own state.
So here, it will be a different one.
And this one, that will be another one,
you know, like, oh, yes,
they are nice little state.
Each of my object will have its
own private state.
And if I want, I can say,
oh, you know, guys, you two you
share the same state because for
I want that you share that you mix
your log in the system,
I don't care.
So we went from a system that is
monolithic.
There is only one `Transcript` from
everybody to a stream pair instances.
And that's super nice.
So we went from a monolithic system
to a parameterizable system.
So now I can decide what I want to do.
So in this solution, I can decide.
In this one, I cannot.
I have only one.
So okay, there is only one.
You want more?
There is only one.
So do you see the pattern?
So let's look at this piece of code.
So this is a scroll bar,
defaultScrollBarTarget.
Whatever it is, we don't really care.
We create an instance of a text area.
And then, we set the background
color of this text area.
And here we said, oh,
color.
I want a light gray and I want a
very much lighter gray.
And then, we can ask yourself,
oh, and what if I am in a dark or
in a light theme and I want another
color?
I cannot do anything because here,
this is that would be that one,
which means this color here,
that is here.
And I don't want that.
So what is the solution for that?
Because I out coded here,
basically the color.
So this means that there will be
only one, this light gray color.
And in fact, now, if we just do
the following, we said,
okay, in my initialized methods,
which is a constructor,
this is the equivalent of a constructor
in Java, I will introduce an instance
variable, default background color,
where I assign my color and I pass here.
I don't use this color,
but I use this variable.
It means that if I have a setter
like here with this setter,
I will do it.
I will go from a design where I
add my rub.
I have an instance of RubScrollText,
which has one color.
And I have a RubScrollText that
point to the same color to a design
that is like, oh, yes,
this is my little color.
I use this one.
This is my little, I have a color
that is the background,
the default background color.
And each of them can have their own.
Once I am in this situation,
I can decide or not to share the same.
It's just a pointer.
So I can say, please share this one,
but not you.
And here you are green,
for example.
So you see, I show you the pattern
with the `Transcript` and then I
show you the pattern with a color,
which has nothing to do with that.
But this is exactly the same problem.
This is you will go from a monolithic
system to a parameterized system.
So when you think about it,
instance variable are state of object.
This is what we said okay in
object-oriented design,
the instance variable represent
the state of object.
But what you can see is that instance
variable, they are also kind of
the parameters of your computation.
So you perform a computation.
And then, this computation is taking
the parameters into account.
And then, you from the outside or not,
you can change the parameters that
you want to do and you can control
your computation.
So instead of having only one parameter,
you can add the parameters that you want.
And that's make a big difference.
So what is interesting is that this
can be shared between classes or not.
You can see there is this shared
variable in Pharo, which are
approximately the same as static
variable in Java.
And there is a lecture.
So we will see that we have several
lectures.
We have a module that is called
Sharing Object.
And we will talk about sharing,
how we can share or not those values.
But you can start to think about
sharing when you have more than one.
Because if you have one,
it means that everybody shares.
So there is only one solution,
everybody shares.
And we want to have a discourse
that is a bit more fine-grained.
Maybe some of them want to share,
some of them do not want.
So what you see is that about globals
variables, the pro is that this is easy.
You don't have to have an instance
variable in your domain.
Sometimes you cannot.
So you cannot add an instance variable
to your domain object.
You don't have to initialize such
globals because it exists already there.
Or there is one system that will
create it and then all the other ones,
they will use it.
The cons there basically,
you have only one.
So you cannot have two.
By construction, you cannot have two.
So imagine you cannot have,
for example, two themes side by side.
You cannot see the user interface
in white and black at the same time
because there is only one.
So it can be black for everybody
or white for everybody.
So you cannot compare.
Testing is difficult.
When you have a global variable,
if your tests are doing side effect
on the global variable,
you may destroy it or you may destroy
invariant because sometimes in your
tests, you want to test some extreme
cases.
So this means that when you want
to write test and you have globals
variable, you should really be careful.
You should be able to copy the state
of the global variable,
do your computation, modification,
and restore the state after.
And sometimes you cannot.
So we should always go with care
when you have a global variable.
And the cons is that when you have
a global, you cannot initialize
it or specialize it for your context.
It is there.
The parameterization.
So what I show is that this is
interesting to have it,
but sometimes you just cannot.
You cannot add an instance variable
to your object.
Why?
Because maybe you have millions
of objects and if you add an instance
variable to each of your millions
of objects, then you will have two
millions of objects.
So it's always this tension between
can we do it or not?
Maybe you have a fixed size for
your object and this is inherited
and you have a constraint that is
inherited in the database and you
cannot change the database.
So you cannot change your object.
So from that perspective,
there will be lecture on sharing
and you have the Flyweight Design
Pattern that is about how can we
control a bit the memory explosion
or reuse or things like that.
So what I suggest, this is the last
point.
Here this is at least factor in a method,
a single entry point to your global
usage because maybe in the future,
it will be easier for you to experiment
or to change.
So what I mean here is that instead
of saying my method M1 global,
my method M2 global access,
my method M3 global access,
I think that you see the pattern.
You don't do that.
What you do is that you do M1 self
use Global, M2 self use Global,
M3, of course, this is more complex
than that.
Usually, you have code around.
So you have code around all these
methods and things like that.
And then you define a little method
that is called use global and your
method use global, you will write
global.
So like that.
So if we scratch that,
it means that if I want to change
this design, I just have to change
this method.
If I change use global,
I can modify all the places that
were using directly my global variable
and I can experiment.
So like that, this is what I said
by factor the global usage to these
future changes.
So in general, my suggestion,
this is avoid as much as possible
the use of global variables.
They go against object-oriented design.
From that perspective,
I would say as a general reflex,
try to avoid to use Singleton Design
Pattern.
So first, you will have to read
the lecture, check the lecture that
we wrote.
But there is a high chance that
you don't need a Singleton.
And once you will have watched the
Singleton lecture, you will know
what I mean.
In general, Singleton,
which are globals and global variables,
make your code less modular and
less testable.
And this is always a problem.