- Hello,
welcome to this lecture.
In this lecture, we are going to
talk about the types and the method
lookup.
Basically, we are going to start
remembering how the lookup works.
We are going to talk about what
are static types and how it reacts
with dynamic types, how the type
checker works in the middle and
how it affects the method lookup.
So first, let's start remembering
how the method lookup,
how is resolved when we send a message.
Sending a message basically is a
two-step process.
The first is to look up the method
that matches the message that we
are sending and execute this method
on the receiver.
So every time we are sending a message,
we have to start looking up the
method to execute and then we'll
execute it on the receiver.
Always the lookup starts in the
class of the receiver.
So we start in this case,
we have the aColoredRectangle,
that is 'ColoredRectangle' class,
we are going to start looking at it.
If it is not in this class,
we are going to go to the superclass
and going to find it.
We are sending the message area,
we are going to find this and this
is the method that we are going
to execute on the receiver.
This was the original idea of having
a message send based system.
But the problem is that when it
started having the idea of static
types and static type checking,
we have polluted this beautiful model.
And now we have problems that how
it works with the static type,
what is dynamic type and how overloading
works.
Basically, we have to start defining
what is the type of a variable.
Yes, we have this simple program.
We can see that a variable is a
box with a label.
It's a box that we can have a name
and references to object,
but also it has a type.
The type of the variable indicates
what kind of object we can reference
from it.
So we can see it like a box where
we can only put the type of objects
that are of this type of the variable.
We have to have an accord between
the type of the variable and the
type of the object that we are putting
on.
Of course, when we say the type,
we say the type and its subtypes
or in this case, for example,
if the variable is the type A,
we can put all the objects that
are the class A and its subclasses.
What is a type checker?
Well, some language, some
object-oriented languages like Java,
C-Sharp have a type checker.
Basically, a type checker is a tool
that in compilation time,
before executing the program,
just when we are compiling the program,
we'll check to see if all the uses
of a variable are congruent with
the objects that we are putting on.
We are trying to see if all the
reference that we store in a variable
has the correct type.
With this type information,
the idea is that we are avoiding
to send unknown messages to a given
object.
So to do this, the type checker
bases it on the static typechanges,
but we also have what is called
dynamic types, that is the type
of a variable during the execution
of a program.
In this case, we have the variable
a that is defined to have a type
of class A.
The static type of this variable
is class A, you can see here,
and is assigned with this declared.
The static type of a variable never
changes because we say it explicitly
when we declare the variable and
it will never change.
The dynamic type on the other side
is the type of the objects that
are pointed by this variable a.
In a given point of time,
we can have that this variable a
points to an object, an instance
of the class B.
In this case, for making it work
and this to compile, B should be
a subclass of A.
So in this point of the program,
just in this point of the program,
until we change the value of a,
A has a dynamic type B,
because it's the type of the object
that we are pointing.
Yes, we have our variable a and
this is pointing to an object of class B.
If we change the value of a in another
part of the program, we modify more
in the future of the execution and
now make it point to an object of type A.
We instantiate a new object,
type A and point a reference to it.
Now the type, the dynamic type of
the variable a is the class A.
In this case, we see that we can
have the same static type and the
same dynamic type or not,
but usually they should be equivalent.
So it should be a subclass.
In this case, the value B should
be a subclass of A.
We have our class A and here we
are going to have our class B.
In this case, it's important to
see that they are different.
And in most of our programs,
this is going to be what is happening.
This idea of static types also affects
the methods.
In the languages with static type
checking, the signature of a method,
let's call it, if you want the full
name, the real full name of the
method includes the type of its
argument.
In this case, this is not the method
foo.
We can say, oh, well,
yes, this is our method foo.
No, in practice, this is the method
foo that receives an object of type
A as a parameter.
So remember that the signature includes
not only the name but also the types
of the arguments of the message.
This is important for the lookup
and we are going to see it much
more in depth with an example.
Remember that we can apply,
we can send the message foo that
receives an A, an object of class
A with objects of instances of the
class B also.
Because as I always say in these
examples, B is a subclass of A.
It's a subtype of A.
So in this case, we are sending
the message and the message is sent
correctly, but the static type of
the variable a is always the class
A and the dynamic type is B.
As before, we have a mismatch between
them.
This is important for the method lookup.
We will see in the examples.
Let's see that we have this little
piece of code where we have two
classes again; class A and B.
And we have two methods,
two methods that are called m in
the two cases, but one is receiving
as an argument an object of class
A and the other is receiving an
object of class B.
And then, we have this little snippet
of code that will create two variables;
a and b.
We'll declare two variables,
one of type B and one of type A,
and we'll assign both the same object.
So we are going to have,
if we have our diagram,
have the variable b and the variable a,
we are going to have in this case,
a single object B that is pointed.
Yes.
Now the tricky question that you
can take some time to try to answer
to it, what are the results of all
these invocations?
What is printing on our logic?
We are going to see it now in a second.
Pause the video and try to find
which is the solution for all of them,
paying attention to the lookup.
Well, these are the results of executing
each of the invocations that we
were saying.
We will see case by case to see
why the result is what we have.
Why is executing this method in
each call?
Because remember always that static
times determine which is the message
that we are sending, yes,
which is the signature of the message
that we are sending and dynamic
types determine where we look for
the method that responds to that
message.
When we have a static type in,
we have two different times and
it's clear that we need to understand
them correctly.
We have a compilation stage and
an execution stage.
At compilation, when we are sending
a message, we have to determine,
we have to, the objective of the
compilation is to know which is
the message we are going to send.
So the first thing that we need
to do is to take the static type
of the receiver, this is important,
the static type of the receiver
to see in which class we start checking.
Second, that we have found this
static type, we can now ask ourselves
if this class of the static type
defines the method that we are looking
for with the name and if it had
this method by name, we have to
see which is the best fit with the
parameters that we have.
With all this information,
we are going to create the signature
that we are going to use for the
message, the signature,
or we can say that we have our message.
Then when we are executing the program,
we are going to use this message
the messages that we identified and we
are doing to do the lookup starting
from the receiver, but basically
starting from the dynamic type of
the receiver.
Let's see the examples to show more
clear what is happening.
Again, we have the same extract of code.
Remember, we are going to do it easily.
We have, this is a static and in
the dynamic view, we have the variables
a and b and both are pointing to
the same object that has dynamic type B.
So we have to see what happened
here during the compilation and
during the execution.
We have the first steps are done
during the compilation and then
we have the execution.
We can divide again.
This part is the compilation and
this part is the execution.
So the first thing that the compiler
will do when tries to compile this
expression is say, "okay,
which is the static type of the
variable a ?" In this case is the
class A.
So we are going to look,
everything that we are going to
look at is from the class A and
it's super classes, never the
subclasses.
Then we are sending the message named m.
So we are looking for the message
m in the class A.
Oh, we found one.
Also, we see that the static type
of the argument here is A also.
See the class A.
So we have here a matching with the type.
So we have identified that the message
to send is that.
And now, so we are looking for the
complete name of the method that
we are looking for is m with an
argument of type class A.
This is the signature that we have.
So when we are in execution mode
and we want to execute this code,
what we do is say, okay,
what dynamic type has the variable a,
in this case is class B.
So they look up, we start from the
class B, but we look for always
the method that S is called m for
a class A.
So we start looking our class B
and we see, ah, look,
there is a method called m,
but it's not the correct one because
the name is not the full name,
the signature is not correct.
So this one we don't want it.
We continue looking in this case
in the superclass and we find the
correct method and we execute it.
And in the console, we have the
correct value.
Let's see this other example.
We have a B in a that has a,
in this case, we are going to test
this expression.
We have B and we are sending the
message m passing as argument,
the little a.
So in compilation again,
we are going to try to decide which
is the signature of the method that
we are looking for.
So in this case, we are starting
with the static type of B that in
this case is the class B that is easy.
So we are going to see the code
in the class B and in its superclasses
in this case in B and in A.
And we are going to look for the
method that is called with the name m.
In this case, we are going to find
two methods that are called m,
one in the class B and one in its
superclass.
However, we are looking specifically
for the method.
Remember the signature and the full
name m with the type A for its
parameters.
So the correct name that we are
looking for is m(A a).
We check the compiler in compilation
times in the static checker,
the type checker will check that
there is a method.
Ah yes, I'll say, ah yes,
in the superclass there is the method
that we are looking for.
So we can compile the method and
eventually, we are going to execute.
When we execute our code again,
we have in this case,
the dynamic type of the variable
b is the class B.
So we start the lookup from this
class and we are looking for the
method with the full name,
with the full signature m that receives
a class A as parameter.
So in this case, we are going to
do a class B.
Is there a method with this signature?
No, this is not.
So we continue looking up in the
superclass and we have found the
one that we want to execute and
we execute and in the console we
have the correct message.
Let's see this example fast,
but it's interesting.
We just do the same.
We have the compilation and the
execution time and in the compilation
time, the compiler tries to apply
the type checker and see,
oh yes, these programs looks nice,
it's sound.
So we start by taking the static
type of the variable b.
The static type of the variable
b is the class B.
Yes.
So we are going to check again in
the B and it's in superclass.
We have found a method that is called m.
So we need to know the type of the
arguments of this method m.
In this case, we are going to check
the static type of the variable
b and we are going to see that this
of the class B.
So now the signature that we are
looking for is basically m,
but this name with a B,
a capital B, with the class B.
This program is good because all
the objects that are of class B
understand the message m with a
B as parameter.
So this is cool.
We can compile the program.
And now in execution time,
we are going to do the lookup.
The lookup starts in the class B
because the dynamic type of the
variable b is the class B.
So it's cool.
And we are looking for this signature
there.
So we are going to find it here
and we are going to execute it and
print the correct exit.
Let's see this example.
In this example is exactly the same
procedure.
We have the compilation and execution.
The compilation will get the type
of the variable a, in this case,
the static type is A,
the class A.
So we only look for in the class A.
We don't care what happens in B.
We have found that there is a method m,
that's okay.
We have found it.
And here, we want to establish which
is the static type of the variable b.
The static type of the variable
b is the class B.
Yes.
But remember that we have a subtype
between B and A.
So all the objects of instances
of B are also of the type I A.
So it's the same that we would say
that this variable b has the type
class B and the class A.
And as we are looking for methods
with one or the other,
we found the one with a signature
with the class A as parameter.
So this is the signature that we
want to have.
As the compiler has found a solution,
has found a method, a valid message
to send, this compiles code and
we can execute it.
And when we execute, again,
remember that we have the two variables
pointing always to the same object B.
We have the dynamic type of the
variable a is B.
So the lookup starts in the class B,
but we are looking for the method
m with the type A.
So the only one that we can find
because here is not the good one.
We found the one in the class A
and we execute that one.
And that one is what is print.
A final example that in this case
will show a different situation
is that imagine again,
we have class A and B and we have
a class C that is not related to
any of them.
We have A, B, this is class B and
we have class C here,
completely out of the relationship,
of the subtype relationship.
So when we want to compile this
expression, we take the static type
of the variable a and in this case is A.
So we start looking in the class A.
We have found the method m,
but we need to validate that the
parameter is the correct one,
like we have done before.
But now we check the variable c,
the static type and this case is
the class C.
And if we see there is no relationship
between the class C and the class A,
so we cannot use an object instance
of C as an A.
So there is no way that this works
and this method is not valid.
So the compiler say this cannot
be compiled because there is no
valid message to be sent.
The examples that we have seen are
really, really simple.
You have to be very careful because
the static types get really tricky
when it introduces new rules to
the method lookup and can end in
a strange execution and unwanted
results.
For more details, you have the lecture
on overloading and interfaces that
you can check or you can recheck
this video and check the examples
slowly and following the steps one
by one.
The rules that we have seen in these
examples are the ones that are applied,
but in more complex examples,
they are getting more complex itself,
but are the same roots.