Hello, welcome to this lecture.
In this lecture we are going to talk
about subclassing and subtyping.
The goals for this lecture is to discuss
the relationship between having an API
and what happens when we have a subclass.
Also, what happens with this API
and the clients of a given class.
We need to compare subtyping
and subclassing and we are
going to  , this content,
, concepts,  , impact the design.
Subtyping is good, even in
dynamically typed language.
Let's start with a simple example.
Let's see this, um, snippet of code.
We can see that we are defining a class
poem as an extension of a 'LinkedList'.
What do you think about it?
Of course, this code, we can write it.
It's a valid code.
What, but the question
is, does it make sense?
It's a good idea.
Yeah.
If we think about the API of our
poem class, the instances of poem
should understood at word, where we
pass a word, and then we can ask if
it's a, it is a haiku or if it's in
Alexandrine mode, but also in this
case, as we are extended 'LinkedList',
we have a lot of methods that you
shouldn't, we should not understand.
For example, 'addBeforeLink' or all the
methods that are defined in 'LinkedList'.
Let's see another example.
This looks a little more to have a
little more sense than the previous one.
We are defining our class 'Stack'
also as a subclass of 'LinkedList'.
Of course, this code is valid,
but again, does it make sense?
A, an API that we are expecting to
have in a 'Stack' includes operations
like pop, push, size, or top, but all
the other methods in a 'LinkedList'
They apply to the, our 'Stack'.
They are valid in the
context of our object.
As you can see,  , in the two previous
examples, we have to think about the API
when we are using subclassing because
the subclassing mechanism is intended to
reuse code, to reuse the superclass code.
And it's not thinking about the API
that we are exposing to our clients.
One interesting.
Thing is that the previous examples
were in our little reduced shower
like syntax because in both cases,
in dynamic type languages and in
statically type languages, subtyping
and some classing,  , really useful.
They are really useful.
We need to use them in the
good points that we care.
And the subtyping and the sub classing
has nothing to do with the type checker.
The type checker, as we have seen in
other lectures, is there for checking
that we are having the variables pointing
to possible good types of objects.
So basically, as we said, it's just
checking that we put squares into
squares and circles into circles.
Let's continue with a simple example.
Again, we are thinking about
implementing a 'Stack'.
And again, we are thinking them
from the point of view of the API.
That the client want to use in a 'Stack'.
We want to push elements, which
want to access the top element and
maybe pop in one of the elements and
get in the one that is on the top.
Also, we want to ask if it
is empty or not this 'Stack'.
We can see that these operations
have sense for our 'Stack'.
We have a API that have sense and that
is useful for the, for the client.
Let's see one alternative to
implement,  , the 'Stack' is to have
a subclass of OrderedCollection.
We are going to have our OrderedCollection
that is already existing in the
system and we are going to extend
it to implement our 'Stack'.
Easily, we can implement the pop
as removeFirst, as this method
also returns the first element.
We can implement the push as addFirst.
We are,  , in the ordered collection,
, always pushing and popping in
our 'Stack' in the first element.
And we can access the top just
by getting the first element.
By this, we are going
to have some advantages.
Implementing the 'Stack' like this will
give us all the reuse of the code that is
interesting in,  ,  , Ordered collection,
like an implementation of size includes.
Do collect and so on that are
interesting for our 'Stack'.
So we, we see that we are using the sub
classing as a way of getting code reuse.
We are winning the implementation,
reusing the implementations
that are useful for us.
But there is a problem.
What do we do with the rest of the API
existing in order collection, for example?
Now our 'Stack' understands
all the methods.
All the messages that are
in our direct collection.
So we can add an element before a given
one, we can remove different elements or
access the 'Stack' in different positions.
Not only in the first one, basically,
but we are saying when we are making
that, we have our order collection
and a subclass for the 'Stack'.
We are saying that all.
Our instances of a 'Stack' are
instances of ordered collection, and
that is not what we want because a
'Stack' is not an ordered collection.
Yes, in this case, we cannot, or
we don't want to have a 'Stack'.
A 'Stack' as a replacement of an
ordered collection, because an 'Stack'
has another API, it has another use
and is intended for another scenario.
Again, we can see, for example, the
examples of methods that are defined
in an ordered collection, but that
don't make sense in the 'Stack'.
For example, we can add an element
in the, in a given position.
Breaking the logic of the 'Stack'.
Where in the 'Stack' we always access
through the top of the 'Stack'.
So we are breaking the 'Stack'.
This breaks completely.
The 'Stack' is broken and the same happen
if we can add elements at the end, or
we can remove elements from the,  , the
top are using remove first directly or
removing any of the elements inside.
All these methods, what they
do is that they break our
implementation of a 'Stack'.
One easy solution that we can
think as good is, okay, we are
going to cancel all the operations
that we don't want to expose.
In this case, for example, we are
taking remote feed first and raising
an error when this is,  , this
message is sent to the 'Stack',
but this can get really complicated
because we were using remove first.
In our pop implementation, you remember is
here, so we need to avoid implementation.
We can do it using super, but this
is really, really, really ugly.
And we should not do it because basically,
, make the solution much complex and it
makes it more difficult to evolve in time.
So taking this into consideration.
We can see that there is
no a simple relationship.
There is no clear relationship between
a 'Stack' and ordered collection.
We are analyzing this
relationship from the API.
We are thinking them from
the point of the client.
The interface that we expose in
the 'Stack' is not an extension or
a subset of the other collection.
There is no.
way that we can find
this kind of extension.
It's not that we are adding new operations
to order a collection, but keeping the
previous one or just using some part of
them, let's see another example, let's
imagine we have a counting 'Stack'.
, this 'Stack' will count every time
that we do pop or push to have a, an
accountant of the operations that we
are doing, but eventually we'll do pop.
Exactly the same that an 'Stack', in
this case, we will have our 'Stack'
and our counting 'Stack', a subclass.
The counting 'Stack' could be a subclass
of a 'Stack', basically is doing
the same plus a little differential.
Let's compare with the previous case.
We have here in a user of our goal that
is, has its program, it's com, it's
.
Basically using an ordered collection
and it's using an ordered collection
and this program works perfect.
And in the other side, we have
another piece of client code that is
using the 'Stack' and it's using the
operations defined in a 'Stack' and
this program also works correctly.
By having a subclasses, we can
see now that what happened when
we replace Our ordered collection
by any of its subclasses.
If we take in this scenario, if we
take now and we are using an 'Stack',
we will see that this 'Stack',
we are using it sending the same
messages that we are using to order
a collection that works, but it's
breaking the nature of the 'Stack'
is breaking the usage of the 'Stack'.
In this case, we see that an 'Stack'
is not an ordered collection.
In the other example, now we change
the user of 'Stack' in this second
user for the user of counting 'Stack'
and we keep exactly the same program.
In this case, the program will work
and will do what the client code
wants with the addition that our
counting 'Stack' in behind the scenes
will count the number of operations.
And this example works because accounting
'Stack' Is a, a 'Stack' has a valid
API and they are a clear replacement.
So how we implement the 'Stack' after
this analysis in abstract, well, we can
implement the 'Stack' just extending from
object, not breaking the,  , breaking,
sorry, the, um, relationship with
or the recollection and we can do
is implemented it with composition.
We can do that.
Our 'Stack' is implemented.
Using a collection inside, could be
an ordered collection inside, and
we can directly use it in this way.
So it's better always to use
composition before using, um,
subclassing when it's not needed.
Remember, subclassing or inheritance
is intended for code reuse.
We are reusing the code that
is defined in the superclass.
And we will add a different
specification in some of the parts.
The, the idea is that, um, we can override
part of the code, but we are not going
to replace all the implementations.
And also remember that is the more
novel is that a subclass can be used
as a replacement of the superclass.
But this is not always true.
It depends.
What it changed in the subclass the
consequences of using a subclass when we
don't Need to is that basically we start
making our code more complex and making
it more difficult to understand we make
more difficult then later to how to evolve
this and Forces us to use a strange hacks
and a strange code like the for example
the one that we had To use super to skip
the implementation in the current class.
The idea of subtyping is that we
are going to inherit the interface.
We are going to have the same
messages that we are going to
understand in all the types.
We are going to work, make
two objects work in a similar
way, interact with each other.
A good way of thinking it is
with numbers and fractions.
They are completely different,
, objects, but they have the same API,
so we can make them work together.
The same happen when we
have collections and arrays.
Arrays are,  , examples of collection
and they should work in the
context where we use collections.
The same happen with fractions.
We have to use them in the
context where we use numbers.
So what we are doing always is that a
subclass from the subtyping point of
view have to always redify and refine how
a better,  , be more specific that the
one define it in the superclass one code
smell that show us that we are using bad.
The sub classing and subtyping
is that that example that we
seen before of canceling methods.
This is a sign of a bad design and
eventually we are going to pay the
cost of taking a bad decision now.
Let's analyze this new example.
We have a restricted 'Stack'.
This 'Stack' allows us only
push new elements that are
smaller than the top element.
We can implement it,
the push, in this way.
What is the good superclass for this?
Maybe it's a 'Stack'.
It looks like a 'Stack'.
We, what we want is an 'Stack', but the
problem with that, we need to be sure
if the, if the client, if the clients
that are using them will be affected
or not by this new,  , restricted
'Stack', maybe this kind of behavior
should be better handled in the client.
And not hidden in the restricted
style, but maybe it's not
a mandatory or possible.
This depends on the
problem we are solving.
And also a subclass that does not have to
make sure that the client program works.
We can talk a little about the
Liskov substitution principle.
Basically, what it says that if
we have two objects, two different
types, S and T, We have a program
that works with the object of type T.
This program should be unchanging
or should work exactly the same when
we change one object to the other.
If they are the S is a subtype of T.
In this case, what we are talking about is
the objects should have the same behavior.
They should have to be what
is called behavioral typing.
Most of the time, we are not going
to guarantee this, because when we
subclass, we are going to change
the behavior because if not, we are
going to use the original object.
A subclass often,  , change slightly
the behavior that, um, that we
implement in the superclass.
This,  , Liskov substitution principle
looks a little useless in this context.
But what is important That we
maintain the idea of the API.
When we are having the inheritance on
polymorphic, we have to be sure that when,
, we have two objects that we want to use
them polymorphic in a polymorphic way.
We need to be sure that we are con
, conforming and we have interfaces that
we can substitute one to the other.
In this way, the idea is that we can.
Use one of the implementations or
the other without caring,  , if
it's one or the other.
That, basically, is the
idea behind polymorphism.
And the only way that that happened is
that both objects had the same interface.
When we are subtyping,  , using
inheritance for it's having
subtyping, we create families of
classes with the similar interfaces.
At id, and usually we create an
abstract subclass, that we are
going to define abstract, and then
we will have concrete classes.
What we do with this is that we want to
define in the abstract subclass, the API
that we want to use from the clients.
When we are,  , using this kind
of,  , abstract classes and
the concrete subclasses, we
are,  , helping to reuse the code.
We push the common code
in the abstract subclass.
And also we are ensuring that.
We are creating polymorphic objects.
One point really important is this
last point, is that well, we can
create polymorphic objects by having,
, subclasses, by using,  , inheritance
to create subclasses of alu glass, but
also remember always that we can have,
we can implement the same interface in.
Classes that are completely independent
or they are in different hierarchies.
And this also is,  , useful
and we are going to use it a
lot when we use polymorphism.
Basically when we have extend or
inheritance or create a subclass,
we are mixing two concepts
because we are creating in a
way, a subtype and a subclass.
We have to be sure what
we are doing with it.
Remembering that sub classing
is about program reuse.
We want to reuse the goal that is
in the super class and subtyping
is about creating family of
classes that share the common API.
We can have a subtyping without
having sub classing, but always that
we subclass, we are subtyping, so
we have to pay attention to that.
Not always that we want
to use,  , to reuse coal.
We are going to use subclassing.
So like that, when we only want
subtyping, when we only want the,
the, the common API, it's better
to avoid the,  , subclassing.
We need to use subclassing when is
for,  , reusing the program code.