Hi, in this lecture, we are going
to discuss defensive programming,
in particular in the case for
dynamically typed object-oriented
language.
We are going to discuss spurious checks,
in particularly for the case when
we are going to validate data in
our methods.
We are going to discuss the impact
of those type checks and checks
in dynamically typed languages and
we are going to discuss the impact
of testing to avoid those checks.
Before going into checks,
let's discuss a bit about this method,
the assertion method that we are
going to use through the slides.
So this method is an assertion method
where objects are going to assert
that a certain condition is true
or false and if false,
we are going to throw an exception.
So this method, `assert:description`,
we are going to use it like this,
so self, assert:[Condition] description,
and then what happens if it fails.
So we check the condition and if
it fails the condition,
we are going to throw an error with
this message.
So it's important to understand
that this method will change the
control flow.
So if the assertion fails,
the rest of the method in the caller
will not be able to execute.
Let's see this with an example.
So here, for example,
we see in the context of a graphics
framework a method that sets the
`padding` inside an object.
So this is just a normal setter.
So here we take an argument and
then a parameter and we are setting
it into a local variable,
an instance variable,
and before actually setting it as
in a normal setter we are going
to assert here that the `padding`
that the argument we are receiving
is not nil.
So in that case, if the `padding` is nil,
we are going to throw an exception
checking that the `padding` must
not be nil.
The question that we can ask ourselves
is, is this assertion here worth it?
So let's analyze it a bit.
First, we need to think about the
runtime cost of such assertions.
Of course, in many different languages
assertions can be optional.
We can turn them on and off and,
for example, avoid them to be compiled
at all at the end.
So for example, we could think that
they are never executed in production.
So in that case, they don't have
any runtime cost.
So that could be, for example,
a potential benefit.
And they could also help us track
problems and stabilize the code
when developing.
So we don't want to have nil as
a `padding` in any object.
So let's validate it right away.
Now let's think about the same code,
but written a bit differently.
Instead of having an assertion error,
we are going to just check it directly.
We are going to check if the `padding`
is nil, then we are going to throw
an error.
So what is the difference between
the previous example and this one?
Of course, the goal is the same.
We don't want that the `padding` is nil.
We don't want our code to be broken
because the `padding` is nil,
actually.
Because if we avoid `padding` to be nil,
that means that our code in the
rest of our program knows that the
`padding` can never be nil and it
can be simpler code.
I refer you to the null object sections
and avoid nil check in the other
lectures.
Now, of course here, we are checking
that the `padding` cannot be nil.
But it doesn't avoid that we set
any junk object as a `padding`.
So we could for example say `padding`
colon and we could put string here.
So if we put string as a `padding`,
our code actually will be broken too.
So why not checking that this is
not a string or this is not some
other object.
So this means actually that this
test here, this check is not enough
to solve all our problems and maybe
it's not worth.
Here is a proposal for a better
setter method.
This is just taking the parameter
here and setting it into this as
better without doing any checks.
Of course, a `padding` is still
expected to not be nil,
but it is also expected to not be
string and other invalid `padding`.
So what are the advantages of this?
Take a couple of minutes and think
about that.
We're going to discuss it in a couple
of slides.
Before going into that,
let's see another example.
So here, we have for example this
source method in an event and it
is also implemented using assertions.
So we are going to assert if we
have no source, then we cannot access
the source.
So this is defensively checking
that you cannot get the source out
of an object if it doesn't have a source.
Again, these assertions are conceptually
optional, so this code could not
be there and the code should be
still okay.
But it still looks like a leftover
from debugging because this will
just throw in development an assertion
error.
If we wanted, for example,
to catch that exception because
it's a valid exception in the domain,
then maybe it could be better to
make it an explicit exception.
We could, of course, turn that code
into this just by removing the
assertions and then this code now
it's an explicit check that is,
of course, mandatory in all our code.
So then, every time that we are
going to access the source of an event,
we are going to check always if
it has the source and in which case
in case it doesn't, we're going
to throw an error.
We can later replace for example
this error with a domain exception
for our particular case.
What this actually changes from
the previous example is that we
can catch in the caller or even
in any of the callers in the call chain,
we can catch the error if we need it.
Of course, the reader knows that
there is a check for real.
This is actually a domain decision
to avoid people getting the source
if it is not there.
Of course, it would be better and
simpler to always have a source.
But if the domain actually supports
that having a source is actually
an optional part of the domain,
we should think about that.
Of course, if having a source is
optional, we can think of replacing
this with a null object.
Another variant of the checks that
we saw before is to check explicitly
for types.
In this case, we are checking that
our `padding` isKindOf BlPadding.
This is equivalent to doing an instance
of check in Java.
What are the benefits and the
disadvantages of this solution?
First, we have to understand that
making an instance of check around
isKindOf check is slow because it
has to traverse the entire hierarchy
to understand if the object is actually
of the requested class.
One of the other disadvantages of
this solution is that it prevents
to extend the program with polymorphic
objects.
Imagine that tomorrow I would like
to have a `padding`, a different
`padding`, but without sharing the
hierarchy of the BlPadding.
I could implement a BlPadding object
or another similar object to BlPpadding
that has exactly the same interface,
understand the same messages,
but it doesn't inherit from the
Blpadding class.
In such a case, I would not be able
to use my `padding` in this code
here because this code is actually
checking that the object needs to
be in the hierarchy of Blpadding
and it's not checking that it needs
to implement the same interface.
So this check is preventing me to
implement polymorphic objects.
As a conclusion, avoid using optional
check that can be used mainly for
debugging purposes or remove them
after debugging.
Also avoid using explicit type-checks
because they prevent code evolution
and favour tests because actually
what we have seen as assertions
in the code and checks in the preamble
of the methods could have been different
tests in our source code.