Hello!
In this lecture, we will look at
the two interfaces of a class.
So the outline of this lecture will
be the following: we will do a short
reminder of the essence of
object-oriented programming that
we already saw at the beginning
of this MOOC.
Then we will look at one question
that you can find in books.
And we will see that classes have
two kinds of clients.
So let's go back to the roots.
So if you remember correctly,
inheritance is about the need for
doing some small adaptations to
existing classes.
So I have an existing class there
and I want to reuse some of its
behavior and without reimplementing it.
So the solution is to do class
inheritance.
So here in the subclass,
what I can do in the subclass is
to express a delta.
So it means that I will implement
a new state or a new behavior or
I can refine behavior,
etc.
So you already saw all of that.
And now the question is,
sometimes in books you can find
the idiom: "fields should be ‘private‘."
And the goal of this lecture is
to think a little bit about this idiom.
So here we have a Java example.
In this class, there is a ‘private‘
field, an instance variable x.
And then in the method ‘foo‘,
I can use x.
So this is pretty standard in Java.
So what are the consequences of
this example?
So here, clients of this class cannot
access the instance variable ‘x‘
because it is ‘private‘.
So this is a good point from the
encapsulation point of view.
But in subclasses, we cannot access
‘x‘ too because this is a ‘private‘
field.
So this is not very good because
if you remember correctly,
object-oriented programming focuses
on expressing deltas in subclasses.
So it means that we want to adapt
the code of superclasses in subclasses
by expressing a delta.
And having a ‘private‘ field means
that I cannot easily express this
delta because I cannot access the
fields of the superclass.
So this example shows that there
are two kinds of clients for a class.
First, its users.
So for example, a ‘Person‘ is a
client of an ‘Address‘.
And then the second kind of clients
are subclasses, its extenders.
And if you look at the extenders
when you are writing a class,
you cannot know if it will be extended
in the future and if another programmer
will need to extend it to express
a new delta.
So that's why ‘final‘ and ‘private‘
prevent expressing delta in subclasses.
So it means that this is much better
to use ‘protected‘ instead of ‘final‘
and ‘private‘.
That will limit the extensibility
of a class.
So the correct idiom,
in fact, should be: "Fields should
be ‘private‘ and the class should
provide ‘protected‘ accessors."
Or a simpler one: "Fields should
be ‘protected‘." And if you look at it,
this is the default mechanism in Pharo.
And now the benefits of it are that
if a field is ‘protected‘,
so here the instance variable ‘x‘
is ‘protected‘ in A.
So it means that it can be used
in the implementation on the ‘foo‘
method in A, but it can also be
used in the ‘foo‘ implementation,
the redefinition of ‘foo‘ in B by
its extender.
So this is good from the encapsulation
point of view because the client
cannot access it directly.
This is not possible because this
is a ‘protected‘ field.
But in the subclass, I can do it.
I can use x.
So this is good for both encapsulation
and extensibility.
As a conclusion of this short lecture,
OOP, object-oriented programming,
is about encapsulation and extension.
And this is always forgotten.
And that a class has two kinds of users,
its users and its extenders.