Hello.
In this lecture, we'll discuss something
really important, it is about
polymorphic objects, and they are
the support of software evolution.
The goals of this lecture are the
following.
We will speak that what is polymorphic
objects and why they are key to
software evolution, and then what
about them in statically typed
languages.
And then we will see that in these
kinds of languages, we will need
the concept of interface.
So let's start with an example.
So here, we have a hierarchy of classes,
`Shape`, which is the root of the
hierarchy, and then we have different
kinds of `Shapes`.
We have a circle, rectangle,
triangle, and all of them implement
the same message, `draw`.
So it means that we have a polymorphic
API there, `draw`, and we can manipulate
any kind of `Shape`.
Okay, and now we have a client,
`Canvas`, that implements the method
display, and inside this method,
we will manipulate a collection
of `Shapes` by sending each of them
the `draw` message.
And now, each `Shape` will answer
accordingly because of the lookup.
And now the question is,
how can we support `Rhombus` in
this kind of design?
Solution one, it's easy.
I can add a new class in my system,
a new subclass of the `Shape` class
that implements the `draw` message.
So I will redefine the `draw` method,
and now it will work perfectly.
But if I cannot subclass the `Shape`
class because, for example,
it could be a third-party class,
or it could be in another library,
or it could be a `final` class in
the Java programming language.
So it means I cannot introduce this
link.
So `Rhombus` cannot be a subclass
of `Shape`.
And I can still create this `Rhombus`
class.
I can still implement the `draw`
method in this class.
So it means that it should play
nicely with the `Canvas`.
And if we look at the code,
if I implement the `Rhombus` like that,
it will answer to the `draw` message
and it will play nicely.
I can introduce some `Rhombus` instances
in the `Shapes` collection and it
will work perfectly, even if the
`Rhombus` is not a subclass of `Shape`.
So what does it mean?
It means that producing polymorphic
objects is good for the substitutability
point of view, and it's key to software
evolutions.
So it means that if I have some
existing code, I can inject new
kind of objects in this existing code,
and it will work perfectly if they
answer to the polymorphic API.
And objects do not have to be from
the same hierarchy to work together.
They just need to implement the
same polymorphic API.
Okay, in dynamically typed languages,
this is usually named Duck typing.
It means that if an object works
like a duck and quacks like a duck,
then it's a duck.
It works perfectly like that.
And now what about statically typed
languages?
In those kinds of languages,
for example, if I declare a variable
s of type `Shape`, it means that
this variable can contain either
an instance of `Shape` or one of
its subclasses.
So it means I could also write s
equal new circle, and it works.
Okay, because circle is a subclass
of `Shape`.
And if I want to implement now a
`Rhombus` as a subclass of `Shape`,
it will work.
But if I cannot, because,
for example, `Shape` is the `final`
class or whatever, or I cannot do that.
So it means that when I will try
to do `Shape s` equal new `Rhombus`,
it will not work at all.
I cannot do that.
So what can I do?
And in fact, in statically typed
languages, they introduce the concept
of interface.
An interface has a name,
defines a type, has one or more
supertypes and contains a group
of methods.
And we might introduce some default
implementation for some method.
And why is this concept needed?
Because it allows developers to
define subtypes out of class
hierarchies.
And it can be used by the type checker
to check subtypes relationship without
the support of classes.
Let's see on an example.
Now I define a new interface,
`IShape`.
Inside this interface,
I declare the `draw` method.
So it means that now the `Shape`
class can implement this interface.
And what does it mean?
It means that I must implement the
`draw` method inside this class.
This is mandatory to fulfill the
requirement of the `IShape` interface.
And from the client point of view,
in the `Canvas` class,
it means that now when I want to
manipulate a collection of `Shapes`,
I will declare a collection array
list of `IShape` and not `Shape`,
the interface name.
So it means that any object instances
of any class in the system that
implements the `IShape` interface
can be added in this collection.
So given this design,
it means that now I can implement
a `Rhombus` class that extends the
object class and not the `Shape` one.
And implement the `IShape` interface.
I must implement the `draw` method
inside this class.
And it will work perfectly from
the client point of view,
because now I can introduce some
`Rhombus` instances inside the
collection in `Canvas` and it will
work perfectly with the `Canvas`.
So a class must implement the method
mentioned in the interface.
This is what we saw.
The `draw` method must be implemented
in the class that implements the
`IShape` interface.
A class may implement many interfaces.
So this is not like inheritance.
This is not a single superclass.
And an interface may be composed
of multiple interfaces.
So from the typing point of view,
it means that now when I declare
a collection, a type like that,
it means that here I am restricting
the possible solution,
the extensibility of the code.
Here I can only introduce in this
collection instances of the `Shape`
class or one of its subclasses.
Whereas in this solution,
I can introduce in this collection
any instance, any object in the
system that its class implements
this interface.
So this is a more open design without
restricting the evolution.
But don't be confused.
Interfaces are nominal types.
So it means that we give it a name.
It is declarative.
And this is really different from
the typing, duck typing that we
saw in the dynamically typed context.
So type compatibility in this context
is defined and based on the name,
the name of the type.
And two interfaces are only compatible
if they have the same name,
regardless of their contents.
So it means that if I define two
different interfaces with two different
names, but the same contents,
the `draw` method inside,
they are not compatible.