- Hello, everybody.
I'm Stéphane Ducasse,
and I will present with Luc Fabresse,
Guillermo Polito, and Pablo Tesone
this MOOC around advanced
object-oriented design.
So what will see in this MOOC is
that we will focus on really the
roots of object-oriented design.
From that perspective,
we will not present any modeling
strategies or methodologies or even
visual languages like UML.
In fact, we will focus on the key
mechanisms that will help you to
design robust and extensible
application.
From that perspective,
this MOOC is unique from the mixture
of the different facets that we
are bringing together.
What we should also consider is
that all in all, we have around
60 or more years of experience designing
complex systems.
So why this MOOC?
In fact, we did the Pharo MOOC,
which was really a good success.
And then, we realized that people
love it so much that we have to
focus on the Pharo MOOC part that
is on design.
I just want to show you this quote
where this guy said, "Oh,
I spent the last 15 years or so
in software development,
and following this MOOC,
I realized that I hadn't really
grasped the essence of object-oriented
design."  And for me,
the aspect of essence was really
important.
And I said, okay, so this means
that really, we should stress this
part and this MOOC, the current one,
is really a focus on all this mechanism
and the essence of object-oriented
programming.
From that perspective,
it is also language-agnostic.
What you will learn in this MOOC,
you can apply it in any object-oriented
language.
So what are the objectives?
Basically, we will revisit the basic
elements such as encapsulation,
delegation.
We will also make you think about
essential aspects of our object-oriented
design, such as message passing,
how do we express choices.
We will present some key Design
Patterns, not all of them,
because the point is not to do a
catalog, but to select the one that
we like and that we believe are
much more interesting.
We will also analyze real case studies
that we will take from Pharo,
and then we will also we will have
four lectures on some specific Pharo
code idioms.
So this MOOC is divided in 10 modules
that are somehow interrelated.
So you can consume a bit the MOOC
in the way you want, but this is
better to follow the numbering that
we propose.
We will start with the Message.
So really the roots, with some
Test-Driven development because
we are really big fans of Test-Driven
and we think that this is super
important.
We will see the Hook and template
approach, revisit what are Objects
with States and Behavior.
Then we will start to sketch and
present some Elementary Design Pattern,
introduce after Double Dispatch,
which is really important for more
advanced Design Patterns.
And then, you will see there will
be some aspects that are really
covered in lecture, like Sharing
of Objects or even this Inversion
of Control.
So from that perspective,
all this mixture will make this
MOOC really powerful sets of concept
that you can really learn.
Now the code example in this MOOC
are from Pharo.
Why?
Because we are the Pharo creators
and for us, Pharo, this is super
simple and beautiful,
so that's why we naturally choose it.
It would not have made sense that
we use another language,
so you will have to read a bit the
syntax.
For that, you take one of the lectures
of the previous MOOC and I think
that in a couple of hours,
you get started.
And in general, we will show the
Java equivalent, if this is important.
So why Pharo?
This is what I explained before.
From that perspective,
this is a pure object-oriented language.
So we don't have all the type system,
the type constraints of other languages.
We have only objects,
messages and lambda expressions.
So this means that you can map that
to JavaScript or to Python if you want,
just check the complement MOOC,
with two or three videos there,
you can get started and follow this
MOOC.
I just want to stress one aspect
here is that if you take the literature
on polymorphism, you will have all
kinds of definitions and we have
one that is if it works like a duck,
if it swims like a duck,
if it quacks like a duck,
it's probably a duck.
What does it mean?
It means that in all this MOOC,
when we say that we want polymorphic
or that we want to use polymorphism,
this is that you expose objects
that expose the same API.
This is objects that are substitutable,
so we can take an object and place
another one that is polymorphic
and the program should continue
to somehow work.
And the key aspect also is that
polymorphic objects does not imply
that there are subtypes.
So you can have two objects with
an API here, with an API and I am
a client and I expect this API.
That's okay.
I don't have to have a subtype
relationship between those.
We don't need that.
If we have it, then this is good.
If we don't have it, then this is
like that.
So remember this definition because
we use it a lot.
So what I wanted to say as a conclusion
is that this is really a unique MOOC.
It took us something like four years
to prepare it.
We applied it in all kinds of lectures
during this four years,
some slides went over six or seven
or 10 revisions.
We have accumulated something like
60 years of experience in
object-oriented design and practices.
We are building Pharo,
and Pharo is a complex system.
And not only Pharo, by the way.
We will really use the concrete
case and try to make them understandable
because when you want to have a
concrete case, often they can be
complex.
And finally, what you will learn
in this MOOC is really actionable
in any object-oriented languages.
So try to avoid to think,
"Oh yes, this is a MOOC on Pharo."
This is not a MOOC on Pharo.
This is a MOOC on advanced
object-oriented design.