- In this lecture, we'll discuss
the Essence of Dispatch,
and we will see that it is important
to let the receiver decide.
First of all, let's start with an
example that we already saw in the
previous lecture.
This is a `Boolean` example with
multiple classes.
Here, you have two subclasses,
True and False, subclasses of the
`Boolean` class.
When you send a `not` message to
an object, it will correctly respond
whether it is the true instance
or the false instance that receives it.
So, we never test exactly which
object receives the message `not`.
And based on the class of the receiver,
it will respond accordingly.
What's the point of this example?
In this lecture, we will focus on
why it is really useful.
We'll probably never reimplement
`Booleans` in the future,
because in most object-oriented
languages it is already there.
So, what are the lessons to learn
and what are the properties of this
solution?
Imagine that we have more than two
classes.
Instead of having just True and False,
we have a lot of classes.
Here, we have a huge hierarchy of
classes.
And now imagine that you need to
implement a new method.
Inside this method, you will have
to test to introduce some conditions
for each case for different classes.
How will we do that?
We will not test each case.
In fact, we will use a message send.
Sending a message selects the right
method to execute based on the class
of the receiver.
This is what we saw in the `Boolean`
example.
And it can be seen as a condition
without explicit ifs.
This is a dynamic choice,
so you don't need to explicitly
test in your code.
Let's take an example.
For example, here we have a collection
of multiple objects that are instances
of different classes.
So, a is an instance of the class `A`,
bb is an instance of the class `BB`,
etc.
Now we'll send the message `operation`
to each of these instances.
Basically, it will answer correctly
according to the class of the receiver.
So, we never tested whether it is
the method `operation` from `A`
or the method `operation` from `BB`.
It's automatically done by the message
send, by the lookup.
It will select the right method
in the right class given the receiver
class.
And this solution is even better
because we can introduce,
for example, a new class in the
hierarchy.
Here, we introduced the `AA` class,
and we have a new instance in the
collection.
And here, what happened is that
I didn't change the client code.
This is exactly the same code and
it worked perfectly.
This is an extensible solution.
So, sending a message is a choice
operator.
It means that each time you send
a message, the execution engine,
the virtual machine, selects the
right method depending on the class
of the receiver.
The next question is,
how do we express choices as a
programmer?
Let's take these two designs.
Could we have the same `Boolean`
solution with only a single class,
like here?
Would it be possible to implement
the `not` method and the `or` method
without if?
The answer is no, of course not.
If you want to have an implementation
without an explicit if in the code,
you need to have multiple classes.
It means that the classes play the
role of the case.
They express the choices in the code.
It means that a class represents a choice.
This is an important point.
Now that we understand this point,
we can compare something more general.
We can have a `Fat Class` here,
on this side, and here we have a
hierarchy of classes.
Now, we understand that the hierarchy
of classes is a better design because
this is a more modular design.
We isolate each point in a different
class of hierarchy.
We don't need to introduce complex
conditions in the code,
because we just send messages,
and the right method will be explicitly
chosen by the lookup algorithm.
And then we can even specialize
the behavior inside subclasses.
We don't need to recompile existing
methods, because when I add a new class,
I can introduce a new method inside
this class, and it does not change
the code of other classes.
And as the programmer,
we can only focus on one class at a time,
so one given concept at a time.
The message dispatch supports modularity.
For example, with the hierarchy
of classes, we can even package classes.
For example, class `D` here,
we can package it in a separate package.
This is better from the modularity
point of view because it means that
it is not mandatory to load this package.
We can load it dynamically as a plugin,
for example, or we can even not
load it at all.
And then, if we load this extra package,
this plugin, the client code does
not change.
This is what we saw in the example
before.
It means that instances of the `D`
class will correctly work with all
client codes without changing them.
So, message send is powerful,
and message sends are supporting choices.
The execution engine acts as a
conditional switch.
It means that you need to use it.
You don't need to test explicitly
in your code.
But for that, you need to introduce
a hierarchy of classes to have cases.
Then, this is a kind of extensible
switch statement by adding new classes
in your hierarchy.
The second message in this lecture
is to let the receiver decide.
Sending a message to an object means
that there is a lookup algorithm
that will select the right method
to execute.
So, the client does not decide.
You send the message and you let
the lookup algorithm decide which
method to execute.
And the client code is more declarative.
It means that you give orders to
objects*, and they will answer correctly.
And then, of course, we can have
different receivers that we can
substitute dynamically.
It means that if we load an extra
package, an extension,
or a plugin, and there are new objects,
they will answer correctly without
breaking the client code.
So, in summary of this lecture,
what is it important to remember?
Avoid conditionals as much as possible
in your code, use objects and messages
whenever you can, let the receiver
decide, do not ask but tell your
object what to do, let the system
select the right method to execute,
and the class hierarchy supports
dynamic dispatch.
So, use class hierarchy and introduce
more classes in your design.