- Hello, everybody.
Welcome to this lecture on Inheritance,
Lookup, with a specific focus on `self`.
So the idea of this lecture,
this is that we will look at what
is sending a message and the Lookup
once for all, so after,
you will know it forever.
So basically in this lecture,
we will look at what is Sending
a message, what is Method Lookup
and what is the semantics of `self`.
And by the way, this is also equivalent
of `this` in Java.
The semantic is exactly the same in both,
they are just different syntaxes.
But this is the same in Java,
C#, Pharo.
So if you remember, in the previous
lecture, we mentioned that inheritance
has two aspects.
One that is the inheritance of state,
which is basically static because
it is done at compile time.
So this is at the moment where you
define a class, the compiler knows
that the state of an instance will
be represented by the state of the
class and the state of its `super`
class.
And inheritance has also a dynamic
aspect, that is the inheritance
of the behavior.
So this means that when I send a
message, which method should I execute.
And this is on this part that we
will focus now.
So if you see, the key aspect,
this is what is sending a message.
Sending a message, this is also,
in Java, by the way, called,
I call methods or I invoke methods.
Personally, I prefer the term Sending
a message because it implies that
there is a lookup.
So if we look at it, sending a message,
this is a two-step process.
So first, we have the lookup of
the methods and second,
we execute the method that we found
on the receiver.
And you will see that this is really
important.
Normally, we have some little video
later in the MOOC that says,
`do you really understand lookup?`
And basically, this is based on
these two steps because often you
mix things, you get something that
is working more or less.
It works more or less up until we
can know exactly if you don't
understand.
So if I look at this example on
the right, when I send the message
`area` to `aColoredRectangle`,
I will first do the lookup.
So the lookup will look for the methods,
oh, is there a method's name `area`?
Yes, there is one.
I return the method, which is this
one and I apply this method on the
receiver.
So you see one step, two steps.
Now let's look at the method lookup.
So the method lookup,
this is the first step that we saw.
So what's happened is that the method
lookup starts in the class of the
receiver.
So when I send the message `area`,
the first thing that I do here,
one step, I go to the class level.
So when I go to the class level,
then I will check inside the class,
oh, is there the method that I'm
looking for?
Yes, no.
If this is not the case,
I will go up.
And when I find it, I just return it.
What is important to see is that
this step, the first step will make
that in a system like Pharo,
where class are objects,
the same method lookup works for
both instance and classes.
If you are fuzzy on that,
I strongly encourage you to have
a look at the video of the first
MOOC because that really explains
well the metaclass and the fact
that there is only one single method
lookup.
So if we look at it, so this is
basic things here.
If I send the message `color` to
my 'aColoredRectangle'.
I jump here, I see, oh,
this is `color`, I return it.
If I send the message `area` here,
I jump to the class.
This is not found here,
I return it.
Nothing special here.
This is super basic.
So, most of the time,
the result of a lookup is cached
and it only happens once for a given
call.
In some languages like C++,
you have dispatch tables.
What is really important,
which is the point that you should
take is that conceptually,
there is a method lookup at execution
and that virtual machines are smart
enough to not always look for the
method.
So now, let's look at what is `self`
or `this` for real.
So what I suggest is that take five
minutes, write the definition on
a little piece of paper,
put pause on the video.
Well, your definition should have
two points, what `self` represent
and how the method lookup happens
when a message is sent to self.
Why do I have these two points?
Because in the lecture on `super`,
you will see that there is a difference
and the difference is only in one
of the two points.
So this is important that for `self`
or `this`, you have two points,
like that, you will be able to compare.
So now, before my definition or
the correct definition,
I will propose you some little
exercises.
So first a convention that we use
in this MOOC.
So this means that when we write `aA`,
this is an instance of `A`.
So this means that if we are in Pharo,
we will write `aA` equals `A new`.
This is the result.
If you are in Java, you will write
`aA` equals `new A`.
So we have this setup where we have
`aA` is an instance of the class `A`,
`aB` is an instance of the class `B`.
Now, what is the result if I send
a message `foo` to `aA`?
So I send a message to `aA`.
Now I know, I look in the class.
There is `foo`.
Okay.
This returns 10, so I get 10.
Now I have my instance `aB`,
instance of the class `B`,
I send the message `foo`,
I look for `foo`.
Okay, I find it, okay I return 50.
Let's look at it.
Yes, we were right.
That's so cool.
So here I said, `self` always represents
the receiver, and this is what we
will see in the next exercise.
So let's take a more challenging
exercise.
So now, we will look for this
expression.
So we send the message `bar` to `aA`,
so the method `bar`, we look in
the class, we find `bar`.
It is defined here.
And then, we will apply `bar` to this,
if you remember the message passing,
I said we look for something.
We look for the method.
We find the method, we apply it
on the receiver.
And then, `self` in that case represents
the receiver.
This is what is written in the title.
So this means that I will send a
new message `foo` to the same object.
I will go up again, I found `foo`.
Okay, this is 10, we got 10.
So what you could say is that basically,
we could only find 10 because there
is only 10.
From the perspective of `A`,
there is only 10.
Now, what is interesting,
in this example, this expression,
`aB bar`.
So what I suggest is that just take
two minutes and just ask yourself,
okay, what is the result?
Is it 10 or 15?
And what you should know is that
you have a good chance to get it wrong.
This is what we really want to make
clear.
So I send the message `bar`,
I look for `bar` in the class of `B`,
there is no `bar`.
So we go up, we find `bar`,
oh, there is `bar`.
This is we find this method,
which is the same as before.
So now we do the same.
We apply the method on `B` and `self`
here.
This is what?
This is the receiver.
So here, this is `aB`,
and then the message `foo` is sent
to `B` to the instance.
So we look for `B`, we find `B`
here and we return it here.
And here, we get 50.
So what you see is that even if
the method was defined in the `super`
class, the method of the subclass
was called in place of the method
of the `super` class.
So if I erase a bit to make the
things clearer, it means that the
method `foo` that is executed here
depends on the receiver.
So if I get an instance of `B`,
this is this method that is executed.
If I get an instance of `A`,
it's this method that is executed,
even if the method was defined in
the `super` class.
And that this is really the key
aspect of object orientation.
You see the method lookup and the
late binding that is happening here.
What I show you here,
this is the same in Java if you
only use public method in Java.
If you use private methods,
then you get a different result
because the private keyword has
a different semantic than public
methods.
So here on this slide,
you have really the explanation,
you can go over it.
Let's go fast.
So this means that `aB` is instance
of the class `B`, there is no method
`bar` in `B`, so we look up `bar` in `A`,
we found the method `bar` in `A`.
The method `bar` is executed and
I would add on `aB`, `self` refers
to `aB`.
So this means that we will resend
`foo` to `self`, so to the `B`.
So we look up for `B` in the class
`bar`, in the class `B`,
and then we return this method that
is executed.
My definition, and a good definition,
the correct definition of `this`
or `super` says that `self` represents
the receiver of the message.
And then the second sentence,
this is: "The method lookup starts
in the class of the receiver."
What is important is that in this
definition sometimes people say
this is the current instance.
The problem is that for me,
current instance, I don't know current
of what.
And I always think, oh,
if I have concurrent processes,
is it different or not?
So here, this is very clear.
This is based on the message.
This is for a message,
`self` represents the receiver.
Just a little variation.
This is not because we introduce
an empty class in the middle that
will change anything.
So this means that here,
as you should guess, right,
I will get 10, 10 and 50.
Why?
Because the lookup goes like that.
So if I send the message `bar`,
if I send the message `bar` to `aC`,
I will go up, find the method `bar`,
apply it to `C`, redo a lookup for
`foo`.
And this is exactly the same mechanism
that I explained before.
So you don't have to have the method
one by one in the class and the
`super` class.
So you see.
So what you should know from this
lecture: so `self` always represents
the receiver.
Sending a message is a two-step process.
We look for the method and we execute
the method on the receiver.
The lookup method in fact maps a
message to a method and it starts
in the class of the receiver.
What you will see is that this is
a bit different when you use the
`super` keyword and this is what
is explained in the `super` lecture.