- Hello, in this lecture,
we'll discuss the basics of inheritance
and we'll come back to some things
that you already saw in previous
lectures.
First of all, the goal of this lecture
is to discuss what exactly inheritance
is, and when to use it.
And by the way, notice that in Pharo,
we have exactly the same inheritance
model as in Java.
Inheritance basically is a reuse
mechanism.
It comes from the fact that we don't
want to reimplement all the codes
that already exist, and usually,
a code exists in classes.
It means that we want to customize
it and extend it, but we don't want
to reimplement it.
Sometimes, we want to specialize
it and express a delta in subclasses.
So, what we want is to adapt existing
code by extending the behavior and
the state in existing classes,
and we don't want to reimplement
everything.
The solution for that is class
inheritance.
We need to extend the existing definition
of classes in subclasses.
So, let's take an example.
What can we do when we create a new class?
Here, I create a new class,
`ColoredRectangle`.
This is a subclass of `Rectangle`.
What can I do in a subclass?
I can add a state, I can add a behavior,
I can use superclass behavior and state,
and I can redefine superclass behavior
to specialize it.
So, let's start with the hierarchy.
If I look at the hierarchy of classes,
the root of the hierarchy is usually
the `Object` class.
All classes eventually inherit from
`Object`, and the `Object` class
defines the common behavior of all
objects.
It raises errors when we send a
message that is not understood,
it provides some accessors to access
the class of an object,
etc.
In Pharo, there is a subtle difference
from other languages.
We have the `ProtoObject` class,
which is a superclass of `Object`,
and it has a special purpose.
This is not really important for
the comprehension of all the object
models, this is just a little difference
in the Pharo language.
It raises as much error as possible,
and it allows for building advanced
techniques and advanced tools,
such as proxy objects and things
like that.
In the rest of the lecture,
we'll just use the `Object` class.
So, if we look at inheritance,
there are two aspects of inheritance.
The first one is the static aspect
for instance variables.
During the class creation,
I can compute all the instance variables
of a class.
And then, there is the dynamic aspect
for behavior.
During the execution,
I can send messages to objects,
and here I will dynamically select
the method to execute.
Let's have a closer look at these
two aspects.
First, when I define the
`ColoredRectangle` subclass here,
I can see that this `ColoredRectangle`
class has four instance variables.
Two of them are defined directly
in the `ColoredRectangle` class,
and two of them are defined in the
superclass.
In fact, the instance variables
are computed by the union of all
instance variables in the hierarchy
chain.
Usually, there is no duplicate in
the chain.
Otherwise, I will have shadowing
in the name of the instance variable.
For behavior, when I send a message…
Here, I have an object,
`aColoredRectangle`.
It is an instance of the
`ColoredRectangle` class.
If I send a message to this object,
for example, I send the area message.
It means that the system will first
look at the class of the receiver
- you already saw that - in the
`ColoredRectangle` class.
It will check if the area
message exists.
And if it does not, it will continue
in the superclass.
And then, it will find it here in
the `Rectangle` class.
This is why we said that the inheritance
of behavior is dynamic.
What you should know in this lecture,
what are the key messages,
is that inheritance allows developers
to add state and behavior and to
refine behavior in subclasses.
Usually, a class has only one superclass.
This is a single inheritance model.
All classes of the system eventually
inherit from `Object` which provides
the basic behavior for all objects
in the system.
Inheritance of state is static,
as we saw, so the instance variable
is computed from all instance variables
defined in the hierarchy of class
and the inheritance of behavior
is dynamic.