Hello everybody.
So this is the first lecture where
we will show a concrete case step
by step and this lecture,
this is about the reification and
the delegation.
So basically this is how did we
integrate inside `.pillar` a new
object so that we could have more
modularity inside `.pillar`.
So this is a case study,
we will show you step by step what
we did so that we could get microdown,
which is a markup language into
the `.pillar` compilation chain.
So the goal here, this is to show
you with a concrete case how the
fact that you have specific object
or dedicated object can support
delegation and that delegation creates
dispatch space.
So this means that suddenly,
I will avoid to have conditional,
but just send message to the right
object.
You will see that again,
in the strategy design pattern later
in the MOOC.
We will study a concrete case,
the way `.pillar` was changed to
introduce the support for microdown
format and also how can we do it
modularly.
Pillar, this is basically a document
compilation chain.
It means it produces MOOC's slide
like the one that you see on the screen,
and websites.
So Pillar uses a `.pillar` file
containing Pillar text.
So Pillar, this is the name of the
compilation chain, but this is also
the name of the markup language.
This is a null markup language that
we want to remove and use markdown
instead, but we want to do that
step by step so that we can still
use Pillar to produce documents
and slowly use also microdown to
produce the same document.
So in fact, we got a new requirement
and this is like in real life.
So Pillar should handle markdown
files containing microdown text
and the challenge was,
Okay, how do we support this new
requirement, and how do we do it
step by step without breaking the
system?
So that's also something important.
This change evolved over a month
or two and we didn't want it to
break everything.
Let me show you how Pillar manages
the file.
So basically, Pillar will get as
input a document with some markdown
and then it will ask a parser and
the parser will convert this input
file into a tree of object.
So here, you will have for example
a header, a text and so on.
So here, this is a tree of objects.
So how this is done?
Okay, we ask the parser to parse
the input.
In fact, in Pillar, there are several
parsers and there is one in particular
that is called PRParser and now
how this is done?
This is that there is one parser
because at that time there was only
one syntax associated with the class
`PRDocument`.
This is what we see here.
When we want to parse an input,
we request the class,
Okay, Class, can you give me the
parser and we send the message parser
file with the file as reference.
So in this version, it was already
good because it avoids to hardcode
the parser everywhere in the code.
We only got one single entry point
to access the parser.
This approach worked when we wanted
to substitute different versions
of the parsers that we have to check
if they are more robust or have
different properties like speed
and things like that.
This was nice because we could have,
we had only one single place to change.
Now the problem is that if we want
to have another format,
it does not work anymore.
If we look in the build chain,
so I don't want to go into detail,
but in the OutputDocument,
so this means to produce something,
we have a buildOn.
What we will do is that we will
have a parse, this parse expression,
then after we will transform the
document and then we write the code
and then we do post transformation
and this parseInput document this
is where we see the expression that
I mentioned before.
We ask the document class,
"Hey, give me your parser".
So basically, this is a global variable
that is disguised.
You will see that there is also
another lecture on singleton and
disguised global variable,
but this is a typical case.
And we parse the file and then this
guy will return a parsedDocument.
So it worked, so this is not the
problem.
This is that when we want to change
something, then suddenly we have
to pay attention because this is
not easy to change.
The implication is that there is
only one parser, there is only one
syntax, it was really good when
we had only one syntax,
but now we have two syntaxes,
so what do we do?
This is the problem, and then also
the other limits, this is that the
check for file extension are hardcoded
somewhere in the code.
So this means that suddenly,
this is not because you provide
an .md file that it will be managed
correctly because if the system
looks for `.pillar` file it will
ignore the .md file.
In addition, for example,
a file does not know its project.
So when the project is an object
that represents how to build it
and things like that and how to
access the configuration.
So basically, at the end,
we could not distinguish between
a `.pillar` and a .md file and even
if we could, we had only one parser.
So what is the solution,
and we will do this solution step
by step.
This is, instead of manipulating
directly a `.pillar` file and a
.md file and doing the check,
what we will do is that we will
create an object that represents
the input and this object will know,
Oh, this is a `.pillar` file that
I should read, in that case,
I should invoke the correct parser.
So what we will do is that we will
reify, create an object that has
the responsibility to represent
what is an input and each input
will know its format and all kinds
of things like the parser.
And then, we will get one parser
per input format.
So the first step was to introduce
the class `InputDocument`,
so instead of manipulating files,
we want to manipulate objects.
And an `InputDocument` just wraps
the files and more information like
file extension and parser.
This was the code for example to
identify the file that should be
treated.
You know, it was checking,
Okay I want to check all the children
and I check if this is a file and
if it has a file extension that
is called `.pillar`, and then what
we did, we said, Okay,
in that case here, let's introduce
a `PillarInputDocument` with specifying.
So here, we create our first
implementation of an `InputDocument`.
Like that, suddenly, with this change,
we don't manipulate any more files,
but we manipulate `InputDocument`
and then naturally we can say,
oh, you are an `InputDocument` so
now the parser, I don't have to
ask it to the `PRDocument` of the class,
but to the `PRInputDocument`.
So here I just put the checks that says,
okay I know this parser,
this is `PRDocument` parser and
now this is responsibility of this
`InputDocument` to return the correct
parser.
You see, for the moment,
the solution does not fully work
because it only manages Pillar and
is still doing a check that at the
end we will remove.
But this is, we will do it step by step,
so this is what we call a little
chicken step.
So one of the ideas is that each
time we did those changes,
we wanted to have always green test
and little modifications so that
we can control what we are breaking
and do not stay a month with a broken
system that says Yes,
tomorrow, it will work.
No, we wanted every day that at
the end of the day, all our tests
were green.
So what we see is that here,
we didn't distribute the responsibility
first.
What you see is that here,
we are still doing the checks here
and not inside.
So the next step will be to move
this inside this object.
So to support .md files,
the compilation chain should accept
.md file.
It has a different syntax and a
different parser.
So what we ended up doing because
I want to show you a synthesized
version because else that can be
really difficult to follow.
At the end, we subclass from this
original `InputDocument` a class
that is managing `.pillar` documents,
and then we did another subclass
to manage MicrodownInputDocument.
What you see that here the methods,
this class has two methods.
One is called parserClass and
parsedDocument.
So parserClass here will say,
Oh, I want to use the `.pillar` parser,
or this is this document parser
that we had previously and the
parsedDocument, this is the object
that will have the responsibility
to invoke the right parser with
the file contents.
On microdown, we have also the same API.
We will have the Microdown parser
that will return a parser that knows
that and then, it will parse the same,
except that here, you see,
there is these little things here
is that when we were at this phase
of the work, we could not do any
treatment on a Microdown files.
We had no visitors and nothing,
we just wanted to get the Microdown
input and convert that internally
as a Pillar internal model.
So that's why here, what we said,
we said, Oh, you know,
this is easy.
We parse with the parser,
and then we convert, we have a visitor
that converts the document model
expressed in Microdown in Pillar.
Now this is not anymore the case
because we are further in the migration.
But the idea is this move was the
cheapest move to be able to get
a different syntax working with
all the tools that we had,
like different visitors and
transformations that I showed at
the beginning, the phases.
So the idea is that, Okay,
here we convert a different input
into an internal format that is
the same as before.
But you see, this is the `InputDocument`
of Microdown that is responsible
for doing this transformation.
When I call, when I use a Pillar
document, I don't do the transformation.
So what you see is that basically,
what we got is that instead of having
this parserInputFile that I show
you at the beginning on the output
document, then it becomes just,
Oh, you know, I have an input file,
I just ask the file to do the job
and I move this code in the
`InputDocument` object.
So I give more responsibility to
my object and this is the same,
this is what I show in the UML diagram
is that we can do the same with the…
what you see that you have the same
input and things like that.
So in the UML diagram,
I was a bit wrong but because we
have multiple parsers,
so here I show that we use the previous
parser.
So now, we add the delegation,
the extension checks.
We don't want to have a place where
we have to do "or if this is that"
or "if this is that" or "if this
is that".
So what we did is that we introduce
the responsibility in the
`PillarInputDocument` to manage
the extension.
And we said, Do you deal with this
extension, and each of them said,
Okay this is the extension I want
to deal with.
So we could have also includes and
said okay that you can manage multiple
extensions, for example like that,
I could say something like,
if this is MD or if this is md includes
an extension, and I would get multiple,
I would get all these extensions
managed for the Microdown.
But again, what you see is that
we pushed this behavior,
which was central in a place before,
that was in the output document,
we push it to the corresponding object,
like that, the object has the
responsibility and we are able to
dispatch, and we don't make a explicit
test.
So then, we got the following question.
What if…
So now we could parse .md and `.pillar`
format, the question was,
Okay, now we would like to be able
to phase out the `.pillar` version.
It is still not the case,
but we want to make sure that they
are optional because like that suddenly
we could say, Oh, please do not
load this package, and then we don't
have the support for `.pillar` because
this is what we want to do,
we don't want to maintain two versions
in the long term.
So the question was how to make
them optional.
So how to make them optional,
we use a registration mechanism
so that every new `InputDocument`
kinds can declare their existence
and say, Oh.
So we define on the `PRInputDocument`
class an inputClass for aFile.
And these methods, based on the
extension, you see, this is where
you see the doesHandle.
We could say, Okay, in all the
subclasses of `PRDocument` is there
one that will manage the extension
of this file.
And here, we have a null object that
we will see in the future lecture.
This is a null object pattern that says,
Oh, by the way, I have no document,
so this means that I have no parser,
I will raise an error and like that,
we don't have to do am if,
if there and things like that,
and we can have different…
We can manage the null situation.
And what you see is that here,
each subclass, when we load the package,
each subclass of `InputDocument`
will declare and said,
Oh, I'm available, I'm here.
Now, since they all expose the same
API which it doesHandleExtension,
then we will select the correct
one for a given file.
Note that this way of doing a
registration is based on the reflective
API of Pharo and we can do a better
registration.
We did it like that in `.pillar`
because it was cheap,
but there are better ways to do
that and there is a dedicated lecture
for this aspect in the future.
So what you see is that at the end,
now we can revisit the code of files
to be built that I showed at the
beginning.
And what we do is we said,
Oh, given a set of files,
we just want to create the corresponding
because this method here will return
either a `PRPillarInputDocument`
or a 'PRMicrodownInputDocument`.
So depending on the file extension,
I will get a given `InputDocument`.
What you should see is that here,
I can mix .md and  .pillar  file
because for each file,
I will get the correct input.
So now, I can also support the
incremental migration of the books
that are written in a `.pillar`
and that the author can mix Microdown
and `.pillar`.
So from that perspective,
that's really nice.
What you see is that this design
really supports well the end user.
So to step back, what we did,
we turned implicit things into an
object.
Basically, we were file checking
plus parser and we turn that into
an `InputDocument` object.
We specialize this one object because
at the beginning, there was only one.
We specialize this one object into
hierarchies, so we went from one
single class `InputDocument`,
we turn it into an abstract class
with Microdown and `.pillar`.
We define polymorphic behavior in
this object.
So here, you have the same API,
they answer the same message.
So this means that from the client
point of view, here, I could call
either this one or that one without
taking care.
So from that perspective,
the fact that we created this hierarchy
and this object, we created dispatch
space.
This means that I just send a message
and the system will resolve.
So if tomorrow, I want an alternate
syntax, I just have to define a
new subclass, which the same API,
and that will say, Oh I handle,
I don't know,
ascii doc format or txt or whatever,
and plus a parser and I'm done.
And then, we use a registration
mechanism so that each of this can
be unloaded and the system can continue
to work or that we can mix files
from different formats.
So from that perspective,
I think that this is a really nice
case study to show that creating
an object was making sure that we
can suddenly get a modular system
and decouple the responsibility.
So as a conclusion, what we did
is that we we define object.
We define each object and its own
behavior, we delegate to such objects
and this is really important to think,
sometimes, if you have a condition,
you said, Oh, I am writing a condition.
The question is, else,
do I have an object to which I can
send a message, and this is what
you have with the "Tell,
do not ask." At the beginning,
the files, we are asking the extension
and things like that and at the end,
we have this registration mechanism
and we just said, Oh,
I want to produce that and the system
does it for us.
So there is a nice pattern that
is in the Object-Oriented Reengineering
Patterns book that is called "Transform
Conditionals" and I really encourage
you to read this chapter.
The book is available on the web.