- Hello.
So in this lecture, I will really
focus on the Essence of Dispatch.
Basically, this lecture is the
cornerstone of many other lectures,
and it will present something that
is really fundamental in the
object-oriented programming,
and many designs are based on this idea.
So we will focus on what does it
mean for real Dispatch.
So the objectives, this is really
to understand what is like binding
or to understand what is in fact
sending a message and not just something
that you write fast and then you
think that you understand,
but at the end, you don't get it.
So this is really the heart of
object-oriented design.
So we will take some time to go
over that.
I will take `Boolean` as an example
for this lecture.
So in Pharo, `Booleans` are,
I would say, normal.
They just have a superb implementation
that we will discover.
So you get classical messages like `&`,
`or`, `not` that are eager.
So that means that both arguments
are executed, or in Pharo,
the receiver and the argument are
executed, evaluated or you have
also `or` and `and` like a lazy one,
which will only execute what is
needed on demand.
And in Pharo, you have also what
is a bit different from the other
languages.
You have also the condition,
`ifTrue:ifFalse` `ifFalse:ifTrue.`
And yes, conditionals in Pharo are
messages that are sent to `booleans`
object.
But this is not the focus of this
lecture.
I just wanted to take this example
because it is really beautiful.
So the first thing that we will do,
this is you will do three exercises.
So I will present an exercise and
then I will let a couple of minutes
so that you can press pause and
do it at home.
So the first example will be implement
`not`, the `boolean` negation.
The second example will be implement
`or`.
And the third example,
this is, what is the goal of this
example?
The key question behind that and
the third one is the most interesting
one.
This is, why do I ask these two
questions in the first place?
So let's start to focus on the first
example.
So I want that you propose an
implementation of `not` in a world
where you have two objects,
`true` and `false`, and you only
have objects and messages.
So what you should see is that here,
basically, I have the object `false`,
I send the message `not`,
it returns `true`.
So in Java, for example,
you will write it like that.
You send the message `not` to the
object `false`.
And then, when you have the object
`true`, you send the message 'not'
and you will get `false`,
for the same that would be true,
I send the message `not` and I get
`false`.
So I will give you some hints for
this exercise.
So the first hint is that the solution
does not use any explicit conditionals,
so the solution does not use any
`if` statement.
So I know that this is a difficult
hint because usually,
the first reflex that you have is
to use a `if` to implement `not`.
What I can tell you is that the
solution does not need any `if`.
So I will make a pause after each
hint so that like that,
you can press pause and try to sketch
something on a piece of paper if
you want.
Okay.
The second hint, this is basically
how do you express choices in
object-oriented programming?
Basically, what you do is that you
will define classes or different
classes that have compatible methods.
What does it mean?
It means that you can send the message
to any of the instances and then
the correct method will be executed.
And this is what we will see in
the example.
So basically, you send a message
to an instance and the right method
will be executed.
So this is what we call:
we let the receiver decide !
So let's look at an example of that.
You see, when I have a variable
`x` and I send the message 'open',
so if I write 'x.open' in Java-like
syntax, it means that `x` can be a file,
it can be a window, or it can be a tool.
The only interesting thing is that
I want to execute the open method
that is associated either with a file,
a window or a tool.
And basically, the method that will
be executed is based on the class
of the receiver.
So I don't know if that gives you
some idea how to implement `not`.
But let's see, because now I will
give you a third hint.
So the solution has at least two
classes.
What does it mean?
It means that in our solution,
`true`, the object `true` is the
singleton instance of the class True.
The object `false` that I gave you
at the beginning is the singleton
instance of the class False.
So the singleton aspect is just
to make sure that this is like that
in Pharo.
But in this lecture, we don't care
that this is a singleton or not.
So actually, the Pharo implementation
use three classes; `Boolean`,
`True` and `False`.
So let's look at that.
So we have a `Boolean` that is abstract.
It is not necessary to have it.
We could have a solution without
`Booleans,` but this is good for
reuse purposes.
And then, we have the class True
with its instance `true` and the
class False with its instance `false`.
And we have two methods.
So here, we will have a method in
the class True and a method `not`
in the class False.
So now normally, you should get
what is the implementation.
So basically, in the class False,
the implementation of `not`,
this is just to return `true`.
In the class True the implementation
of `not`, this is just to return
`false`.
So let's look at it graphically.
So we have a situation like that.
`not` in class True returns `false`.
`false` in the class False `not`
returns `true`.
So how does it work at runtime?
So now I send the message `not`
to the object `true`.
So I look in the class of the receiver,
which is 'True'.
And I find `not` here.
I say oh, this is this one,
and I return `false`.
Now when I send a message `not`
to my instance `false`,
where do I look?
I look in the class False.
I find the method `not`,
which is this one, and returns 'True'.
So what you see is that we have
two classes.
And because we have two classes,
we have two methods.
And the correct method will be executed
depending on the receiver.
What we see is that in the Pharo
implementation, we will have the
class `Boolean`, which is abstract,
the class True, and the class False.
They implement all these different
kinds of methods that they specialize
for the specific instance.
So now, let's look at the second
example.
So the idea, this is to implement `or`.
So here, I wrote the table for `or`.
So if I have `true` or `true`,
I get true.
If I have `true` or `false`,
I get `true`.
If I have `true` or anything,
If I get `false` or `true`,
I get `true`, `false` or `false`,
I get `false`, and `false` or anything,
which is anything.
So just take two minutes and propose
an implementation of this method.
So basically, we will have the same
that for all.
On the classe `Boolean`,
we have an abstract method.
So in Pharo, we write such subclass
responsibility.
But it means that the method is
abstract.
And then, on the class False,
what do we have?
We will have, if I have a method
`or` with an argument,
I just return the argument.
Because this is what is written here.
So if I have `true`, I return `true`,
if I have `false`, I return `false`,
anything returns anything.
So I said, okay, just return the
argument.
This is what it means.
Now let's look at the class True.
So this is the value for `or` in
presence when the receiver is `true`.
So in the class True,
I just return `true`.
So this is what I'm doing here.
So again, what you see is that I
have two implementations for the
method "or`.
So basically, just a parenthesis,
in Pharo, if you look at the code,
you will see that this is not return
`true` like that, but `self`,
indeed because the receiver is `true
`in that case.
So I really return the receiver.
This is what I mean.
So if we look at it visually,
again, we have two implementations
of `or`, this one and this one.
When I send a message to True to
this receiver, I will look here
and it will return me `true`.
And when I send a message here,
or an argument, I will look for
this one and it will return me the
argument, so we get done.
Let's step back.
In fact, what we see in this example
is that at no point in time I was
asking, what is the receiver?
I was never asking a question.
I was just answering things.
So this is an example of a principle
that we will see over and over in
the MOOC.
This is the Do not ask,
tell principle.
Here basically, we delegate the
resolution to the correct object.
So when I have `true`,
this is the class True that will
do something.
When I send a message to False,
this is the class False that will
do something, and each subclass,
the class True and the class False,
will implement their own logic.
So as a summary, what we see is
that the solution was really that
we implemented operation and we
end up sending a message,
was basically making a choice.
So I send the message to the object
and then the object was selecting
the correct method for me.
What you see is that,
in fact, I didn't reply to the third
exercises and it will be in the
next lecture because this is so
important that we will do that in
a separate lecture.