- Hello.
In this lecture, we are going to
talk about super and what does it
mean to make a super message send.
So before in the previous lectures,
we saw what it means to send a message,
what it is the method lookup and
today we are going to extend the
previous lectures with super message
sends.
So we are going to talk about the
semantics of super and what are
the differences with self.
Those are the main topics of this
lecture.
So first, I would like that you
take five minutes to try to write
a definition of what is super and
what does it mean to send a message
to super like this here.
Your definition should have two
main points.
So what does it mean super?
So what does it represent and what
is the message that is going to
be looked up in this message send.
Now you can also take five minutes
here and try to answer these three
questions.
So imagine that you have these three
classes; the class A,
the class B and the class C.
So C inherits from B,
B inherits from A.
They define methods foo and bar
that are as they are defined in
these little boxes here and we have
three different instances.
So we have an instance of A that
is instantiated like this,
we have an instance of B that is
instantiated like this.
So we have an instance of A,
an instance of B and an instance of C.
And we are going to send each of
these a message bar.
Take a couple of minutes to try
to understand what will be the result
of each of these expressions.
If you did well, you probably reached
these answers.
So the result to send a message
bar to an instance of A will be 10,
the result of sending a message
bar to an instance of B is 20 and
bar to an instance of C is a 100.
So how does it work?
First, imagine let's take the third
example that is probably one of
the most interesting here.
So we have an instance of C is C new.
So the first thing that is going
to happen is we have here our instance
of C and we are sent.
So this one is an instance of C
and we're going to send it the message
bar, yeah, okay like this.
So we send the message bar to an
instance of C and following the
rules of the method lookup that
we saw before, the first thing that
we need to do is to search for the
class of the object.
So we see that the class of C instance
is the class C.
So we are going to start the lookup
there and we're going to look for
the message, the method bar.
So in this case, C doesn't define
a method bar.
So we are going to follow the
inheritance link and we are going
to look for the method bar in the
superclass.
Here we find the the method bar
in B and this method is defined
as in here.
So it's saying to return the result
of 'super bar + self foo'.
So now, we need to define what is
super bar ?
So we are here.
So super bar is of course is another
message sent.
So the thing that will change here
is that super is also a reference
to our instance C.
But it will change the way the method
lookup works.
So here we're going to send the
message bar to the object aC.
But we're going to start the method
lookup in A.
So we're going to start the method
lookup in here, we're going to find
the method bar in A as it is defined
in here.
We're going to execute cell foo
and send to it at the instance of
C and of course sending the message
foo to the instance of C,
it results in 50.
That means that this one,
it value is 50 and then we are going
to do cell foo here again as itself
is also the instance of C.
The result of this expression doing
the lookup in C and finding this
the method foo here again.
It's also 50.
So at the end, 50 plus 50,
the result of our main message is 100.
So what is the definition of super?
Super actually changes where the
lookup starts.
So I already told you in the previous
slide that super refers to the same
object as self.
Yeah, so it is a receiver of the
message.
Now take a couple of minutes to
understand and to try to define
where the method lookup starts when
we have a message to super.
So the answer is that the method
lookup starts in the super class
of the class that contains the super
expression.
So imagine that we have the same
example as before.
We have B and we have here a super
foo and we have method foo in here
and we have foo.
So since this super foo expression
is defined in the class B,
the method lookup is going to start
in the super class of B.
So super is in B and the lookup
starts in super class.
Yes.
There is a main difference between
self and super.
So self is really dynamic.
At compile time, we don't know where
the method is going to be found
and what is the kind of object that
is pointed by self.
We only know that it is an object
from the hierarchy, but we don't
know if the object is low in the
hierarchy, around here or higher
in the hierarchy.
Yeah, so since we cannot know that,
we don't know where the method lookup
is going to start and we don't know
exactly at each call site what is
the method that is going to be executed.
Super differently from self is static.
So that means that just by looking
at the code and how it is organized,
I know exactly where the method
lookup is going to start and I know
what is the method that is going
to be found.
So here for example, I know that
super foo is installed in the class B.
so the lookup is going to start
in A and that means that I'm always
going to find this method foo from
this call side here.
That is why we say that super is
static and it's defined at compile time.
What you should know is that even
some books get it wrong.
So there are some books that will
define super sense in this way.
So super looks for a method in the
super class of the receiver class.
What does it mean?
Is that if I have an instance of C,
I do a super send to an instance of C,
it will always start from the super
class of its class.
So in this case.
it will take its class and start
from the super class B.
The problem with this definition
is that it may create loops.
So this is not the right definition.
So let's see with an example what
happens here when I send to C to
this C instance the message foo.
What will happen is that we are
going to send a message foo to a
C and with the first time so doing
a C foo, and this will do a normal
message send with a normal method
lookup.
So it will take the C instance,
it will take its class and then
it will look up starting from there
the method foo.
So C doesn't define a method foo,
it will look up in the super class
B and it will find foo defined as this.
So this definition of foo will do
super foo.
If we use this definition that we
saw before, super foo should start
from taking the instance the receiver,
which is a C.
It will take its class and then
its super class and restart the
method lookup from there.
So that means that it will start
to look for foo from B.
Starting from B will find foo the
same method foo as before again
and it will execute the same method
foo again.
So this will loop like this.
Yeah.
Instead with our definition that
is taking the place where the super
expression is defined and going
to the super class to start looking
for the method, this expression
will actually do the following.
So we take C, we send a message
foo like this.
We find this method first and then
we do the super foo.
Super foo will start the method
lookup from A from the super class
of the method where the super is
and it will find the method foo
defined above.
So that means that this expression
returns 10 and this expression which
is this expression returns 10.
What you should know is that self
and super always represent the receiver.
They represent the same object.
So what you should think about is
what happens if you do self equals
equals super. So meaning here equals
identity comparison, the one that
really compares object pointers.
So the difference between self and
super is that super changes the
method lookup.
Self always starts from the class
of the receiver object.
In this sense, self sense act as a hook.
That means that they can be redefined
in subclasses to do different things.
However.
super always goes up in the hierarchy.
So it can never be redefined by
subclasses.