- Hello!
In this lecture, we will have some
discussions about
the Visitor design pattern.
The goal is to revisit the Visitor
design pattern and to discuss some
specific points or variations that
we could have on it.
For example, about the navigation
control, about cons that are usually
against the Visitor pattern,
or about the method granularity
or the double dispatch shortcutting.
First of all, controlling the traversal.
A visitor embeds the traversal of
a tree structure, and usually,
this traversal could be either on
the visitor side or on the domain side.
Usually, this is on the visitor side,
but it depends on the context.
Let's give an example of it.
Here, in this design,
we chose to put the traversal on
the visitor side.
It means that here, in the `visitPlus`
method of the evaluator, the visitor,
we recursively visit the left side
and the right side of
the `Plus` structure.
In this alternative design,
the recursion is not done at all
in the `visitPlus`.
Here, this is done on the domain side.
It means that when we accept the
visitor in a `Plus`, we will directly
send the visit message on the left
side and the visit message on the
right side to the visitor.
Here, this is the domain side that
initiates the visiting of the tree
structure.
Let's talk about another aspect
of visitors: it externalizes the
behavior out of domain objects.
It means that some operations are
modularized inside visitors and
not directly in the classes of the
domain.
On the contrary, it provides a clear
separation between the states of
the operation and the state of domain
objects.
Because now, you can embed specific
states for a specific operation
inside its visitor class.
And then, you will have the possibility
to package operations independently.
And it provides you with an incremental
definition of operations because
this is just a matter of adding
a new visitor in a new subclass.
It brings a lot by extracting the
operations from the domain object
and putting them in the visitors.
Now let's talk about another variation
point.
When we are using a language that
supports a class extension,
like Pharo, it means that we can
directly introduce new methods inside
existing classes, and those new
methods could belong to another
package in the class in which we
define these new methods.
This is really nice because we could
imagine inserting `accept`methods
inside existing classes and packaging
those `accept` methods in a visitor
package.
But it wouldn't be that good because
it would prevent us from defining
a specific state for a visitor because
we can package methods separately
but we cannot introduce a new state.
And then, a visitor is an encapsulation
of a complex operation.
It means that reifying the visitor
is always good.
Now let's talk about the methods'
granularity.
For that, you could compare those
two designs.
We have a `SimpleNodeVisitor` here
and we have a `ProgramNodeVisitor`.
The only difference is that inside
this one we have one method,
`visitNode`, a generic method,
and inside this visitor,
we have multiple methods.
And the idea is that the
`ProgramNodeVisitor` has a richer API.
Each time this method,
for example, `visitTemporaryVariable`,
is executed, it means that we know
that the parameter is a temporary
variable.
So, there is a context that is embedded
inside each method of the visitor.
So, a visit method encodes a context.
And then, a too-high-level API will
require a lot of tests.
It means that here, in the simple
version, if I want to write the
code inside of this method,
I will probably need to test what
the parameter (n) is - is it a local
variable?
Is it a temporary variable?
What is it?
- to have the correct action.
On the contrary, when the API is richer,
it means that this is automatically
done because the domain calls a
specific method.
Usually, this is much better to
have a richer API on your visitor.
Now let's talk about shortcutting
the double dispatch.
Here's an example.
I have a `visit` method in the visitor
`RBProgramNodeVisitor`, and inside
this method, there is a message send,
`visitVariable`.
The visitor is doing a self-send.
Usually, we call it a shortcut.
We are shortcutting the double dispatch
because the visitor is doing a
self-send, so it means that we do
not let the domain decide and dispatch
directly to the domain side so that
it will double dispatch to the visitor
side.
Like that, it prevents the use of
more specialized API.
It means that the domain side could
send us a message: `visitLocalVariable`
or `visitTemporaryVariable` or
`visitInstanceVariable`.
It could directly test for us using
the double dispatch.
That's why this is normally better
to not shortcut the double dispatch
and use a form of code like that:
`each acceptVisitor: self`,
and not sending directly the message
`visitVariable`.
Another discussion or variation
point when we are designing a visitor
is that when we are using a collection
in the domain, we sometimes wonder
if it's necessary to turn this
collection into a domain element.
When we have a collection,
it may be important for the visitor
to take some action or some specific
operation on those collections.
Usually, this is a variation point,
this is a design choice.
Should I promote this collection
in my domain or should I provide
an API on my visitor,
like `visitArrayOf` or something
like that? This is always a trade-off.
Now building a generic visitor is
usually difficult.
Usually, this is much better to
have an `AbstractVisitor` class.
You could define an API on this
class for each visit method and
you will have a lot of subclasses
that specialize this API for special
cases.
Like that, I can provide some families
of visitors and share codes between
them.
Now let's discuss another point.
When we are using a statically typed
language, we have two alternatives
to implement a visitor.
The first one could be to have one
method `visit`, and this is the same one,
with different parameter types:
`(Number)`, `(Plus)`,
and `(Times)`.
An alternative design could be to
have multiple methods - `visitNumber`,
`visitPlus`, and `visitTimes` -
with specific parameter types.
The first case here is called
overloading because we are using
the same method with different parameter
types.
Usually, this is not the right way
to design a visitor because you
will have to cast your object explicitly
everywhere in your code.
You might execute the wrong method,
and to understand what is this point,
I encourage you to see the lecture
about overload vs.
override.
In conclusion, Visitor is a very
nice design pattern but it could
be tricky to master.
And usually, it helps a lot if you
carefully use the `accept` and `visit`
vocabulary.
Visitor is powerful for complex
structure operations,
and as we saw, we can modularize
operations outside of domain objects.
And it provides a kind of pluggable
recursive treatment of a composite
structure.