- Hello!
In this lecture, we'll discuss something
really interesting.
This is a Visitor Design Pattern,
and this is one of my favorite ones.
So the goal of this lecture is to
start by studying some examples
to motivate the need for this design
pattern.
Then we will focus on the explanation
of this specific design pattern.
And finally, we will discuss some
pros and cons of it.
So let's start with a simple example.
Imagine we want to represent,
to design a system, a simple
mathematical system, in which we
reified some ‘Plus‘.
So here you have the ‘Plus‘ class.
And when you have the ‘Plus‘,
you have two operands.
You have the left one and the right one.
As you saw in the code there,
we reified everything.
So everything is reified.
OK.
In Pharo, we could have done something
simpler.
We could have not wrapped numbers,
because this is possible in Pharo
to add some method on existing classes.
So, for example, we could have
implemented our own method directly
on the ‘Number‘ class of Pharo.
But this is just a parenthesis,
we will not do that, and we will
continue with the first version
in the following of this lecture.
To represent this kind of expression,
what we do is we use a Composite
Design Pattern.
So this is something that you already
saw in a previous lecture.
And here, what we can see in this
example, we have the expression
abstract class.
And we only have one kind of
leaf, the ‘Number‘.
And then we have a composite structure
there and two recursions.
So an operation is composed of a
left expression and a right expression.
And there are two kinds of operations
that are supported in this design,
‘Plus‘ and ‘Times‘.
So let's see some examples.
For example, if I want to represent
the value one, the number one in
my system, what I will do is I will
do ‘Number value: 1‘.
So this is a class method that I
send to the class, value.
And like that, I can wrap the number
one.
If I want to represent this expression
there, three times two,
what I can do is I can use the message
left, right, and send to the class
‘Times‘.
And then I can fix the left operand
and the right operand.
The same here for a more complex
expression.
So this is a ‘Plus‘.
On the left, there is only one,
and on the right, there is a ‘Times‘
with three on the left and two on
the right.
OK, so we understood the model,
the design of the model,
which is a Composite,
a regular Composite Design Pattern
to represent some mathematical
expressions.
So what do we want to do with this
model?
We want to implement two different
operations.
So the first one is Evaluation.
So I would like to be able to evaluate
some mathematical expressions.
So, for example, if I have this
kind of mathematical expression,
I would like to obtain seven.
And I want to be able to print them.
So to print them in a Polish notation,
it means that we first print the
operation.
So here, this is ‘Plus‘,
and here I have the left operand
and then the right operand.
And here, this is another expression.
So I have the ‘Times‘,
and here I have the left operand,
and here the right operand.
So this is a specific notation for
mathematical expression.
So how can we implement these two
operations?
First of all, first design.
What I could do is I could add some
specific methods in the whole hierarchy
of the composite.
So here we introduce the ‘evaluate‘
message in all classes of the composite.
So we have an ‘evaluate‘ in ‘Number‘,
‘evaluate‘ in ‘Plus‘,
and ‘evaluate‘ in ‘Times‘.
Then we introduce another message,
‘print‘, for the second operation
in all classes also.
So this first design,
if we look at the implementation of it,
for example, evaluating a ‘Number‘
consists in just returning the value
of the number.
But evaluating a ‘Plus‘ expression
means that I need to evaluate the
left operand plus the right operand.
OK.
And then for the ‘print‘,
if I need to print a ‘Number‘,
I just compute the string representation
of the value, of the number,
And then, etc.
For the Plus.
So what can we say about this design?
So first of all, some operations
require a stack.
So it means that if I need to,
for example, print the expression
in a different form, for example,
instead of printing in Polish notation,
I could directly print an expression
like that, 3 + 2, and this is called
the infix form, to represent some
mathematical operation.
And for that, I need a stack.
And the question is, where should
I put this stack?
Where should I define this state?
I can declare a stack directly in
the domain, in the composite,
but this is strange because the
stack will only be used when I print.
So this is not really nice from
the design point of view.
And it will lead to mix the
states of operations,
here printing, and the state of
the items themselves, so it means
the domain, the mathematical elements,
so ‘Number‘, ‘Plus‘, ‘Times‘,
etc.
So this is not good at all from
the design point of view of mixing
these two kinds of states.
And if we look at a bigger system,
a real system, for example,
the Pillar Pharo library.
So the domain contains about 50
classes and it represents some document
models.
You remember, titles,
headers, paragraphs, sections,
etc.
And then we have different operations
supported on this model.
We have exporting to LaTeX,
exporting to HTML, Beamer,
ASCII, Markdown, etc.
And we have some code checkers,
etc.
So a lot of different operations
are supported on those 50 classes
that represent the model of a document.
So you can imagine that we have
a lot of states that are specific
to the LaTeX exporter,
for example, and mixing all of that
in the domain classes will not be nice.
So what can we do?
First of all, the conclusion of
this first design is mixing everything
in the domain classes.
So it blows up the class API.
So it means that all states of all
operations plus the state of the
domain elements are mixed inside
the same classes.
So we are mixing some concerns.
Then this is a non-modular or not
well-modularized system.
And then it prevents some extension.
So it means that this is difficult,
each time we want to add a new kind
of operation, we need to change
the domain model.
If it is a model that comes from
a third-party library,
this is difficult to modify it or
to extend it.
It depends on the language we are using.
So this is the essence of the Visitor
design pattern.
This is why it is needed.
So a Visitor is something that
represents an operation.
It decouples this operation from
the domain objects.
So we have the domain objects on
one side and we have the operation
we want to apply to these domain
objects.
And there are a lot of objects in
this domain.
It supports modularity.
It means that we can package separately
the Visitor, the operation to evaluate
from the domain of the mathematical
expression.
And it supports extensions.
So it means that we can provide
new operations on the same model.
This is without changing the domain
objects.
So this is the essence of the Visitor
design pattern.
So we have the ‘Domain‘ model on
one side, here it is on the right,
and we have the ‘Visitor‘ on the
left side.
And if we look at it,
this is a composite design pattern,
it does not change.
We have the recursions that are there.
An operation is composed of expressions.
And then, in the ‘Visitor‘ package,
we have two kinds of visitors.
In fact, in this example,
we have three visitors,
an Evaluator, so it can evaluate
an expression to compute its value,
a Printer, and an InfixPrinter.
So here it can print the expression
in Polish notation, and here in
infix notation using a stack.
And the stack is well-defined and
well-modularized in the Printer.
So what are the key points of the
Visitor design pattern?
It requires a structure to operate on.
So a Visitor must be applied on a Domain.
And this Domain should be a
pre-structure.
So usually, this is a Composite.
Then it performs different actions
based on different kinds of elements.
So it means that a Visitor,
an Evaluator, will do something
different if it visits a ‘Number‘
or if it visits a ‘Times‘ operation.
So based on the elements that are
in the Domain, it will perform different
actions.
And then a Visitor manages its own
specific states.
This is what we saw with the infix
printer.
We can define some specific states
inside the Visitor, which are different
from the states of the Domain objects.
And Visitors are independent from
each other.
So this is really nice to be able
to load and to separate operations
and to load them independently.
So Visitors and Composites are two
design patterns that are a perfect
match.
They can play very nicely together.
So how can we use Visitors?
So let's start with that.
So here, we have a complex mathematical
expression.
And now I have a Visitor there,
an Evaluator.
I can instantiate it and I can send
it the message evaluate.
I pass there as an argument the
expression and it will answer the
result, seven.
I have another Visitor there,
the Printer.
I can instantiate it.
I can send the message Print.
So you can see that each Visitor
can define its own methods.
So here the evaluator has an Evaluate
method, but the Printer has a Print
method.
So a Visitor is really a unique
object that can define its own state
and behavior.
Then I send the expression as an
argument to the print and it will
print the expression there.
And the InfixPrinter has the same
API as the Printer.
It will print the expression in
infix form.
So now we can have a closer look
at the implementation of the ‘Visitor‘.
So first of all, to implement a
‘Visitor‘, I should start by
instrumenting the Domain,
the domain objects.
So this is the first step.
to prepare the domain to accept
‘Visitors‘.
So how to do that?
It means that on all elements in
the domain, we will add a new method
that is prefixed by accept,
‘acceptVisitor‘.
And here is the parameter of this
method.
So we can define it here.
This method is abstract in the upper
class of the hierarchy of the domain,
in Expression.
And this is ‘acceptVisitor(v)‘ and
the parameter is a ‘Visitor‘.
And in ‘Number‘, I will have a method.
This method is redefined,
‘acceptVisitor(v)‘.
This is a ‘Visitor‘ that is passed
in argument.
And if we look at the implementation
of this method, what does it do?
It just sends the message ‘visitNumber‘
to the ‘Visitor‘ that has been passed
in the parameter.
The parameter that is passed is self.
And this is what is important.
So here we are telling the ‘Visitor‘
that the element that it is visiting
is aNumber.
And we know it because we are in
the Number class.
So we tell the ‘Visitor‘ what it
is currently visiting.
Then all the ‘acceptVisitor‘ methods
are defined only once for all ‘Visitors‘
in the domain.
So now this is the implementation
that we saw.
So it means that we need to redefine
the ‘acceptVisitor‘ in all elements
of the composite, of the Domain.
So on ‘Number‘, we will say ‘aVisitor‘
visits a number: self.
But on a ‘Plus‘, we will tell the
‘Visitor‘ that it is visiting a Plus,
and we will pass the element self
because this is a ‘Plus‘.
And the same for ‘Times‘.
As we already said, this is really
important, we will implement this
‘acceptVisitor‘ method only once
for all ‘Visitors‘ on the Domain objects.
Now it comes to implementing the
‘Visitors‘ themselves.
So, for example, for the Evaluator here,
we will implement the ‘visitNumber‘ method.
And now we know that the parameter
is aNumber.
And for aNumber, when I want to
evaluate aNumber, the only thing
that I need to do is to send the
message value to the wrapper object,
aNumber value.
But I need also to implement the
‘visitPlus‘.
And I know that the parameter is
anExpression.
In fact, I could be more specific.
Here, this is aPlus.
I'm sure this is aPlus because I
receive it from the domain.
And now there, what I should do
when I want to evaluate aPlus,
it means that I will send the
‘acceptVisitor‘ method on the left
operand and pass self,
the ‘Visitor‘ itself.
So it means that here I will propagate
recursively to the composite elements.
So I will evaluate the left side,
then the right side.
And I know that I'm doing aPlus
operation.
So that's why I put aPlus there.
And this is the same thing,
the same thing here for the ‘Times‘.
The ‘Visitor‘ is really nice to define,
to modularize some operations.
And it is really simple to implement
a new kind of operation because
implementing a new operation is
just implementing a new ‘Visitor‘.
So I will implement a new subclass
of the ‘Visitor‘ class,
for example a ‘Printer‘.
And then I will implement the expected
API.
And the expected API is really easy,
now we know it.
This is ‘visitNumber‘,
‘visitPlus‘ and ‘visitTimes‘.
These are the elements that are
defined in the domain.
Once I implemented a new ‘Visitor‘,
this is easy to use it.
So to use it, I could do anExpression
‘acceptVisitor‘: Printer new.
So here, this is my new Visitor.
Or I can do something simpler,
the reverse.
If I define the print method inside
the Visitor, I could do
‘Printer‘ new print: anExpression.
So let's step back a little bit
and try to really understand.
Did you really understand the subtle
interaction between the ‘acceptVisitor‘
and ‘visitXXX‘ methods?
And this is the key point to really
understand Visitor.
So we'll go back to it more in detail.
When I send a message to a ‘Printer‘,
so when I have a ‘Printer‘ object there,
and I send it the message Print,
and I pass anExpression to print.
So what happened?
So here, the ‘Printer‘ will answer.
So we will find this method.
And inside this method,
what does it do?
Basically, it just dispatches.
So we don't know what is this expression
there.
We don't know if it is a simple object,
a leaf in the composite,
like a number.
Or if it is a more complex expression,
like an operation, a ‘Plus‘,
a ‘Times‘ or whatever.
And we don't want to test specifically
in the ‘Visitor‘ code.
So what we will do is that we will
do a dispatch.
We will send the message ‘acceptVisitor‘
to the expression.
And this is the right method that
will be selected.
If you remember correctly,
we already spoke about that.
Sending a message is making a choice.
It means that the system will select
the right method to execute.
So here, if it is a number,
this is the method that will be
executed.
But if it is a ‘Plus‘,
this is the method that will be
executed.
So this is the first dispatch.
And the right expression element
will answer accordingly.
And now that we are there,
imagine it was a ‘Plus‘.
If the expression there was a ‘Plus‘,
it means that it is this method
that will be executed.
And here, what we will do inside
the implementation of this method,
if you remember when we implemented
the domain, we implemented it like this:
‘aVisitor‘ ‘visitPlus‘: self
So it means that we will do a second
dispatch, and we don't know which
‘Visitors‘ we have in this variable,
but this is the right ‘Visitor‘
that will answer correctly.
So if it is a ‘Printer‘ or an Evaluator
or whatever, it will execute its
‘visitPlus‘ method.
So in this case, it will be this one,
passing self,
so the expression ‘Plus‘.
So when we are executing in a ‘Visitor‘
the ‘visitPlus‘ method,
we are sure that the variable in
parameter, p, is a ‘Plus‘.
And this is the second dispatch.
So this is why we said that the
‘Visitor‘ design pattern is based
on double dispatch.
There is a first dispatch from the
‘Visitor‘ hierarchy to the Domain
hierarchy and a second dispatch
from the Domain hierarchy to the
‘Visitor‘ hierarchy.
So this is the core mechanism of
the ‘Visitor‘ design pattern.
If you look at it, there are no
conditional checks in the code.
Not at all.
We never test the specific node
elements that we have or the specific
‘Visitors‘ that we have.
This double dispatch provides a
decoupling between Visitors and
domain objects.
So this is really nice from the
extensibility point of view.
It provides also a decoupling between
the different ‘Visitors‘.
So now the question now that you
really understood the ‘Visitor‘
design pattern is: when should you use it?
So the idea is that you should use
it when you want to implement some
specific operation on structured
graphs or trees or things like that.
Let's give some examples.
If you have a parse tree,
this is a tree that represents a
piece of code, okay, like a program
node.
And inside this program node,
you have a bunch of expressions
and things like that.
And you want to use a ‘Visitor‘
because you will implement different
‘Visitors‘.
One specific for the compilation,
you will emit some bytecode in the
code stream.
Another one for pretty printing.
For example, you will analyze the
parse tree and you will send some
errors or you will provide some
hints to the syntax highlighting
if there is an error or something
like that, or to provide some specific
colors to variables or things like that.
You could have a lot of different
operations on parse trees.
And then, another example,
this is rendering documents.
This is what we saw with the pillar
example.
So here you have different exporters.
You have a ‘Document‘ model,
and then you want to export this
‘Document‘ to a specific format.
This could be HTML, LaTeX,
or whatever.
The specific challenge of the ‘Visitor‘
design pattern is when the elements
of the composite change.
It requires changing all the Visitors
and implementing some more
accept methods and more visit methods.
When you have more dynamicity in
the composite, this is difficult
for the ‘Visitor‘.
This is related to the expression
problem in statically typed languages.
In conclusion, what we saw,
this is a ‘Visitor‘ design pattern,
we saw that it is a very,
very nice design pattern from the
extensibility point of view and
the modularity point of view.
You can remodularize some operations
in specific packages outside of
the domain, and it is based on the
double dispatch that makes it
plug-and-play.
It means that you will instrument
your domain object only one time
and it will work for all ‘Visitors‘.
On the con side, it can look complex.
So it means that this is a design
pattern that in a first understanding
is a little bit complex because
of this tricky interaction between
accept and visit methods.
And it's not well adapted to changing
structures, this is what we say
at the end.
If we change completely the nodes,
you need to re-implement a lot of
things in the ‘Visitors‘.