- Hello, everybody.
In this lecture, I want to give
you a starter on Double Dispatch.
Double Dispatch is important because
it's not really a Design Pattern,
this is a kind of coding idiom that
will let you remove conditionals
when you want and produce a more
modular design.
And this is the basis for the visitor
Design Pattern.
So, this is quite interesting and
important.
For that, we will look at the Stone
Paper Scissors exercise and how
we model it.
The goal of this example is to exercise
dispatch.
We will not use conditionals because
we don't like conditionals.
I guess that you understood now
in the lecture that we don't like
conditionals, and we will implement
the following exercise.
Here, we created a Stone and we said,
"We want to play the Stone against
the Paper, and this is the Paper
that wins".
Everybody knows Stone,
Paper, Scissors, so I don't have
to explain the game.
Basically, you know that Paper wins
against Rock or Stone,
that Rock wins against Scissors,
and that Scissors wins against Paper.
In fact, this is very symmetrical
from that perspective.
We also love tests, so let's write
a test.
Basically, I just turned the previous
expression into a test.
I set `self assert`…
so nothing new.
But I like to say that you should
write tests because people don't
write enough tests.
The inverse is true too.
This is a symmetrical case of Double
Dispatch.
We will have another lecture where
we will show that Double Dispatch
does not have to be symmetrical.
Here, I said `Paper new vs:
Stone new`.
It should still return that this
is the paper that won.
Basically, we have one class,
Stone, and you will implement the
`vs:` method.
What is very important in this exercise
is that you take the time,
pause the video, and try to fill
up the dots.
And by the way, from that perspective,
once I was giving a lecture and
one of the teaching assistants told
me the following: "Yes,
I understood really well but I realized
that when I did for real the exercise,
I understood much better".
So, there is a value in doing,
basically.
I will give you some hints.
The first one is that this solution
does not contain an explicit condition.
So sorry, no if today.
But there is a cool hint inside.
Sending a message is making a choice.
If you remember the first lecture
of this MOOC, on note implementation
and why this is interesting,
then the message was:
sending a message is making a choice.
In fact, it will select the correct
method.
If you remember this lecture,
we said, "Okay, then we need multiple
classes".
So, what are the classes that we
need here?
This is the second hint.
I give you three classes:
`Stone`, `Paper`, and `Scissors`.
How do you implement the `vs:` methods
without condition, of course?
I will give you more hints.
This one may look a bit stupid or
obvious, but it is really important,
and we will take advantage of it
to see the solution.
So, the first thing to realize is
that when we execute the method `vs:`,
when we have `Stone new vs:
Paper new`, we know the receiver
of the message.
This is `aStone`.
What we don't know is what the argument
is.
We would like to know what the argument
is because if this is Paper,
this is Paper that will win,
or if this is Scissors,
that is Scissors that will win.
But what is nice is that we have
already half of the solution because
we know the first one.
So, the idea there, the hint is,
"Ah!
If sending a message is making a choice,
then I just have to send another
message.
Like that, it will select the correct
one." The idea here is we know that
we are playing against Stone,
so why don't we introduce a method
that is called `playAgainstStone`?
This method will make another choice
for us, so we will implement that.
Let's look at it.
I have my method `vs:` and what
I know when I write this method
is that the receiver is Stone.
This is what I'm saying.
I'm saying, "Okay, I know Stone,
and I don't know what this element
is" because it could be Scissors,
it could be Stone, or it could be Paper.
I will just send a message to this
object by saying, "Yes,
I know, I play against Stone and
the system will work for me".
So, let's see.
In our case, we've got `aStone vs:
aPaper`.
This means that usually,
for the moment, I would just focus
on the Paper side.
Now the question is: if I tell you,
"You are `aPaper` and you receive
`playAgainstStone`, what should
you return?" You should say,
"That's easy, this is Paper because
I know if `aPaper` plays against
`aStone`, this is Paper." So,
you return it and this is what we do.
Here, first I will send the message
`playAgainstStone` to `anElement`.
And after, I will define
`playAgainstStone`, for example
in `#paper` for the moment.
With these two methods,
I know that if I write `aStone vs:
aPaper`, I get `#paper`,
which is cool.
I have the right solution without
any test.
Now, of course, this is what I'm
saying here, it works for Paper,
but it does not work for Scissors.
So, how do we fix that?
It is easy, let's do the same.
We will define - you know how to
do it - probably a new method in
the class Scissors.
So, let's look at that.
Imagine conceptually,
we said Stone plays against Scissors.
So, we will say `aScissor
playAgainstStone`.
I have to write in the class Scissors
the method `playAgainstStone`.
Now we know that if I play Scissors
against Stone, who is winning?
The Stone.
So, I write `#stone`.
And now what is left?
This is Stone because if I said
`aStone vs: aStone`, then I should
return `#draw` because this means
that there is equality,
and I cannot conclude.
This means that we now already have
a good part of the solution.
I will show you all the code.
We have all this code.
I have the method `vs:`,
I have the method `playAgainstStone`,
and I have the method `playAgainstStone`
in three different classes.
I can get the solution for all the
games where the receiver is Stone.
So, this means that if I have `aStone
vs: A Scissors`, `aStone vs:
aPaper`, or `aStone vs:
aStone`, I know the answer because
what will happen is that I send
this message to this guy,
and depending on the class of this guy,
I will either go there,
or there, or there.
Now the point is, how do we generalize
that?
We will do the same for each of
the elements.
So, let's step back from what we saw.
If we look at it, when we were executing
the method `vs:`, we know that this
method is executed on the Stone
class and the system selected this
method.
And then, basically, what we are
doing is that we just send another
message to the argument,
to select another method.
Here it will be one of the methods
that are called `playAgainstStone`.
This means that, as a conclusion,
with two messages, I can select
a method based on its receiver and
its argument.
This is powerful from that perspective,
and this is something that we will
use in the future for the Visitor
Design Pattern.
For Scissors, what I will do is
I will create a `vs:` method that
will say `playAgainstScissors`.
Scissors against Scissors,
that will be `#draw`.
`playAgainstScissors` in Paper,
this is `#scissors` that wins.
And `playAgainst Scissors` in Stone,
this is `#stone` that wins.
So, with this code here,
now I can manage all the cases where
I have `aScissors vs:
aPaper vs: a Stone and vs:
aScissors`.
This one will return `#draw`,
this one will return `#stone`,
and this one will return `#scissors`.
In the same way, we will do the
same for Paper.
For Paper in the class Paper,
this class has its own `vs:` methods
and we know that the receiver is
Paper so we will send the message
`playAgainstPaper` to the element,
and each of the classes - Scissors,
Paper, and Stone - will implement
the `playAgainstPaper` differently.
So, `Scissors >> playAgainstPaper`,
this is `#scissors` that wins.
Paper against Paper, this is a `#draw`,
and Paper against Stone,
this is `#paper` that wins.
So, if we look at the design,
in the end, we have that.
We have a method that is abstract
- these methods are basically abstract
- and each class implements a different
`vs:` method and a different
`playAgainstStone`,
`playAgainstScissors`,
`playAgainstScissors`.
Here, you have basically a Double
Dispatch in the sense that if we
look at `aPaper vs: aScissors`,
what will happen?
Which method `vs:` will be executed?
Oh, that's easy!
The receiver is `aPaper`,
so this is an instance of that class.
We will look for the method `vs:`
- you remember the lookup methods
lecture - so that will be this one,
and this one is implemented as
`playAgainst`.
So, that will be the argument
`playAgainstPaper`.
This argument can be an instance
of Stone, Paper, or Scissors,
so it means that it will select.
Again, there will be a lookup on
the argument that will select this one,
this one, or that one.
So, basically, if we look,
we have two kinds of messages.
We have the `vs:`, where we have
three methods, and then we have
one message `playAgainstPaper`,
one message `playAgainstStone`,
and one `playAgainstScissors`.
First, the system will select the
correct `vs:` method,
and then it will select the second
method based on the argument of
this method.
That's why we said that there is
a double dispatch.
First, we dispatch here,
and second, we dispatch on this one,
or this one, or this one.
This is a toy example because this
is a little game.
We don't need to pass an argument
during the dispatch.
When we look at a Visitor Design
Pattern, we will pass the argument.
What it means is that for the moment
we said `playAgainstPaper`,
we don't need the argument.
But usually, when we do a real Double
Dispatch, we pass the argument.
Here, we pass `aScissors`.
We didn't add this argument because
we don't use it in the method body here,
so there is no need to pass it as
an argument.
In the Visitor Design Pattern,
we will need that.
So, this means that the only difference
is that `vs:` typically in Paper
will mean, "Pass self,
which is the object receiving the
message, so that we can do something
here".
And the difference is that here
we have the argument,
while in the previous one,
if you look here, we don't have
the argument.
Now what I suggest you do is you
should extend this exercise with
Spock and Lizzard.
This is in the Big Bang Theory;
the guys invented a more complex
version of Rock, Paper,
Scissors.
What you see is that Spock wins
against Scissors and Rock,
and Lizzard against Paper and Spock.
So again, this is completely
symmetrical, and we suggest you
do that as an exercise to implement
the Stone, Paper, Scissors,
and to extend it.
What you will see is that in the
extension, you will never get any
conditionals.
With the same principle,
you will have `playAgainstSpock`,
`playAgainstLizzard`,
and implement them in the different
classes.
You will not have to change any
lines of code from the previous
implementation.
This means that from that perspective,
this is modular.
As a conclusion, a Double Dispatch
is not a Design Pattern per se,
but this is a powerful mechanism.
It is modular.
You just send an extra message to
the argument, and we use the late
binding.
What you should see is that Double
Dispatch is as if we would have
used the first lecture twice.
This means that in the first lecture,
we noted, we said, "Okay,
sending a message is making a choice".
Here, we send two messages,
and we make two choices.
This is the natural generalization
of the first lecture.