- Hello, everybody.
I just want to come back in this
lecture to the previous lecture
on Stone Paper Scissors,
and I would like to discuss a bit
the case of the results.
You will see this is a very small
lecture, but it can help you in
some situations.
This is to think a bit about results.
What are the results at the end
of the day, and what do we do with them?
If you remember, in the previous
lecture, we took a Stone,
we were fighting a Stone against a Paper,
and it returned Paper.
We had this kind of design,
where we had one abstract class,
we were using Double Dispatch,
and each class defined a `vs:` method,
and they all defined different methods
to handle the case.
It was working well, and it was fun.
This is the context.
Now the question was for me,
what should be the result of `vs:`?
So, when I do `Paper new vs:
Stone new`, what is the result?
We said, "Oh, yes, we return paper".
Why not?
But what else?
Could we return something else?
And what are the consequences of
those choices?
We could return numbers.
We could have said, "Oh,
easy!
I will return minus 1 when it fails,
and 0 when there is a draw,
and 1 when there is a success.
Like that, it's easier to sum up." Well,
except that it is not good because
I should also return minus 1 when
Paper is the argument.
So, what does it mean to be minus 1?
In fact, if I do `Paper new vs:
Stone`, it should return the same
number because it's the same case.
So, we decided to return symbols
because, like that, in the slide,
you could really follow the lecture.
But what does it mean?
It means that if I want to do something
with the result of the computation,
then I have to do something like that:
`aPlayer vs: anotherPlay = #draw`.
`IfTrue`, then I will do something.
This means that everywhere we are
using `vs:`, we have somehow to
interpret this.
Imagine that you want to count how
many times the guy is winning,
we will have to count another counter.
And then we were thinking,
"Okay, maybe we could do something else.
We could also have an API where
we will pass Rocks." We said,
"Okay, when I do the battle,
I will say `onDraw` and you should
increment `Draw` on `Receiver`.
The game should increment the receiver
and things like that.
You know, we could implement it
like that.
We could say, "Okay, this is easy,
we can do a value here and things
like that on `playAgainstStone`".
On `playAgainstStone`,
for example, we said,
"Okay, this is Paper that plays
against Stone, so the winner will
do something", except that it does
not look nice because you don't
want to have four arguments like that.
This is not satisfactory either
from that perspective.
I'm not fond of this solution and
I'm not fond of the other solution
either.
In fact, I'm not fond of any solution
from that perspective.
But what we could also do is we
could say, "Maybe we should have
a result handler".
This is an object that will know
how to do things.
I prefer this solution.
So here, I could say,
"`Paper new vs: Paper new` and I
give you `aResultHandler`.
This is a guy who knows how to do
something and in the `Paper >>
playAgainstStone`, for example,
I know that the Paper is winning
so I would say, "A result!
Please configure yourself so that
you know that the Paper has won".
To me, this solution feels more
like a "Do not ask, tell".
I'm saying to the result handler,
"Please do something".
Like that, I'm not forced to ask
myself what I should do and things
like that.
And from that perspective,
we could have different result handlers.
We could have one that just accumulates
results and others that do statistics
or things like that.
So, what I suggest is to implement
the Stone Paper Scissors and play
with those kinds of things.
Try to educate your test on design
and see what the possibilities are.
Now, what I learned during this
exercise is that we should also
often focus on the client.
So, this means that we design something,
but we should not design it in the air.
We should design it because we have
a scenario and that we have a user.
And the way the user uses us will
have an impact on the design.
In general, you don't have a design
that will solve all the solutions.
You have one design that solves
a given interaction with a client
of your program and maybe you will
have another client and then you
will have to adapt your design to
this new client.
And this is what I learned while
doing this exercise.
So, I really encourage you to do that.
If we step back, from my perspective,
Symbols look better than returning
numbers.
But there are some other cases where
numbers can be better.
So, creating result handlers can
be heavy, but this can be interesting.
What is interesting is that the
context and the scenario should
tell you where you want to invest
and what is worth from the
reuse perspective.
In general, you should not also
do just good design for good design,
but good design for a reason.