- Hello everybody, welcome to this
lecture on Double Dispatch.
This is an alternate lecture from
the other one where we will really
add numbers as a Kata,
as an exercise.
The outline is that we will see
some fun exercises that you should do,
think about them, and then step
back to see what we learned.
The idea is that you will do exercises
and I will do exercises with you,
where you get access to three
primitives: `addi` to add two integers,
`addf` to add two floats,
and `asFloat` that converts one
integer into a float.
With that, we will build an addition
between numbers.
Basically, the goal of the first
part of the lecture is to support
the addition with the same `+` message
with the numbers 1 + 2,
the integers 1 + 2, the float 1.1 + 2,
adding an integer plus a float,
and two floats.
The idea is that we will not use
any explicit conditionals.
Let me give you first some hints.
You saw in the first lecture that
sending a message is making a choice
and that classes support choice
expressions.
Basically, it means that we will
have two classes: `Integer` and `Float`.
Nothing is new here, so we will
have these two.
And by the way, in the second part
of the lecture, we will add fractions,
so we will have integers,
floats, and fractions.
It means that if we have two classes,
then we will have at least two methods
`+` and we will have a third one
in Fractions in the future.
What I will do during this lecture
is that you will have to fill up
some text.
What I suggest is that you try to
do it and you just look at the video.
You can pause when I have a "fill
me up :)".
This means that you can pause,
take a pen at home, and try to fill
it up.
This means that you have two classes,
`Float` and `Integer`,
with two methods `+`,
`+ aNumber`.
It means that the exercise is to
fill up these two methods.
Another hint that is a bit obvious,
but this is very interesting to see,
is that when I execute a method,
I know that the receiver of the
method is an instance of the class
or a subclass of that class.
So, this means that I have already
some information and we will use
this information as part of the
solution.
Now let's start.
Imagine that we add one method that
is called `sumWithInteger:`.
With the primitive, we know how
to do it because we know how to
add two integers together.
This means that in the class `Integer`,
`sumWithInteger:` should be
straightforward.
Let's look at it.
So, `sumWithInteger:` in the class
`Integer`, when I have an argument
that is `anInteger`, I will just
call the primitive `addi` with `self``
and the argument and I'm done.
Here, there is a strong assumption
that the argument `anInteger` is
an instance of the class `Integer`.
Now the point is that we know that
we have `sumWithInteger:` here,
so the question is, how do we use
this `sumWithInteger:` from the
other one?
Our idea here is that we are basically
working on that.
So, it should work.
Now we should be able to have a
solution for `1 + 2`,
where 1 and 2 are integers.
So, imagine the solution.
Let's see the solution.
Here, what I do is that when I do
`1 + 2`, this means that this method
will be executed, `aNumber` will be 2,
and then I just send `sumWithInteger:`
to `aNumber`.
I don't know if normally that is
`aNumber`, but at least in that
typical scenario, I assume that
this is correct.
Since this is an integer,
this method will be executed.
I ended up with the correct result.
Just to explain, let's take this
code and we will make sure that
we understand where the arguments
are going inside.
Here, we are looking at the execution
on `1 + 2`.
So, 1 is an integer, so `+` will
be on the `Integer` class,
so this is this method.
And you see here, I took the code
and put it in parentheses,
or I replaced the text with the
actual argument.
Here I said `1 + 2`.
This is this call, `1 + 2`,
and then I will do `2 sumWithInteger:
1`.
What is super important is to see
that we switched it and it means
that now I'm looking for
`sumWithInteger:` in the class
`Integer`.
This is this one.
I'm calling `2 sumWithInteger:
1` and I end up doing this.
By the way, this trick of looking
out the argument, the receiver,
and the argument of the message
flow within the text is a very nice
way to understand the ping-pong
that is actually happening during
the Double Dispatch.
I saw that this is really helping
people to understand the Double
Dispatch.
Now the question is: what about
2 + a Float?
Because when I do that,
if this is a Float, I will have 2 here,
`aNumber` will be a Float,
and I have 1.2 with 2.
And the system said, "I don't know
what is `sumWithInteger:` when I'm
a Float".
So, you know what?
We should define `sumWithInteger:`
on `Float`.
Let's do it!
What is `` sumWithInteger:` on `Float`?
Take a moment; normally with the
primitives, we know how to do it.
So, `sumWithInteger:` with `Float`,
this is basically calling add Float,
`addf` with `self, asFloat`,
and converting the integer as a Float,
and we have it.
Now we have the solution,
so this means that when I send a
message `+` to 2, I will select
this method and 1.2 will be here
because 1.2 is here, and then I
will call `sumWithInteger:`, but
on the class `Float`.
So, I will call this one here and
then I convert so I'm done.
Again, I just did the same,
you can press, and you can follow.
I did the same.
I see, okay, yes, it goes like that.
This guy is here, and it goes like that.
So, now I call this guy here and
it happens.
Again, what you see, and this is
really important, is that I send
a new message to the argument.
What do we do when we add two Floats?
Because before we only had `Integer`
and now we have `Float`.
This means that we have to define
`+` on `Integer`.
How do we define `+` on `Integer`?
Take a moment to think about it.
Basically, what we should do is
we should define a new method like that.
We should say `aNumber sumWithFloat:`.
Why?
Because we don't know if 'aNumber'
is an `Integer` or a `Float`.
So, since we don't know,
we define `+` with this method.
The impact is that we will have
to define `sumWithFloat:` on the
class `Integer` and the class `Float`.
Now, you see, I added `sumWithFloat:`
on two classes: the class `Integer`
and the class `Float`.
So, `sumWithFloat:` on the class
`Float` is easy because I used the
same primitive, `addf` with `self`
and `aFloat` because this is a Float.
And here, `sumWithFloat:` on the
class `Integer`, what do I do?
I have `aFloat` as an argument,
so I convert the argument `asFloat`
and I add it.
And what you see is that with this
piece of code, we can add `aFloat
+ aNumber` and `aNumber + aFloat`.
You can also do the same exercise.
What I suggest is that I will not
go into the details, but you see
that if I have the `+` here,
I have a Float, so the Float means
that I will execute this one,
and then I will execute `sumWithFloat:`,
which is this one, and then
`sumWithFloat:`.
You can follow each time the flow
of messages.
So, what you see is that the previous
code supported all that.
If you do not get it fully,
what I suggest you do,
and it works really well,
is to do exactly the exercise of
following the argument on the text,
on the code.
Basically, you take this,
you take cases, and you select where
the methods are going,
and which method is executed;
it works really well.
Let's step back.
We see that we have two things.
We have two kinds of messages.
We have the message `+` defined
on two classes, `Integer` and `Float`.
And we have `sumWithInteger:` or
`sumWithFloat:` that are defined
on two classes, `Integer` and `Float`.
The fact that I am sending this message,
I am doing a second dispatch.
I have a first dispatch between
the two implementations here,
and I have a second dispatch between
the two implementations here.
So, this means that `+` will select
the correct one and once we send
the message `sumWithInteger:` or
`sumWithFloat:`, we will also select
the correct methods of each of those
methods.
Now, let's say that we want to add
fractions.
A fraction is an object with a numerator
and denominator, like in maths,
nothing special.
This is a fraction.
We know how to compute `asFloat`
getting the denominator and getting
the numerator.
And now we want to support this.
I want to add a fraction plus an
integer.
I want to add a float with a fraction
or fractions together.
How do we do that?
First things first.
We have a Fraction class and then
we define a `+` method on this Fraction
class.
You see, it follows the same pattern.
What should we do?
Take a moment, you will see that
we should probably add something
like that: `sumWithFraction`.
This is what we did for the previous
one.
Let's check.
Yes, this is correct.
Now it means that we will have to
define `sumWithFraction` in the
class `Fraction`, the class `Integer`,
and the class `Float`.
Let's start with the class `Fraction`.
A fraction in a fraction,
you know the maths, this is that
kind of thing.
Let's do it.
You see, this is a bit verbose because
I send messages, but I create a
fraction with a numerator and a
denominator, and this is done.
Now it means that this code supports
this because when I send the message
`+`, I will select the `+` in the
class Fraction, this one,
and then I will use `sumWithFraction.`
This is a fraction, so I will create
these kinds of things.
With these two methods,
I already support fraction addition,
but I want more.
I want fractions plus integers and
fractions plus floats.
Let's do it!
Now, we will define these two methods
in the two different classes.
This is exactly this definition.
For this one, we have a float added
to a fraction, so we have 0.3 +
a fraction, 2/3.
We will convert this one as a float
and we will add it.
Here, this is what we do,
we said: let's convert the fraction
as a float and `self` is a float,
and then we invoke the primitive
`add float` that will take these
two and do the addition.
This means that if we see,
now we'll manage to support well
a fraction plus fraction,
a fraction plus a float,
and a fraction plus an integer.
But we have still some things to fix.
What about 1 + a fraction?
This means that I have an integer.
Here, when I send the message `+`,
I will look in the class `Integer`.
I will look for this `+`.
What you see is that the definition
of `+` was the following.
It said, "Okay, I have a number
and I will send `sumWithInteger:`
to this number, here a fraction".
What do we have to do?
We have to define the method
`sumWithInteger:` inside the Fraction
class.
So, let's do that.
Basically, here we end up with the
same kind of code because we will
have a fraction with an integer.
So, a fraction plus an integer,
we will do…
And this is what this code is doing.
I create a new function where I
sum and multiply the denum,
etc.
This means that with this definition,
now we support the addition of an
integer with a fraction.
Basically, we should do exactly
the same for this case because the
receiver can be a float.
So, when the receiver is a float,
what should we do?
We should define the method
`sumWithFloat:` in the class Fraction.
What I suggest is that you do it
because I know how to do it and
this is always the same.
Now I just want to show you the
complete code.
Here, this is the complete code
for the integration and the definition
of the management of fractions.
So, you have three methods in the
class Fraction, one method in Integer,
and one method in Float,
plus the `+` to support the integration
of additions that can manage Float,
Fraction, and Integer.
Now you can relax.
If you really want to understand
for real or if you need it,
just take a pen and follow the calls.
The code in the previous slide manages
all those cases.
So, this is quite nice.
And even more than that,
it will manage 1.5 + 0.5,
for example, without problems.
So, let's step back.
What we saw is that the essence
of Double Dispatch is in this code.
You have a class X, you have your
message +, and then an argument.
And then, what we do is that we
send a new message to the argument.
This means that the system selects
first the message based…
if you have an X, it will select
this one, and we will have a Y that
will have plus a something,
and then we will do the same:
a something `sumWithY:self`.
So, the first time when we send a message
to 'aX', it will select this one.
If we have 'aY' + something,
we will select this one,
and then we will have the other
messages that are the helper message
where we will do the second dispatch.
In fact, we have one dispatch and
a second dispatch.
That's why this is called Double
Dispatch.
What you see is that we could add
`Fraction` without changing any
of the previous methods.
This is quite cool because this
means that we could add a complex
number or something else to the story.
This is an illustration of sending
a message is making a choice,
and this is based on the idea that
you have a primary message and double
dispatching messages.
What you should notice also is that
sometimes people do triple dispatch,
typically for the graphics library,
because they have a canvas,
Cairo or Metal for example,
and they will select the pen - is
it a line like that?
- and the texture inside the brush.
They don't want to do checks,
so they can do a triple dispatch
to do these kinds of things.
What you should see is that Double
Dispatch is really the essence of
the Visitor Design Pattern.
Then, we will use it to do the ping
pong between composite patterns
and some algorithms that will be
applied to those composite structures.
Again, the Double Dispatch is a
clear illustration of the "Don't ask,
Tell" principle.
And it is often used for events
and drawings and things like that.
Now, one question is when not to
use Double Dispatch.
In fact, first, the simple one is
that if you don't have a different
class to dispatch on,
then you cannot use it.
This is not that you can,
this is that you cannot.
Basically, you need a different
instance of a different class to
be able to dispatch, to execute
a different method.
Second, what I would say is that
if you have a limited case with
two or three methods that you have
to check and you know that it will
never change, maybe you don't have
to bother to introduce Double Dispatch.
What are the drawbacks of Double
Dispatch?
Overusing it may force to create
a lot of many little classes.
It can lead to a design that is
a bit more obscure and difficult
to follow.
Sometimes, a simple condition can
be good too.
We should not be ultimate on that.
Design is about tradeoffs.
And then, you have to decide.
Now, for you to decide,
you should really understand how
it works and practice it so that
you can say, "No, I don't want to
use it" or "I want to use it".
Now, I would like to talk about
overloading because Double Dispatch
is also useful in statically typed
languages such as Java.
Sometimes, people don't understand
it and they get into trouble.
What I mean is that the typical
case of a Visitor Design Pattern
where you will use only one visit
method that uses the overloading
of the language will work sometimes
and sometimes won't work because
the static typing will select the
wrong methods.
So, if you use overloading for visitors,
you will learn it the hard way.
And I think that in any case,
this is good because you will learn it.
But what I know is that I will not
use overloading to support Double
Dispatch because it does not work
in real cases.
In conclusion, what you saw is that
Double Dispatch is powerful.
We could implement all this conversion
between this addition without any
conditional.
This is modular.
We could add the fraction without
changing any methods.
At the end of the day,
what we did was just send an extra
message to the argument and we'll
use late binding so that the correct
method is executed.
So, in the end, this is super simple.
Now what you should pay attention
to is that if you use Double Dispatch,
you can make the program execution
a bit difficult to follow for people
when they are debugging or things
like that, because suddenly another
object can receive a message and
you are not expecting it or things
like that.
At runtime, it's happened,
but when you read the code,
especially typically when you have
a dynamically typed language,
this may not be obvious.
You should pay attention that this
is potentially a drawback of the
solution.