Guillermo Polito - Hi.
In this lecture, we're going to
discuss again double dispatch,
in the case of non-symmetrical use
of double dispatch. So we're going
to look at double dispatch again,
but we're going to see that it doesn't
have to be symmetrical as we have
seen in previous examples.
So remember, in the previous lectures,
we have seen the paper,
scissor, stone example where we
could make stone versus paper or
paper versus scissors and so it's
a paper scissors rock game.
And then, the result was the one
that win.
Yeah.
Now the problem with this is that
it could lead you to the confusion
that always having a double dispatch
requires to have a symmetrical
implementation.
So here actually, in stone we had
to implement the versus scissors
versus stone and versus paper.
We had to do actually the same in
the paper, for example.
So we had to implement each of the
versus methods in each of the classes.
So that is not actually always the case.
To put you in context,
let's imagine a game model of a Sokoban.
Sokoban is a game where we have
a little person that is going to
push boxes in a maze and the objective
of the game is to put each box on
top of each of these dots.
Yeah, so in our model,
we have boxes we have boxes that
are above the target,
so like this one.
We have empty blocks,
which represent the empty square
where we are going to be able to walk.
We have a player, we have walls
that we can't trespass.
Let's imagine an implementation
that actually is implemented with
too many ifs.
What is happening here is that here
we have a block here.
This block is a block in the game
So here for example, this could be a box,
it could be a player,
it could be a wall.
And then, here what we're doing
is to try to draw it,
So to implement that,
what is happening here is that we
are taking the block and we are
asking are you a wall,
then I will draw a wall,
are you a player, then I'm going
to draw a player and so on.
If we wanted to implement this using
double dispatch, one of the way
to implement it is to directly delegate
to the block object.
So instead of asking the block what
it is and then deciding how to draw it,
what we can say is "okay block,
you know who you are.
So draw yourself on this canvas
and I am the view".
Then each kind of block for example
the wall or the empty blocks,
they can tell the view,
okay, draw a wall or draw an empty
block in this canvas.
So here what is happening is that
to be able to draw something,
we are doing a double dispatch.
The decision to draw,
it is shared between the game view
that knows how to draw different
elements like drawing a wall or
drawing an empty block and the block
itself that actually knows how to
dispatch to the view.
What this solution help us to do
is to for example, change and have
different kind of canvases and views
to be able to draw.
So we are doing double dispatch
between the different kind of blocks.
So we have the block hierarchy,
block 1, block two, block three.
And then, we are going to have canvases
or views and we are going to be
able to have different kind of canvases
to draw differently for.
So for example, here we could have
an HTML view that will draw in one
way and we could have for example
a vectorized or a 3D canvas that
will draw it in a different way.
So what is happening here is that
we're telling the view how to draw
an element and before that we are
telling the block that it has to
draw itself because the only one
that knows how to draw itself,
what kind of element it is is the
element itself.
So we are telling the element draw
yourself and then the element will
tell the canvas or the view oh,
I am a block, draw myself.
So in this way we can have a really
a modular system where we can change
the canvases, add new kind of blocks
without rewriting the entire system.
So that is why sending messages
is a powerful tool.
What happened here is that what
I told you: actually the double dispatch
doesn't need to be symmetrical.
What happens is that you need to
look at the double dispatch like
a matrix.
So in this case, for example,
we have all the different kind of
blocks.
We have walls, we have empty blocks,
we have players and then we have
all the different canvases;
canvas one, HTML, 3D.
So in the previous case when we had rock,
paper, scissors, we had rock,
paper, scissors here and we have
also rock, paper, scissors in there.
That's why we had a symmetrical model.
But in this case, what we're crossing
is the different blocks and the
different canvases.
So in this case, our model and our
double dispatch is not symmetrical.
In conclusion, double dispatch is
a good way to add the variation
point without hardcoding all the
entire path of execution.
It is modular because we can add
new elements in the decision process
by adding for example in our case,
new canvases or new blocks.
And it can be symmetrical as in
the case of the rock,
paper, scissors or it can be
asymmetrical like in this case here.