Hello everybody, welcome to this
new lecture on double dispatch.
This is a complement to the previous
lecture on stone, paper,
scissors.
Here we will see how we can add
a `die` and `dieHandle`.
So the goal of the lecture,
this is to show how conditionals
can be turned into extensible design
using message and double dispatch.
This is typically the case for a
more complex situation with the
Visitor Pattern. So let's see.
In the previous MOOC,
we did not have the complete lecture.
In this MOOC,
we could have a `DieHandle` that
would contain `Die`.
So here, for example,
I have a `DieHandle` that contains
a `Die` with six faces and one with
ten faces.
And then we could say to the
`DieHandle`, OK, roll,
and it will return here a number
between 1 and 16.
So this was an exercise in the previous
MOOC.
It was fun.
We strongly suggest you have a look.
This is a six-minute video and then
there is an exercise,
so you should have a look.
Now the question is that in this
version, we could really write
expressions like that,
like in the Dungeon Dragon books,
where we could say, Oh,
you know, I have two dice of 20
faces plus three dice of 10 faces.
And the plus would create a handle.
And like that, what we could do
is that we could take the Dungeon
Dragon books and just write this
expression, put in parentheses and
write roll.
And then like that, we could just
play our games following what is
written in the book.
So that was what we did before.
And now in this lecture,
we will change the plus here because
before we were doing 2D.
So this means that this 2D was returning
a `dieHandle`.
And the plus was always between
`dieHandles`.
And you will see that we want to
have it between dice.
So, for example, we added new
requirements on the previous exercise.
So here we said, Oh, you know,
why do we limit ourselves plus only
with `dieHandle`?
Why can't we say that I have a `Die`
with six faces and I will add another
`Die` with six faces.
And this guy should return me
a `dieHandle` with two dice.
And then in that case,
I can send the message roll to this guy.
What you see is that here,
the plus suddenly is managing also dice.
And before, it was just `dieHandle`.
Then we added…
we can turn this requirement as a test.
And this is easy.
You know, this is the same.
And you said, OK, this means that
we will have a `dieHandle` that
has two dice.
Now the requirement two is that
why do we limit ourselves?
We want to be able to send the message
plus to a `dieHandle` with as argument
a `Die` or the inverse.
Why can't we just send the message
plus to a `Die` with a `dieHandle`
as argument?
And this is what we will do in this
lecture.
You see, we can turn also this new
requirement as a test.
We do it like that, like that.
We really strongly suggest that
you do the exercise during this MOOC.
And then you know if you succeed
or not when your tests are passing.
So the possible solution,
this is with conditions.
Here, what I am doing is that I'm
creating on the `Die` class a message
plus with an element,
an argument that is either a `Die`
or a `DieHandle`.
And then what do I do?
I just create a new `DieHandle`
and I add the receiver.
And then after, I fall back on the
previous case.
So this means that before,
I knew that if I have a `DieHandle`
plus a `DieHandle`, I know that
it was returning a `DieHandle`.
So here, basically, this is what
I am doing.
I said, You know, I try two
`DieHandle`, except that it does
not work.
Because if I specify a `Die`,
I didn't convert it.
So it could nearly work,
but it was not the case.
So what I have to do,
in fact, here, I wrote it the
traditional way.
You know, I said, OK,
so on `DieHandle`, when I have a plus,
I will check that my argument is
a `DieHandle`.
If this is the case, I create a handle.
I go over all the dice.
I add them to this new handle.
And then now I know that my argument
is a `DieHandle`.
So I can get dice and then add them
to the handle.
And I do the same in the other branch.
This is not really nice,
but this is what we can do.
It works for two cases,
but it does not really scale.
So, of course, in our little toy
example, we have only `Die` and
`DieHandle`.
In reality, when we will work with
documents, for example,
or with trees that represent programs,
we have 35 nodes and not two.
So this means that you see the size
of the condition that can be really
intractable.
Or it can be, but it leads to designs
that are really brittle.
So typically in Pilar,
the system that is used to create
the slides that you are watching,
we have list, figure,
paragraph, section, title,
text, reference, two kinds of lists,
(code block)…
We don't have a plus,
just a plus.
We have rendering text,
generating HTML, generating LaTeX
and so on.
So this means that for each of those
guys, we have to repeat this.
We would have to repeat this condition
for something like 35 different nodes.
And when you do analysis of languages,
for example, what you should notice
is that in Java, you have around
70 nodes in C++, 180.
So it does not really scale.
That's why the Visitor Pattern is
working well.
And this is based on what you will
be learning in this lecture.
So now, the solution.
A good solution that we want to
show in this lecture is based on
the first lecture of this MOOC that
says that sending a message is making
a choice.
In fact, the system will select
the correct method given the receiver.
So this means that to select a method
based on the receiver and the argument,
because this is what we want to
have here.
Here, if we step back,
we want to have a `DieHandle` plus
a `Die` working.
We want to have a `Die` plus a
`DieHandle` that is working.
Or we want to have a `DieHandle`
plus a `DieHandle` or a `Die` plus
a `Die`.
All these solutions should work.
So this means that basically,
conceptually, this is like if we
would have different versions of
plus that are based on the different…
the receiver and the argument,
the configuration, you see.
So double dispatch is made to really
select the correct methods based
on the receiver and the argument.
So the sketch of the solution.
In fact, when we want to add two
elements, a `Die` or `DieHandle`,
we will tell the argument to add
itself to the receiver.
Because the receiver,
we know who it is.
What we don't know, this is the
argument.
So basically, we just have to send
a message to the argument.
And the argument will have to have
multiple methods to handle this case.
And this is a bit the same like
what we did in the stone paper scissors.
Here we said, OK, when the receiver
is a `Die`, it will tell the argument
to add itself to a `Die`.
When the receiver is a `DieHandle`,
it will tell its argument to add
itself to a `DieHandle`.
Let's see how we do it.
It's a first try.
It will not really work,
but let's try.
So the first thing that we can do
to add the plus in the `Die` class.
This is we create a `DieHandle`.
We add self and we add a `Die`.
It does not work because this guy
can be a `DieHandle`.
But let's see.
Let's start like that.
So you see, this is what I said.
`aDie` here can be a dice or
`DieHandle`, like in this code.
Here the plus.
This is a `DieHandle`.
So it does not work.
But we can do better.
So now we can introduce `sumWithDie`,
with `aDie`.
We said, OK, let's make sure that
we know how to add a `Die` and a `Die`.
So to add a `Die` and a `Die`.
This is what we did before.
We just create a `DieHandle`.
We add the `Die` and we add the
parameters and its returns a
`DieHandle`.
So we are happy with this one.
And now what we can just say,
we can say, Oh, you know,
the plus, we revise it and we said,
OK, we send to the argument the
message `sumWithDie`.
Passing self as argument because we know,
because we are in a `Die` class,
so self is a `Die`.
What we don't know, this is what
is this guy.
So this guy can be either `aDie`
or `aDieHandle`.
So we just send this message.
And now this case, for example,
let's look at it graphically.
This case is working for only one case.
This one.
We have `aDie` plus `aDie`.
So we send the message here plus
we know that this guy is 10,
for example, and this one will be six.
So we know it.
And then it means that it will execute
because we will send `sumWithDie`
to `aDie`.
So we look inside the class `die`.
OK, we have `sumWithDie`.
This is this one.
So this is OK.
It works.
So now the key question,
this is how can we make it work
so that we have `aDie` plus
`aDieHandle`?
Because with that case here,
it will not work because it will
send the message `sumWithDie` to
that guy.
So, in fact, what we should do is
that we should implement these methods.
To support this message,
when the argument is not `aDie`
but `aDieHandle`, what do we do?
We define `sumWithDie` in a`DieHandle`.
So now this is clear.
We know that we have as argument `aDie`.
So we create `aDie` handle.
We will copy all the dice of the
receiver inside this new handle.
And then at the end, we just add
`aDie` to the new handle because
this is done and we know that this
is this one.
So we are done.
So let's look at it now.
Graphically.
So imagine I have `aDie` here and
I have `aDieHandle`.
I send the message plus.
Now it starts to be interesting.
So I send the message plus.
This is `aDie`.
So I looked for the method in this
class.
OK, I have the message plus.
So this is this method that is executed.
So self.
This is `aDie` six.
This is this guy.
So I send the message sum to an
instance of `DieHandle`.
So I will look for this method.
Basically, this is this method here
that will be executed.
And I do the correct things and
I return it.
So you see, so it worked well when
I have `aDie` as receiver,
and as argument, I can have `aDie`
or `aDieHandle`.
So what we see is that we have two
kinds of messages.
We have the plus that is selecting
first a class and then `sumWithDie`
that is selecting the message that
will be executed on the argument.
OK, now we want our solution to
also accept receiver as `dieHandle`.
What should we do?
We will do the same for `dieHandle`.
In fact, this is just the repetition
on another case.
So what we will do is that we define
the method plus on the class
`DieHandle`.
And now we know we will set
`sumWithHandle` because we are in
the class handle and we specify self.
In fact, we do exactly the same
as what we did on the `Die` class,
but we do it on the `DieHandle` class.
And then we will have the support for…
We will define this method on two
classes, one for `Die` and one for
`DieHandle`.
And like that, we will be able to
handle all the case.
We will be able in this particular
case to handle the sum of two
die handles or one die handle
and a die.
Let's look at it.
So on the class `DieHandle`,
to sum `aDieHandle`,
this is easy.
I create a new die handle.
I go over all the `die` that are
in the receiver.
I add them into this new die handle
and then I take the argument.
I take the dice of the argument
and I do the same and I return the
handle.
By the way, this is a functional
designer.
So this means that if you have
`aDieHandle` plus `aDieHandle`…
So if let's say this is 10,
10, 10, and here, this is 6 and 10.
When I do plus, I will return a
new `dieHandle` with 10,
6, 10, 10, 10.
So that's why I create this new
die handle.
Now on the class `Die`,
I will define the `sumWithHandle`.
And now I know that I have `aDieHandle`.
So I will create  a `DieHandle`.
I will sum  the die of
the die handle into
this new handle.
And I add self because I am on the
class `Die`.
So I just add a new die.
So now you have the complete solution.
Here we manage the four cases.
Let's play a bit with that.
If I have `aDieHandle` plus `aDie`,
what happens?
First, the plus will select in the
class `DieHandle`.
So this means that this is this
one that will be selected.
So I will execute first this case.
And the argument here is `aDie`.
So this means that I will have `aDie`
`sumWithHandle`.
So in that case, I will go here.
I will go here because I have aDicable.
So I don't know if this is `aDie`
or `aDieHandle`.
But in my case here, I know that
this is `aDie`.
So suddenly I go here and then I
execute this code.
Now let's do another one.
So imagine that you have `aDieHandle`
plus `aDieHandle`.
That's easy.
The plus is what?
This is this one.
We go here.
This argument aDicable is this guy.
So I will do `sumWithHandle` on
the `DieHandle` class.
So `sumWithHandle` on the `DieHandle`
class.
This is this one.
And we do that.
Now let's continue.
So imagine that we have `aDie`
plus `aDie`.
So if I have `aDie` plus `aDie`,
the plus is which one?
This is this one.
So it will select this one.
I will look.
So this is the method.
I know that `die`, this is the argument
here.
So that would be `SumWithdie` on `aDie`.
This is this method.
Now what do we have that is missing?
We have `aDie` plus `aDieHandle`.
OK.
So let's erase that.
So `aDie`, the plus is what?
This is sent to a `Die`.
So this will be this one again.
Now I know that this is `aDieHandle`.
So here I will have `aDieHandle`.
So I will send `sumWithDie` to
`aDieHandle`.
Sum to `aDieHandle`.
So the `sumWithDie`.
So this means I will jump here.
What you see is that we have a first
dispatch, the plus, that select,
this plus or this plus.
Then we have a second dispatch here
and there that will select this
version of `SumWithdie` or this
version of `sumWithHandle`.
Double dispatch.
So the two here and two here.
So what you see is that each time
you send a message plus,
the system selected the correct
methods on each class.
And then after internally sending
another message to the argument
was selecting the correct methods
in the different classes.
In fact, if we step back,
we apply two times the same principle.
We send a message and the system
selected the correct method for me.
So sending a message to an argument
was a way to select again between
different methods on different classes.
So as a conclusion, double dispatch,
sometimes it can be difficult to grasp.
You have to try to do it,
to follow what's happened,
do the exercise.
But this is really powerful.
Sometimes you don't want to use
too much because it can be confusing.
But you have certain cases like,
for example, compiler or things
like that or document or when you
have a composite structure,
you will see the composite pattern soon,
a composite structure
with a lot of nodes where you have
to do special treatment for each
of the nodes.
And you have to do different special
treatments.
Then you will see that this is really
a call for the design pattern.
And the Design Pattern Visitor,
it is based on this double dispatch.
And to understand really clearly
the Visitor Design Pattern,
you have to understand double dispatch.