Hello.
In this lecture, we'll discuss about
very nice and common design pattern,
which is a composite design pattern.
So the outline of this lecture will
be the following.
We will first start with some examples
that motivate the need for the Composite
design pattern, then we will present
it in detail and we will have some
discussions about it,
about its advantages and its cons.
So first, imagine that we want to
describe or to design a system in
which we have some file entries.
So a file entry could be either
a regular file, like there,
or a folder, like there.
And in a folder, you can put some
different file entries,
you can put also regular files or
folders.
So you have a recursive definition.
So it means that you have a tree
structure.
And the idea is how to model that
efficiently in an object-oriented
manner.
But we have other examples of this
kind of tree structures.
For example, we could have the
description of a document.
So a document is composed of a title,
a table of content, chapters.
A chapter is composed of sections,
and then some sections are composed
of paragraphs, figures,
lists, and subsections.
So it means that you have a recursion
there also, a section is composed
of sections, etc.
So how can we model that efficiently
in an object-oriented system?
And finally, a last example about
this kind of tree structure,
a Diagram is composed of elements,
and an element could be a Circle,
a Segment, a Text,
or a group of elements.
So it means a Diagram.
So now the question is how can we
draw Diagram elements and Diagram
in a uniform way from the client's
point of view?
Can we avoid testing in the client
side or check if we are trying to
draw elements or Diagrams?
This is the point.
And the answer is yes,
of course, we can.
So to avoid this, it means that
we need to have a common API between
the elements and the `Diagrams`.
And for example, here in this design,
so all elements, simple ones,
which are called leaves,
answer to the `draw` message there.
But composite elements,
here a `Diagram`, it's composed
of `Graphic`, and a `Graphic` could
be either a leaf or a `Diagram`.
So the recursion is in this link there.
Here, a `Diagram` is composed of
elements, and we can `add` and `remove`
elements, but it also understands
the `draw` message.
And this is the point.
So the intent of the composite design
pattern is the following.
We want to compose objects in a
tree structure to represent part-world
hierarchies.
And the idea is to let clients treat
individual objects and composition
objects uniformly, because they
will answer the same API.
And for example, if in my client
code I have an object called a`Graphic`,
I don't know if it is a composite
one or if it is a leaf.
But I can send the `draw` message,
the same message, and it will respond
accordingly, being a `Text`,
a `Circle` or a `Diagram`,
a group of elements.
So the essence of the composite
design pattern is the following.
This is a `drawing` that you can
find in books.
You have four different roles;
the client, the component,
a leaf, you may have multiple leaves,
and a Composite, and the recursion
is in the Composite class.
So the essence of this Composite
design pattern, what is key,
is that leaves and the Composite
offer the same API.
This is this uniformity that avoid
testing in the client's code,
which we want to do.
And then, each leaf does something
different.
It just needs to implement the same API,
but it's not mandatory to do the
same thing.
Each leaf can have a different
operation.
So the Composite element offers
the same API and plus some functionality
to manage the children.
So you can `add` and `remove` children
in the composition.
And of course, since they have the
same API, leaves and composite are
substitutable, clients do not have
to check.
So let's go back to the example
and let's analyze all the participants
in the design pattern to really
understand the point.
So first of all, we have the client,
and the client can manipulate all
objects in the composition through
the component interface.
And here the component interface
is defined by the `Graphic` class here.
And it defines one method here.
This is a `draw` method.
So it means that all objects in
the composition should understand
the `draw` message.
And now, we have the component
interface.
So here, this is what we said,
it declares the common interface
for all objects in the composition.
It may implement a default behavior.
So here, you can see that the `draw`
method here could be either abstract
or it could be concrete.
It could provide default implementation
for all objects in the composition.
And maybe you want to also declare
here in the component accessor to
manage children, but this is not
mandatory.
Then you have some leaves and leaves,
here we have three kinds of leaf.
So a leaf represents an object with
no children in the composition and
it defines a primitive operation,
but it must conform to the common API.
And finally, we have the composite
there.
So the composite also implements
a polymorphic API.
Here this is a `draw` method.
And basically what does it do?
It just forwards a message to all
elements that are in the composite,
all children in fact.
And of course, it has some operation.
Here, this is `add` and `remove`,
to `add` and `remove` elements in
the composite.
What is important is to understand
that a design pattern is a name
and an intent, but it can have multiple
implementations with some pro and cons.
For example, we could have a different
implementation in a dynamically
typed language.
For example, this is not mandatory
for the 'leaf' class and the 'composite'
class here to have a common superclass,
because what we need in fact,
this is a common API.
And since they both implement the
operation method, here it means
that from the client point of view,
they are polymorphic objects.
So it means that I can send the
message operation to both leaves
and the composite elements and it
will work perfectly.
Of course, not having a common
superclass, this is not possible
to share code between the leaves
and the composite.
And it is more difficult to recognize
the composite design pattern.
Another extreme implementation would
be to only use one class,
the composite class.
And inside this representation with
a single class, in fact,
the leaves are replaced with a composite
with no children.
This is basic.
The gain is not really clear.
And in my opinion, this is not really
a nice design, because if you have
only a single class, you will not
benefit from dispatching.
Because if you remember correctly,
when you're sending a message,
you are making a choice.
The system will make a choice.
It will lookup the method in the
hierarchy class.
And the fewer classes you have,
the fewer choices you have.
So usually, this is much better
to have a hierarchy of classes.
There are some frequently asked
questions about the composite design
pattern that we can review now.
Can the composite contain any type
of child?
Yes, definitely.
The only thing that we need to take
care is that they implement a common
API.
And for example, sometimes this
is difficult when you want to introduce
in your composite objects that come
from third-party libraries.
So it means that perhaps you will
need some adapters or wrappers to
enforce this common API on these
third-party objects.
Can we limit the depth of a composite
object, the number of children?
Of course, we can in the composite
class.
So it means in the `add` and `remove`
methods, I can check the depth,
for example.
And then, can we have different
composites in the same system?
Yes.
And each composite in the system
can have different constraints and
different behavior.
We may have some different variations
about composite behavior.
So far, we only saw the simple forward
message send.
So it means that the composite will
only send forward the message to
all children and merges the results
without performing any other behavior.
But it could also selectively forward
the message to one of the children,
conditionally, of course.
Or it can extend the behavior by
adding an extra behavior and delegate
to the leaves.
Or it can completely override the
behavior of the leaves and have
its own behavior.
The composite design pattern is
really interesting because it can
work perfectly with other design
patterns.
For example, we will see that the
composite and Visitor are really
nice together and play very nice
together.
And Visitors, we will see it in
another lecture.
This is to implement specific operations
on composite.
But composites can also be used
with factories because sometimes
this is difficult to create this
kind of tree structure.
And using factories can help to
have different kinds of elements
in the tree structure.
As a conclusion, composite is about
compositing objects into tree structure
to represent partial hierarchies.
Composite provides a uniform API
to clients.
So leaves and composite are treated
uniformly by clients without checking
anything.
And the composite design pattern
is completely extensible.
This is really easy to `add` new
type of leaves by subclassing.
Of course, we will see that composites
play very nicely with other design
patterns such as Visitors in a future
lecture.