Hello, welcome back.
In this presentation,
we are going to talk about the state
Design Pattern.
The goal for this presentation is
to present this pattern in the most
clear way possible.
We are going to start with a motivating
example that will allow us to present
the characteristics and the good
use of this design pattern.
We are going to represent the different
states of our machine,
of our state machine as objects.
And we are going to encapsulate
in each of these objects the operations
and the state transitions.
Also, we are going to talk some
details about how to handle the
state machine state.
We are going to start by analyzing
an example where to apply this design
pattern.
We are going to have,
in our example, an automatic coffee
machine.
The idea of this machine is that
it will produce for us a coffee
once we pay for it.
So the machine will pass into different
states, it will start waiting for
an order.
Then once we select the beverage
that we want, the coffee that we want,
it will wait for our payment.
It will do the coffee and this coffee,
once it's ready, it will be taken
by the user.
We can represent these states by
this simple state diagram,
where we start with the waiting
for order.
In this case, we call it the 'Idle State'.
Once the user accepts one order,
we are going to pass to the second
state, that is waiting for payment.
The machine will stay in this 'ToPay
State' until we pay enough money.
And then, it will start making coffee.
It will continue making coffee until
it ends and changing its state to
Coffee Ready.
As we see, we have four states and
the machine will be moving in these
states during all its life.
In this case, when we model this
machine as an object,
we are going to have exactly the
same operations.
We are going to accept an order.
We are going to be able to tell
the user 'howMuchIsIt',
this order, so the user can put
money to pay for it.
That is the third operation.
We are going to get the 'coffeeDone'
when it's ready and we are going
to be able to take the coffee from
the machine.
These are the operations that are
exposed by our coffee machine.
When we are having these operations,
not all operations are available
when we use the machine.
They depend on the state that we
are using.
For example, we cannot enter money
into the machine until we select
correctly which is the coffee that
we want.
So if we model this in our Smalltalk
code, we can see that our code starts
having a lot of conditional questions
like this one, where we check in
which state we are to allow the
user to do the operation or not.
In this case, if we are not in the
correct state, we are going to raise
an error.
So we are going to ask for each
of the operations if we are not
in the correct state.
Also, other thing that happened
is that we are going to handle the
state of the machine by hand.
So in each of the operations,
we are going to have mixed conditional
code to check if we are in the correct
state, code to handle the transitions
of a state, and then the real code
that will do the actual operation.
This starts being much more complex
than only having the real operation.
So we can see that this pattern
is repeated in all the operations
that we have.
In this case, we cannot ask the
machine how much is the coffee that
we want if we don't select it first
or if we are not in the correct
machine state.
So we see exactly the same pattern
again when we have to have a conditional
code to check if we are in the correct
state.
Even when we have a really simple
operation that in this case is just
returning an instance variable,
we have a lot of boilerplate code,
code that is complex and does not
add to the final operation.
So what is the idea behind the state
Design Pattern?
Basically, is that we are going
to have objects to represent our states.
We are going to have our coffee machine,
that is our subject, and it will
delegate to another object the
operations and the transitions of
a state.
We are going to represent in our
case each of the four states,
we are going to represent with a class,
where we can implement the different
behaviors for each of the states.
It's important to see,
in this case, we have selected to
have a common superclass for the states.
But this is not needed and just
what we need is that they have the
same interface or they understand
the same message.
In this case, we have selected to
have a common superclass because
what we are going to do in each
of the operations in the common
superclass is to mark them as invalid
and just raise an error.
In this case, all the operations
that are not supported by the current
state will just return and will
raise just an error.
As I said before, the key point
in this Design Pattern is that the
coffee machine, the object that
has the complex state,
the complex state is a complex state
machine, will delegate to each of
the states the operations that we
want to do.
We have rewritten our method acceptOrder
to send the message to the machine
state, to the new object that represents
the state.
When we are in the idle state,
the machine will send the message
acceptOrder.
We are going to do the lookup and
find the correct method and the
code in the Idlestate class will
execute and we are going to perform
the operation and we are going to
change to the new state.
We can see this pattern again in
the other operation that we analyzed
before, that is how much is it the
coffee that we are asking,
and we see that we have the same
pattern.
We delegate in the machineState
to perform the operation,
in this case just returning the price.
We have for all the states an
implementation that raises an error
because is our default implementation.
But in the correct state,
we are going to return the correct
value.
In this case, we have a lot of
advantages.
The idea is that in each state,
in each object that represents our
state, we are going to just implement
the operations that we care on.
Also, we are hiding in these objects,
in this implementation,
the state transitions,
that in this case is simple and
we have a circular state transitions.
We go from one state only to the
next one and so on.
But this could have been more and
more complex, it gets easily more
and more complex.
We also have less conditional code.
We are using much more delegation,
we are using the idea of tell and
don't ask.
This eases a lot the reading of
the code and these properties that
we are marking, like just implementing
the needed operations,
encapsulating the transitions in
each of the class of the states
and having less conditional code,
start being more and more important
when we have much more states or
more complex transitions.
We have an additional point that
is interesting to talk and to analyze
in this design pattern,
is that where to put the instance state.
When I say, instance state,
I mean the state of, in this case,
in the next example, the coffee machine.
So we have to select where to put,
in this case, the instance state
of our coffee machine.
In this case, in this example,
we have just two instance variables
and we can select to put them in
the machine object, in the coffee
machine object, or each of the state
objects that we have.
If we put it in the coffee machine
object, this is useful because this
state is used by all the machine states.
So they are common, they can delegate
to the coffee machine to use the
internal state of the coffee machine.
When we change from one state to
the other, we don't need to copy
these values.
So this simplifies the changing
of one state to the other.
But there is a problem that in this
example is not clear,
but if we have a lot of instance
variables in the coffee machine,
we will need to use them and the
problem is if these instance variables
are different from state to state.
For example, in our example,
if in the either state,
we are using a set of instance variables
that is different than the ones
that we are using in the state while
the machine is doing the beverage,
is doing the drink.
So the problem with that is that
maybe we have instance variables
that we are not using in all the cases.
The other alternative that we can
explore is if we put the state in
the state object itself.
We will put all the instance variables,
all the internal state of the coffee
machine in its state objects.
This is useful.
It's a great idea when each state
of the coffee machine has different
internal state.
We need a different set of instance
variable.
It's also good because we can do
that each state object can directly
access this instance state.
We don't need to use messages or
sending accessors only to the machine,
to the coffee machine,
but it has the consequence that
every time that we change a state,
that we create a new state and assign
it to the coffee machine,
we need to copy, we need to pass
all instance variables to it and
we have to pass the state from one
state object to the next one.
As a conclusion, the state pattern
is useful and is used a lot when
we have an object that has a life
with many states that have a complex
translation between states and that
have different operations for each
of the states because it encapsulates
the operations and the state
transitions.
So we use more delegation instead
of conditional code.
We just will delegate in the state
instead of implementing conditional
code and allows us more flexibility
towards new states and new operations.
Of course, as using any design pattern,
this is a more complex solution
than doing it directly.
So we have to balance it and decide
when we need to use this new complexity
versus the clarity and flexibility
that we win with using this new tool.
As any tool that we have in our toolbox,
there are cases when we are going
to use it and cases when we are
not going to use it.
And it's important to understand
the consequences, the positive and
negative consequences of using one
or other tool, in this case,
the state pattern.