Hello, welcome to this lecture.
We are going to analyze in this
lecture how to turn procedures to
objects and what are the good advantages
of this.
The goals for this lecture is to
present the idea that objects
representing procedures,
representing algorithms are really
powerful and we want to use them
when we need to have complex algorithms.
It is basic idea is to take some
`Behavior` to take some procedure
and convert it in object,
in one or more object.
We are going to explore a basic
example and we are going to see
how this example if we start adding
variations and if we start adding
configurations start getting bigger
and bigger and it is not manageable
and we need to create objects to
represent them.
Let's start with our example.
If we take any class in Pharo and
we send the message `printHierarchy`,
we can see a textual representation
of its hierarchy.
It has in one side the receiver,
the class that we are printing,
the superclasses of it and the
subclasses of it and for each of
these classes we are also printing
the instance variables.
This is really cool.
It allows us to have a nice simple
tool that generates a textual
representation of our hierarchies.
If we see the code that implements this,
we see that it's kind of
straightforward.
We have a `printHierarchy` in `Behavior`
that is the superclass of the class
meta object and we see here that
what it's doing is first iterating
all the superclasses and printing
them and then doing the same with
the subclasses.
In this case, delegating in another
method.
If we see the printSubclassesOn,
this is implemented by doing a new
`tab` in the printing,
then putting the name of the class
and then printing the instance
variables.
This is for the current class that
we are printing and then what it's
doing is that it's starting to iterate
on all the subclasses and doing
this printing in a recursive way.
It does some kind of ordering so
we can print the subclasses always
in the same order, but basically
what it's doing is applying the
same procedure to the subclasses.
This is really good.
It's a good solution because this
procedure has been split in two
methods that are quite simple.
We have one method that is responsible
for printing the superclasses of
the class and one method that is
responsible for printing the subclasses
of the class.
All the state that is needed by
this procedure is passed as arguments,
so we have a really clean and nice
solution.
The problem starts when we start
to add new features to this solution
and we want to have other requirements.
We start seeing the limits of it.
What happens if we need to filter
some subclasses?
In the case of this class RBLintRule,
we will see that has a lot of subclasses
so we want to filter them or we
want to show some of them.
What happens if we want to show,
I don't know, the first three,
the first four or none of the
subclasses?
For example, what happens if we
want to decide to print or not the
superclasses depending on if they
are in a package or not because
for example, we want to only print
the superclasses that are part of
our own package and we don't care
about printing object or proto object
or any of the classes that are part
of the Pharo system?
What if we want to print or not
instance variables?
These are some little examples of
possible configurations that we
want to do to our hierarchy printer.
But now if we want to do it,
we have to add more and more arguments
to our method to print that those
arguments also will be passed to
the printSubclassesOn that we have
in the that is doing the procedure
for the subclasses.
As we see, we can start having
an explosion of new arguments that
we have to add.
Also we cannot start adding this
state as instance variable because
the implementation of this printer
is directly in `Behavior`.
It will affect all the classes in
the system so it's not a good idea,
it's not a good solution to add
instance variables in all the classes
of the system just for printing.
Also it is complicated to configure
this printer because if we have
a printer that requires 10 new arguments
and we just want to use it as before,
we are going to pass values to these
arguments and know what are the
values to pass when we want the
default `Behavior`.
So what we want to do is turn this
procedure into a simple object that
we can configure in a simple way.
In this case, if we want to configure
our printer in the default way,
we are only going to create it because
when we instantiate this printer,
it will have the default configuration
and we are going to send the messages
only to modify the `Behavior` that
we want from it.
A more complex idea, this is a really
really simple one we are going to
print the rectangle class not showing
the instance variable not showing
the superclasses, but we can get
more and more complex.
And for example saying okay we want
to print the RBNode class not showing
the instances, not showing the
superclasses we can send or not
this message if we want or not and
then we can pass for example one
or more or two collections saying
which are the classes to exclude
and which are the classes that we
are limiting on.
As we see, we have different ways
of configuring our hierarchy printer
object because now we have a more
flexible element that we can play
and do all the tools that we already
have seen in this MOOC.
Let's see a little of its
implementation.
We see that it's a really simple object.
It has all the state required for
executing the procedure.
We are going to create it with the
instance variables that are required
to do the procedure itself.
And the most important part is that
when we instantiate it,
it will come with default values
for this for the default `Behavior`.
And then, we can have a nice API,
very fluid API that we can interact
with it to configure it.
We can configure it directly saying,
okay class printer I don't want
you to show the instance variables.
When we send this message,
it will store that in an instance
variable knowing to show or not
the state or we want to be limited
to some specific collection of classes
and we can talk to them.
And also, we can add all the kind
of API that we need for implementing
for example decorations if we want
to add more `tab`s between each
of the elements or we want to leave
white lines in the middle.
All that `Behavior` is implemented
in the `ClassHierarchyPrinter` object.
Let's see another example.
In this case, we are going to talk
about a date printer.
A date printer is a really nice
example of this because we have
different formats of printing dates,
even we have different format that
change from language to language
from different ways of printing
in French, in English,
in Spanish and also we have different
format that are printed different
ways depending on our program.
We can have the day and month complete,
we can have the day and a short
month or different representation
with different separators of the
numbers or different order depending.
And the question is, we implement
all this `Behavior` in the classic
`printOn:` method that is in date,
it will be a little limited.
We will have to choose for only
one and accepting that the others
are not there or we will have to
have an explosion of different `printOn`
methods or different way of configuring
it with arguments.
So what we want in this case is
to have an object that represent
us the date printer and that we
can configure in the different formats.
This object exists and we have a
really more complex example that
is the timestamp format is two different
ways of representing a timestamp.
A timestamp is just a date with
the time in the highest precision
that we can.
So we can represent that in different
way.
We can print them in different way.
And this is the work of the timestamp
format, is basically an implementation
of this printing a textual
representation for a timestamp and
can be also used for parsing.
So we can get from a date or a
timestamp, we can get the text
representation in different format
and from this test representation,
we can also parse using the same object,
using the same configuration we
can parse a given string.
So in this case, we can see that
we can parse the timestamp and read
it from a string and also we can
format this string and say how it
has been printed this timestamp.
It has the two operations,
but the important thing is that
the timestamp format encapsulate
this complex printing and the timestamp
itself, the object timestamp does
not need to know how to be printed.
In this case, we can show another
example when we configure the timestamp
format with a given format for the
date and when we parse the new string,
we get the correct time.
As we see in this example,
we are taking the timestamp format,
configuring it and then using it
for one of these operations of parsing
a day a string and obtaining a date
or taking a date or a timestamp
and printing it as a string.
If we do a little analysis of all this,
of all this lecture, we have the
idea of creating little objects
give us the power because they can
be configured.
We can modify them to have different
internal state to act in different ways.
We can have in this way all the
state that is needed for the procedure,
for the computation that we are
doing for the complex algorithm
complex or not.
But we have all the state and all
the configuration.
Then we can have nice APIs that
we can configure and make the user
of this procedure happier,
easier to read, more flexible because
we are not thinking about adding
a lot of arguments to the procedure.
But we are configuring object and
the object can have specific initial
values that already are useful for
most of the situations.
And as we have a little object and
these objects are independent,
we can write beautiful tests on them,
so we can test if they are working
as we want.
This idea of turning method,
turning procedure, turning `Behavior`
into object is a key point of the
command design pattern and the Visitor
pattern.
And is a really powerful idea.
You have to think always if you
want to take your procedures,
your actions and reify them as objects
to gain flexibility and to gain
the ability to configure and add
new features in the future and make
it more maintainable.