Hello, in this lecture,
we are going to talk about Null
Checks and how to avoid them.
The goals of this lecture is to
understand the implication of methods
that return `nil` or null.
So `nil` is actually the equivalent
of null in Java or C Sharp,
for example.
We're going to analyze what happens
in the side of the provider,
so the one that returns `nil`,
and what happens in the client side.
And we're going to see how to avoid
propagation by correctly initializing
an object, and then how to also
use a design pattern called Null
Object to avoid `nil` checks.
So what is `nil` in Pharo?
In Pharo, `nil` is an object,
as any other object in the system,
it's an instance of `UndefinedObject`.
So every time that you write `nil`
in the code, this is like a reference
to a singleton object that points
to this instance of `UndefinedObject`.
This is equivalent to `nil` in other
languages such as Ruby,
or null in other languages such as Java.
The main difference between Pharo
and Java is that in Pharo,
`nil` is a real object,
as anybody else, as any other object
in the system, but it's just a singleton
object.
There is only one instance of
`UndefinedObject`.
Also similarly to other object-oriented
languages, every time that we are
going create variables or instantiate
objects, the variables are initialized
as `nil`.
So every time, for example,
if you have a 'point' class with an
'x' and a 'y' attribute, every time
that you do point new,
the object that is created will
have an 'x' variable and a 'y' variable
that will point to `nil`,
to the same `nil` object.
This also means that we need to
be careful and we need to know when
to use it and when to not use it.
So this, they will come by default,
but we can manage it.
So let's first look at what happens
from the side that returns `nil`.
So every time that you write a method,
so 'm' that returns `nil`,
or a method 'n' that will do some if,
condition, if true, return `nil`,
else return 7, for example.
The question is, what happens with this?
What are the consequences of doing this?
So we can ask ourselves this question.
Let's approach this with an example.
So here, for example,
you see the code of an inferencer.
So it's a rule system.
It's a simple rule system.
We have an inferencer object that
has rules to be applied in certain
conditions.
For example, here there is a little
DSL that says, okay, when it is sunny,
I'm going to use sunglasses.
And when it is sunny,
I am also going to use solar cream.
When it is rainy, I'm going to use
an umbrella.
So this little arrow,
if it is this, I'm going to do this.
So here what happens is that if
I take the inferencer and I ask,
okay, give me the rules for sunny,
it returns a set of rules.
So here it's an array,
where the first rule is,
okay, since it is sunny,
I'm going to use sunglasses.
And since it is sunny,
I'm going to use solar cream.
Now what happens if I ask the rules
for some weather that was not programmed
in the set of rules?
So for example, here we can ask,
okay, what happens if it is cloudy?
And right now, our inferencer is
returning `nil`.
So we can check how this is implemented.
In this case, every time that we
ask the rule for a fact,
so here the fact will be cloudy or sunny,
so it will be the symbols sunny
or cloudy, first we check if we
have rules for that fact.
If we have no rules, we return `nil`.
Otherwise, we return the rules that
apply for that fact.
So `nil` here, it is used as a token
to indicate that there were no rules
for that weather or for that fact
in this case.
So now, what are the consequences
of returning this `nil`?
We're going to see those consequences
in every place that is calling this
method, so in the clients.
So returning `nil` in our rule method
means that every time that there
is a method that is going to call
this method, it has to check if
the result was `nil` or not.
So every time that we are going
to call this method, we are checking
if it is `nil` or not.
So that means that all the code
that is doing this will be followed
by conditional checks all the time.
So this will somehow pollute the
code and make it more difficult
to change.
So one solution to this is to use
polymorphic objects.
So if we think about this,
so one way to avoid this is to avoid
the problem that we saw before is
that if we ask for the rules for
a weather that is not there,
we could return an empty collection.
So if we ask for the rules for a
weather that we know,
we are going to return the collection
of rules that match.
And if we ask for the rules of a
weather that doesn't exist in our
system, we can just return an empty
collection.
So of course, an array with elements
is polymorphic to an array with
no elements.
So that will simplify the code and
allow a simple way to manipulate
the result of our method.
So of course, in this case,
since we were returning collections,
the choice is easy.
We can just return an empty collection.
But you can think of this as when
you were studying math.
So we can think that the collection
is the zero or the neutral element
of the collection.
So when you concatenate the collection
with another collection,
it will return the same collection.
Or when you iterate a collection
that is empty, it will do nothing.
So it is an element that does nothing.
So it represents the empty or the
no collection, naturally.
But in cases when we are,
for example, manipulating numbers,
we can return zero, for example,
if we are going to add them.
If we are going to multiply them,
maybe we want to return the one,
yeah, and so on.
So this is a kind of rule that we
can apply to many cases when we
are adding or removing,
actually, this `nil` check.
So that means that the code that
we saw before can be refactored
to look like this.
So instead of returning `nil`,
we can just return an empty collection.
We return an empty array in this case.
And then, the client can be refactored
or replaced by this code.
So now, we don't need a `nil` check
anymore.
We can just iterate the result of
our method.
So if we have rules for a fact,
this is, of course, giving us a
collection of elements that we are
going to iterate and do some code
here for each of the elements.
However, if we don't have any rules
for this fact, this is going to
return an empty collection,
and the iteration will just do nothing.
So what are other ways of limiting
the propagation of `nil`?
So first, we should think about
the method that are returning `nil`
and try to avoid them.
So for example, adding these null
elements.
We can also store, or we should
also avoid storing `nil` in variables
explicitly.
So one of the rules is to avoid
explicitly using `nil` as a marker.
And of course, to do this,
we can initialize properly the instance
variables of the object.
So remember that every time that
we are going to initialize an object,
all the instance variables are going
to be initialized with `nil` or
with null in other languages.
So it is the developer's responsibility
to produce objects that are well
initialized.
If we provide objects that are well
initialized, we can avoid `nil`
checks in the rest of our code.
So to give you an example,
here if we have an archive,
we can define in Pharo the initialize
method.
In the initialize method,
we can actually take care of the
initialization of all the instance
variables that can have default values.
So here in this case,
we can initialize the members instance
variable as an order collection.
Of course, sometimes default values
are not enough.
And sometimes the values that should
come as the values of our instance
variables should come from the outside.
So a good way to provide a well
constructed object is to provide
the constructor method.
So we can say, for example,
that the only legal way to instantiate
the point is by doing it using a
constructor method like x:7 y:17.
And this will create a point that
will have a correct value of 'x' and
a correct value of 'y' and avoiding
`nil` in points.
Of course, you may think sometimes
you have to check.
We don't have empty collection.
So collections have empty collections.
Numbers have zero or one as potential
Null Object.
So what can you do when you have
some object of your domain that
you want to represent as empty?
So one way to do it is to represent
it with what we call a Null object.
So you can turn your default case
into a Null Object of your model.
So here we have some code taken
from Pharo actually.
So let's imagine though we have
this `ToolPalette`.
This `ToolPalette` has tools inside.
It has a selected tool in particular.
So you can think about,
for example, if you are using Photoshop
or Paint, you have a set of tools
with buttons and then one of the
buttons is selected showing that
you are using this tool.
So for example, we can use the pen.
Okay, we have the pen and the bucket
of paint and so on.
But we are using the pen.
Now, it may happen that we have
no selected tool at all.
So the program should behave properly
when no tool is selected too.
If we check the code,
it is asking all the time.
Okay, if I have a selected tool,
so if the selected tool is not null,
I will do something.
Or in the previous action method,
if I have a selected tool,
if it is not null, I will do something
else.
So if we check at the model,
so in an UML diagram of this,
so we see that the `ToolPalette`
is using a tool.
So it has actually right now it
has zero or one tool.
And that is why it is not null check
because it may have zero elements
in here.
So this is either a tool or `nil`.
And we see that the tools understand
we can have different kind of tools.
So for example, a tool for 'creation',
a tool for adding 'NewNode'.
And then all of the tools,
they are polymorphic and they understand
the same messages.
They understand attach or detach
handles.
What can we do to actually remove
here the `nil` check?
If we only restrain ourselves to
basic objects like collections,
numbers or 'nil', of course,
we are forced to check if there
is a selected tool.
One way to think about this one
another way is that we can have
always a tool.
And it could be a tool that does
nothing when it is not selected
because what happens in this code
when there is no tool?
Well, actually, when there is no tool,
this 'ifNotNil:' check will not execute
the block and it will just continue
and do nothing.
So we could have a tool that does
exactly that.
It does nothing.
And we could have the same behavior.
So this actually is an idea coming
from a design pattern calling the
Null Object that comes from the book,
Pattern Languages of Program Design
of 1998.
The objective of this design pattern
is to provide an object that is
polymorphic to other objects,
but has only default actions and
default values.
Of course, I invite you to read
it and get a deeper understanding
of this pattern.
In our case, what we could do is
to implement the absence of a tool
so we can implement a different class,
a different object that will represent
the null tool.
And in this case, each `NoTool`
that we can instantiate in our system
will do nothing when it is asked
to attach handles or to detach handles.
Then we can refactor our previous
code to look like this.
We can initialize initially the
`ToolPalette` with `NoTool`.
So by default, `NoTool` is selected.
And then, all the code in our actions
will just take the selected tool,
whatever it is, it is not `nil` anymore.
Now it is either a no tool or a
correct tool, and we can ask it
to attach or detach the handles.
So the only thing that we did in
our model before was to add a new
kind of tool in our model.
So we just exploited the polymorphism
in our model.
And now instead of having zero to
one element tools in our palette,
we just have always one tool in
our `ToolPalette`.
And then the `ToolPalette` doesn't
need to check anymore if it is empty
or not.
What are the advantages of using
`NullObjects`?
So the main advantage is that it
will simplify client code.
So there will be no need to check
for `NullObjects`, for `nil` all
the time anymore.
So since the `NullObject` will have
the same API as the original objects.
It also clarifies what is the default
behavior.
So what does it mean to have nothing
selected?
Now we can just take a look at the
new class, the `NoTool` class that
was there.
And if we inspect all the methods
that are there, we can see what
is the behavior of our system when
there's `NoTool` that is selected.
And now this tool is also reusable.
We could also reuse this code to
be able to deselect stuff easily.
Now, of course, as every engineering
decision, using `NullObjects` has
benefits, but also has disadvantages.
Now, it may not be easy to actually
add `NullObjects` everywhere when
we need it.
So sometimes, it will be difficult
when we have large object graphs,
for example.
Also, when we have a `NullObject`,
we cannot just transform it into
a real object later.
And finally, all clients should
agree on the same do nothing behavior.
So it is easier.
Of course, it has the same behavior
for many parts in the application.
Otherwise, we will have different
`NoTools` for different parts of
the application.
Sometimes it's also not easy to
apply this `NullObject` because
the API is too large.
So if we have 50 methods to implement
in our `NoTool`, maybe it is not
practical to use it.
And maybe it is simpler to just
put that code into the client.
The same case as we discussed before,
maybe we need too many `NullObjects`
if they don't have the same API
or they don't have the same behavior.
And sometimes it's not clear what
does it mean to have no behavior.
So what is the default behavior
that the `NullObject` should implement?
That is not clear in the model
sometimes.
So some points about the difference
between the `NullObject` or `nil`
and the `NullObject` as the design
pattern.
So sometimes it is possible that
we initialize an object,
like for example, our point with
default values, with for example,
null values.
We could initialize the point in
the initialized method with 'x'
equals to zero and 'y' equals to zero too.
That could give us a default point
that can be usable in case we didn't
use the constructor.
Some other examples could be,
for example, to use a null time
zone for times.
Or it could have, for example,
as we talked before, null values
for common objects like collections,
zeros for numbers, and so on.
For exceptional cases,
one thing that could happen is that
instead of having a default behavior
or a `NullObject`, we could use
exceptions.
So for example, we can replace `nil`
by throwing an exception to avoid
errors and unexpected cases.
So for example here, if we have
a stream and the stream can be in
two different states,
it can be readable or writable,
then we want to avoid writing on
the stream if it is not writable.
Instead of having a default behavior
that ignores the incorrect behavior,
what we can do is to just throw
an exception here, for example,
when there is an attempt to write
into the object if it is not written.
Then it is up to the client to manage
the exception, but since exceptions
bubble up in the call stack,
so we have calls that,
methods that call each other,
and at some point we have an exception.
The exception automatically bubbles
up in the stack, and then we can
manage it in the correct layer,
and we don't need to manage it directly
in the caller, as it was the case
for the `nil` check.
A `NullObject` is a way to use messages
to manage default values and default
cases in the behavior of our systems.
So we could deal with dispatch and
messages instead of if checks.
We can avoid null checks returning
polymorphic objects either by using
objects that are already available
in the system, like collections
and zeros, but we can also create
our own creating `NullObjects`,
implementing our own,
and also remember to initialize
your variables to avoid checking
for `nil` in the client.