Hello, welcome to this presentation.
In this lecture, we are going to
talk about blocks and their relationship
with objects.
We are going to think about when
to use blocks, when to use the objects,
and what are the advantages and
disadvantages of one and the other.
For this presentation,
we are going to think about the
API and the power that blocks give
us in Pharo and how they are powerful
and handy to use.
And then, we are going to compare
them with small objects and show
how small objects that we are created
for a given specific task are more
powerful than blocks in the long term.
Blocks are really powerful.
We are using them all days in Pharo
syntax and in our object model.
It provides us with a good model
to implement iterators.
They are really cool to generate
new iterator definitions and also
to produce DSL-like APIs.
When we use blocks, they are central
to our system based on message paths.
Remember that blocks freeze the
execution and give the power to
decide when to execute them.
We use them, for example,
to implement beautifully the `Boolean`
operators in Pharo and also to implement
the conditional code.
And they are key for the compact
syntax of Pharo.
We also use blocks all the time
when we use iterators,
our own collections.
We use them to express what we are
going to do with each of the elements.
For example, in this case,
we have a collection with two numbers
and we are going to iterate them
with the 'allSatisfy' operation to
check that all of them respond to
whatever we pass inside the block.
In this case, sending them for each
of them the message even.
We see that this is used in more
complex iteration patterns,
like, for example, when we want
to iterate a collection,
in this case, this part,
and also do something between each
of the elements.
This iteration is more complex,
but also it's using the power of blocks.
In this case, also we are using
blocks to establish the limit when
we want to have a string generating
a new string.
Blocks are really useful for us
because also allows us to implement
new iterators.
If we see how, for example,
the methods 'pairsDo:' is implemented
in sequenceable collection,
this method is implemented using
exactly the same mechanism that
is already present.
It's using the iteration one to
the given position to do with the
message to do of integers and we
are iterating this collection.
As we can see, we can nest blocks.
Yes, the block that we are receiving
as argument, we are using it inside
another block.
This is really, really powerful
and we use it a lot in all the programs
that we write in Pharo.
Other cool feature that we use all
the time about blocks is that we
can use it then to implement DSL-like
APIs.
We can in this way generate a little
context that will be executed or
when we are using the builder.
In this case, we are building a
presentation, a composite presentation,
and we are passing it the instructions
to build it inside.
This is more complex,
but we can extract the same example.
For example, when we are taking the text,
we are creating a new composite
text with this title and the content
that is produced by this block.
In this case, taking the file and
evaluating its content.
However, the blocks, even being
so powerful, sometimes are a little
weak when we compare them with literal
or small objects that we create
for a given task.
Because blocks on the spot are just
literal objects, but they are not
different, they don't have any
difference with objects that understand
the message `value`.
The good thing of using blocks is
that we can create objects without
needed to create a given class or
define a given method.
But it has a problem.
When we want to store them and change
the state on them, it's really
complicated, so usually we are not
doing.
We have also a single entry point to it.
We can only send the message `value`
or any of its varieties with more
arguments.
When we need to pass more than one
argument to a block, it's difficult
to see what is the order of them
and what is receiving in each of them.
So does not expose well the arguments
and how we need to use the blocks.
It looks like it's easy to write
because blocks are easy to write.
In Pharo, the syntax to create a
block is just using the square bracket.
But when we start extending these
scripts, it's more difficult.
Because what we want to have always
is have a rich API that allows us
to have more flexibility.
And in this case, with blocks,
that is impossible.
Blocks basically works like black boxes.
You can only send the message of
the `value` family, `value`,
`value` colon and `value`,
`value` and so on for different
amount of arguments.
We don't have the ability to modify
the state of the block.
We can only execute it.
We don't have access to modify easily
the state of the block and we cannot
add instance variable to them to
add behavior that we are going to,
for example, accumulate.
A nice example is what happens if
we want a block that every time
that we execute will accumulate
some information.
Well, you cannot do it in a really
clean and nice way.
We always can hack, but at the end
is a solution that is really bad
and ends with a poor quality solution.
The same problem, we have it with
the arguments.
When we start having a more complex
operation on the arguments,
for example, we want optional arguments.
That starts to be a problem in block
because we cannot select which arguments
to pass or not to a block.
We have to choose exactly the order
of arguments and which arguments
we are passing.
So if we design it wrong,
we will only have a given order.
We cannot have more than one order.
Also, there is cull: in the system,
but we should avoid using it because
it's reflected by nature and it
is a bad practice and we have better
ways of representing optional arguments.
Even having optional arguments or
not having optional arguments,
one of the main problems of blocks
when they have more than one argument
is that we need to choose exactly
what is each of them.
The order of the arguments that
we are passing is important.
And when we see as an example,
this message send using inject into
that receives a block with two
arguments, we never know which of
them is the accumulator and which
of them is the element that we are
iterating.
Remember that inject into what happened
is that uses a `value` that is keep
accumulated in each loop in each
iteration of the collection and
the other is the element that we
are iterating.
So it's not clear, for the user
is not clear for the reader of the code,
which is one or the other.
Also, we have that saving blocks
is painful.
Block is by definition,
a dynamic element in our language
and it's complicated to save it,
to export it, to serialize it,
to save it to a database or to represent
it from any kind of data.
Also, we cannot add any kind of
a message to it to add new behavior
and having extensions via subclassing
or adding a new implementation is
impossible.
When we have long blocks that have
a lot of code inside,
we lose a big opportunity that is
to split that code in many methods,
because in a block we have only
one unit that has all the code
intermixed inside and we cannot
explicit it or using template methods
or delegating to other methods with
a self-send.
We need to send messages and we
need a receiver in order to be able
to reuse and have a nice solution.
So every time that we have a long
block is a code smell that we have
to see and that we have to analyze
if it's worthy or not.
For example, we have these two cases
that are doing similar code that
are having the same effect,
but we want to modify it.
We pass from having a big block,
a long block where we have many
operations to have a new 'method'
where we can delegate to this 'method'
inside the block.
As the method is the unit of reuse,
we want to have it and we want to
have this method created in a given
class so we can start using tools on it,
a template method or a specialization
in a subclass or dividing it for
clarity or doing whatever we want
with it.
This is exactly the same example,
but now with a real code,
we see the complexity of this block
and all the messages that it's sending
and all the decisions that it's taking,
and we cannot do any kind of refactoring
inside it.
The first that we need to do to
work it better, this code to improve
its quality, is extract it to a
method where we can do all the different
tools that we have already seen
in all the lectures.
So we have here a clear problem
that we use it all the time.
We want to have little objects.
We want to model our solution with
objects.
So in this case, we will see that
having little objects that have
a really nice design API and that
has internal state can be much,
much powerful than blocks.
We can specify optional arguments.
We can give initial values to them.
We can give a different behavior.
We can structure the code in different
methods, and we can delegate and
use polymorphism and subclassing
and all the tools that we have in
our toolbox, and by having these
little objects that we are delegating
the behavior instead of using a block,
we can always have extension and
refactoring.
As a conclusion, a good way of using
blocks is always keeping them as
small as possible.
When we start having long blocks,
that is a code smell,
that is a situation that we have
to analyze to improve the quality.
You see them a lot to generate DSL-like
constructions, DSL-like builders,
and it's really good to do scripting,
but when you are defining your domain
model, pay attention not to overuse
them because they are less flexible
than having real objects that we
model and we create with a given
task in mind.
Don't have fear to create classes
and pass instances and create new
instances, small instances for represent
our behavior and to replace blocks.
And this, you will learn it little
by little because as any of the
discussions that we have in this MOOC,
it requires to analyze when to use
it and when to not use it.
Because as I said before,
blocks are really powerful and we
want to use them when they are useful
and we want to avoid them when they
give more pain than benefits.