- Hello,
welcome to this presentation.
In this presentation,
we are going to present the Command
Design Pattern.
The goals for this presentation
starts with a little example for
having a motivation for this Pattern.
Then, we are going to see which
is the power of reification of actions.
And finally, we are going to enter
in the Command Design Pattern.
Let's start with an example.
Imagine that we have a robot that
we can script, that we can script
with a string that has this shape,
where we have the action to do and
the parameter to the action.
In this case, for example,
take the direction to the east or
move two units or take the direction
to the north and move three units.
Let's see how we can implement this.
Well, first, what we can do is take
our string and splitting it on the
new line character, so we have a
collection of orders.
For each order, we are going to
have one string that we are going
to again split, in this case,
by the space character.
Like that, we are going to have
for each order, a pair that is the
operation and the parameter for
this operation.
So later, we can take our collection
of orders and in this case,
the variable orders will contain
an array where we will have a pair
with the first element will be the
order and then the parameter of it.
Then for example, we can have one
'dir,' #north and so on.
This is the structure that we have
in our collections of orders.
So we are going to take each of
them and we are going to see if
the operation is moved,
we are going to tell the robot to
do this operation parsing the second
argument.
The same, if this is not moved,
we are going to check if it's a
'dir' operation and we are going
to execute that.
As we see, we have conditional code
that will test each of the actions
that we are doing.
Now let's see what happen when we
tried to add more operations to
our robot.
Imagine that we want to add a 'pick'
operation or a 'drop' operation
or a 'return' operation that takes
back the robot to the base.
In this case, what we are going
to do is adding more and more
conditional code on it.
As we had before, just asking for
move and 'dir,' now we are going
to ask for if it's a 'drop,' 'pick'
or 'first.' Seeing that adding here
more and more operations,
what that does is that we have more
conditional code, increasing the
amount of complexity of this method.
Each time we add a new operation,
we are going to have a longer method
that has more and more complex
conditional code.
So let's analyze up to here the
example that we have.
In this example, when we add a new
order, we have to modify exactly
the same method all the time.
Adding them is highly expensive
because we have to improve the
complexity of this method.
Adding more and more orders,
finish with a really big execute method.
Also imagine if we want to have
orders that are more complex.
In this scenario, we can have an
order that allows us to execute
many mov at the same time.
Let's see, for example,
if moving once, executing mov 10 mov 10
and mov 10 is more expensive.
We can unify them in a single mov 30.
Doing the three instead of doing
three mov, doing only one.
In this case, well, we will have
our text that represents the action,
the string, the extra strings and
manipulating strings to compact them
itself into this mov 30 is complex.
We want to have objects to manipulate
them because they are easy to modify.
Also, let's see another example
where our solution is really short
is that what happen if we want to
replay this action that we have done.
But in the inverse order to make
it come back to the home base
for example.
Well, you can tell me okay,
we are going to iterate now the
string in backwards.
But that again is complex.
We want to have a better solution.
So in this example, let's introduce
the idea of the Command Design Pattern.
This is the intention that we have
taken from the Design Pattern book
from the Gang of Four,
but it says exactly what we want.
We want to encapsulate in this case,
the operations as objects,
a request or operations as an object.
Then letting like this as we have
objects, we can start parameterizing
them by the client, modifying them
for example, for each of the operations
in the parameters to use or the
order to execute it.
And then, as we have objects,
we can do operations on them.
We can queue them, we can log them,
we can undo them or we can for example,
compact many of them in a single
operation or do whatever operation
we want because now we have objects
and they are more powerful than
having just a text representation.
Basically, a Command is just reification
of an order or an action itself
in that we want to create as an
object that in case will represent
an order or an action on more complex
object.
Usually in a Command,
we are going to encapsulate more
than just the action that we are
executing, we are going to encapsulate
all the context, all the elements
that it needs to execute.
For example, we can encapsulate
all the parameters, we can encapsulate
how this is a log or for example,
information to create a menu or
how to display this action.
And Commands are really useful when
we want to have and do operations
because as we are going to create
a list of objects with each of our
actions, we can keep this list and
basically reverse the order and
execute and still executing in reverse
order we can execute it in them
back in an undo fashion.
And as each action, each Command,
it knows what are the arguments
and what it is doing,
it's easy to implement a reverse
operation.
In the case of the road,
if it has turned to the east,
we can make it turn it in the west
direction, which is basically a
stricter of a Command.
Well, we have two roles clearly defined.
In one side, we have the clients
of our Command Pattern and then
we will have the object that we
are modifying with these actions.
Then we are going to have concrete
objects representing each of the
operations that we want.
In this case, it's common that we
have a Command abstract superclass
between the concrete Commands,
but this is not required.
Usually, it is decided because we
are going to put all the Command
behavior in the superclass,
but that is just a decision we can
have a Command Design Pattern just
using a polymorphic message that
is the most important thing because
who will create the action will
create the Command will configure
it and eventually somebody will
send the message execute,
to execute it in a polymorphic way.
It is the same, it executes the
concrete action one or the concrete
Command2.
Let's see our example in action,
let's put the Design Pattern in
our example.
In this case, we are going to a
superclass in Command,
common abstract superclass.
But the important thing is that
we are going to create an object
for each of the operations that we have.
In this case, we are going to create
one for the DirectionCommand and
we are going to give in it the direction
that we want to turn.
In this case, in our solution,
we are going to have two methods
in our Command.
In one side, we are going to have
a method to handle the arguments
to parse the arguments and store
it in the correct values for the
Command storing in the instance
variable direction the value that
has extracted.
And then, we will have an executeOn
that will do the action.
Each of the operations,
each of the Commands will do is
affect a specific action depending
on what we are doing.
For the move, we have exactly the same.
For the move, in this case,
we are going to get the argument
direction from the arguments and
we are going to extract it.
In this case, the Commands are simple
and just has one argument,
but this same architecture,
the same solution can be used to
extract more complex arguments from
the collection of orders.
And then, exactly the same when
we are executing the action on the
robot we are going to delegate the
correct action into the robot.
As we see, now the executeCommand
will be much much simpler.
We are going to have exactly the
same code to parse the strings,
but later when we are executing
each of the orders, we are going
to delegate to the Command to execute.
We are going to decide which is
the Command to execute,
just create a new instance and parsed
the arguments and execute it.
So in this case, we are going to
create this Command for class,
we'll take, we'll delegate in each
of the Commands and ask if the given
string that represent the Command
applies for each of them.
As we see in this example,
we have reduced all the conditional
code, all the boilerplate code that
we have before that was not adding.
It was just adding complexity to
our solution.
In this case, the solution is much
easier because we are just delegating
into the correct class.
In our scenario, if we want just
to add new Commands to our robot,
we just add new classes extending
by Command and each Command is now
responsible for handling the arguments
and the information needed to perform
the action.
It also encapsulates the applicability
and what to do in this action.
This is important because now we
have an object that we can use to
ask and demand information and now
we have a collection of objects
that we can do many things.
For example, we can log them,
we can sort them in the correct order,
we can undo it, we can merge them
if they are needed because we have
objects and we now have a better
representation for our actions.
But there are always consequences
of using a Design Pattern and in
this case is not different.
Well, not all operations that we
have in our solution should be turned
into Command objects because basically
when we start adding more and more
Commands, we are going to have a
large hierarchy of simple classes
that will grow and grow.
So we need to select which are the
operations that we want to represent
as Commands.
Also it's important that we keep
the behavior of the object that
is exposed in the actions inside
the object because if not,
we can tend to break the encapsulation
and break the nature of the object.
If the robot just do nothing now,
we are going to have a problem.
It's not a nice solution.
As a conclusion, you have to think
the idea, the main idea in the Design
Pattern is that we are going to
take actions and we are going to
take orders and operations and we
are going to reify them as objects.
We are going to create first class
citizens for these operations.
And so, like that we can use it
as any other object in our system.
This solution is great when we have
to do operations like undoing the
operations that we have executed,
we have a list of operations and
then we want to reverse them in
order and undo them, when we want
to replay the same, when we want
to optimize before executing or
when we are delaying the execution
between the creation of the objects
and this real execution.