- Hello everybody,
welcome to this new lecture.
In this lecture, I will talk about
fluid APIs.
I think that there are really few
lectures in the world on that,
so that will be really interesting
to see what is this tool.
And in particular, we will look
at the case for the class definition
in Pharo as a concrete example.
The goal of this lecture is to think
about methods with a large number
of parameters to show you what is
in fact the fluid API and what are
the properties, and to think a bit
more modular, and also to study
a really concrete case that is the
class definition in Pharo.
So for example, the DockingBar class
has a method with one,
two, three, four, five,
six parameters, which is too much
in fact.
And what you see is that it is invoked,
for example, in these other methods
with default values, because the
user does not know exactly what
is the value that it should pass,
or if it is optional.
So in the case it is optional,
it will put nil.
So what you see with this example
is that first, there are too many
parameters, but in addition,
it forces users to specify all the
parameters.
And when you don't know,
you put nil.
It goes against the idea of limiting
the propagation of nil,
as you saw in the avoid nil lecture.
So we can do better.
In addition, imagine that you would
like to say, oh, you know,
as a developer, I don't need this,
or my client do not need this optional
argument.
So I want to propose in the API
of my class, a new method.
That should be okay, but it means
that suddenly you will have to provide
all this variation, because how
I remove action, I have one with action,
I have with key text.
And here, this is easy because we
remove the optional argument at
the end and we go from right to left.
But what if we want to change the order?
What if the optional argument is
in the middle?
It's a total mess from that perspective.
We will have far too many methods
and a combinatorial explosion.
So let's study what is a fluid API.
So a fluid API, this is basically,
instead of having mandatory parameters,
like here, we will cut these methods
into separated methods.
And like that, the user,
so this expression will become like
that.
We said, okay, instead of having
the methods add, icon,
help, and by the way,
in the Java syntax, this method,
this is addIconhelp(w,a,h).
We will just say, okay,
we just want to have x.add(w),
x.icon(a).
So we turn these single methods
into multiple methods that are
autonomous.
And this way, we can,
as a user, use them in a different way.
So this means that I could call add,
icon, and help, or I can call icon,
and add, or I can also just say,
oh, I don't need to change anything,
I just want to specify the help string.
So if we analyze this solution,
we don't need to pass all the default
values around.
There is no combinatorial explosion.
So this means that from the developer
of the class, you don't have to
think about all the possible variation
that maybe your user would like to have.
You just specify your messages or
the methods, the methods that are
needed, and no more.
From the user perspective,
you can focus on the message that
you need.
You will just specify,
oh, I need that method,
and we'll send this message.
Of course, it requires that you
have a good and modular initialization,
because this means that the arguments
that are optional, they should be
well initialized.
And you should pay attention.
If you have dependencies between
parameters, then in that case,
maybe you will have a method.
For example, if I take back the example,
you could have add, icon,
for example, because maybe the add
and the icon, they are linked together
into an initialization.
But this means that you can split,
you can still split your long,
your method with long parameters
into a different variation.
So it has the fluid API is really nice.
And now, we will see a concrete case.
The question that we got with Pharo,
this was, okay, how do we support
the evolution of class definitions?
Because in Pharo, we have multiple
class definitions, and they have
to change because over the years,
we introduce package,
we introduce multiple formats,
like ephemerons or not.
And we also introduce the point
that we have now, we don't have
instance variable anymore,
we have first class instance variable.
And we want to do that without having
a parameter explosion.
So let's look at it.
So Pharo is originally inspired
by Smalltalk-80, and in Smalltalk-80,
one of the ways to create a class,
so for example, this one,
this is a class with a variable part,
the instance have a variable part,
we will use this message,
variableSubclass, instanceVariableNames,
so this is already five parameters.
That's already too much.
And the funny thing is that I always
joke this definition,
because I said, oh, you know,
you have to pass default value,
instead of not passing the value,
you have to pass it.
And here, we have to pass an empty
string and I was always worried
about that.
I said, if this is empty,
why do we care?
So first, up to Pharo 9,
we removed one of the parameters,
you see, you don't see it anymore,
because it is not frequent that
people use shared pools.
This is a lecture that you will
see in the future.
Shared pools are handy,
but when you don't use them,
why do I have to specify an empty
string?
So in Pharo, up to Pharo 9,
in fact, we just introduce a new
version where you have package instead
of category and no pool here.
So we remove it.
So you see, this is already,
this is another version of the class
definition with four parameters.
And then, we have to change the
variable subclass also to have the
full version variation.
And like that, I could continue
endlessly.
I guess that we have 40 different
methods to create a class definition.
And this is insane.
So we wanted to really have modern
class definition because we have
package, tags, slot.
We have various format like Word,
Byte, Double Byte, Variable,
Indexed.
And then, we have new format like
ephemerons because they are special
things for weak structure.
And we face this, we said,
okay, we cannot continue like that.
So we decided to use a fluid API.
So this means that using optional
argument and to be able to control
the mandatory parameters and only
specify the necessary parameters.
Like that, we have a syntax that
is extensible.
And what you will see is that it
needs a builder and sometimes you
need optional default values.
So let's look at it.
So in Pharo 10 and Pharo 11,
now we define a class like that.
We said, okay, I would like a subclass
of the class ArrayedCollection.
And here, we have separated messages.
Here we have three different messages.
When we don't need to specify a
layout or when we don't want to
have a tag or when we don't want
to have something, this is also correct.
Here, this is a metaclass.
We can say, okay, this is the metaclass
definition.
It does not have instance variable
and this is working.
You see here, I don't specify things
that are not needed.
The same here, I only specify what
is needed.
By the way, what I want to show to you,
this is that this little lesser,
lesser return a class builder and
the other messages will configure it.
And what we end up to have,
we end up to have something that
is modular, compact and extensible.
So let's look at some examples.
So you see here, in Pharo,
we have a first class instance variable
that are called slots.
And this is the way we said,
okay, this is the slot.
And then, we have a specific way
to define a slot inside this definition.
And again, here I don't specify
anything else than what is needed.
I said, okay, this is in the package.
This is in the tag, because in the
package, we can have some classification
and the instance variable.
That's it.
We have also traits in Pharo.
So now in traits, I can just define
a trait.
And if I don't need to have anything,
then I don't write it.
Let's step back and look a bit at
what we have, because in fact,
we have three kinds of messages
in the class definition and the
fluid API.
So first, we have the starting or
creator message.
In fact, it will create a kind of
accumulator.
So here, when we said object << #point,
for example, this message generate
a builder.
The builder, this is what ?
This is an object that will be able
to be configured via the other message.
So the other message that we have here,
the configuration/setter,
they are like slots.
For example, oh yes, I have the
message slot and I can specify
something.
It will configure the instance of
the builder with different values.
Like if I can send a message tag,
for example, I would say,
okay, this class is in the tag total.
Okay.
So the builder is configured and
we have a closing message.
This is the one that perform the
action once the argument are passed
and that the accumulator has been
configured.
In our definition, this is package.
The package message is really saying,
okay, the builder has been configured.
Now I can do some action.
And this is what you see here.
This is the creator.
Oh, this guy return a builder.
We configure it with multiple messages.
We don't care of the order and things
like that.
They are optional.
And this one is mandatory.
And it will send a message to the
builder and say, please do your job now.
And do your job now in the case
of a class builder, will check,
validate and install,
create a new class that is configured
into the system.
Now I want to show you that in fact,
this is also available in other system.
Like in Seaside, Seaside is a web
framework for written in Pharo.
In Seaside, often people should
write for each visual component,
they should write a method that
is called render content on where
the builder is specified.
So the HTML is already the builder.
This is the framework.
This is the framework that created
the builder and you have the
configuration.
These messages are configuration
and the closing are these three
messages.
So on the simple case,
for example, I said to the builder,
oh, I want that you configure yourself
to emit a header at level three.
And I want, this is the text.
So when the people designing the
API of Seaside, they made sure that
the developer will not forget to
close the builder by having this
with or this is not three closing,
but this is like that.
This API will create a kind of
object that will present the  to emit
in HTML.
And here what we see,
this is another case,
for example, where they said,
oh, they have again this configuration.
They have this fluid API that is
a bit different from the class
definition, but still at the end here,
they will have a PA or something
like that with hello world.
And then, the width is used to control
and to give a scope.
So here they will do OL,
for example, or the overall list.
They will close the OL and here
inside they will generate LE item
one and they use the width to make
sure that the expression is closed.
You see, so the width here will
make sure that this guy is written,
but this is the same idea.
This is how can we offer an API
where we can compose messages and
without having extra argument and
too many arguments.
So what you see is that fluid API
are nice because they handle the
combinatorial explosion.
There is no combinatorial explosion.
They handle optional argument.
They will force the initialization
to have good values because your
object should be well initialized
so that you can avoid to use a value.
And then the logic, this is the
builder that we'll have to pay attention
and to be careful with the logic.
And like that, the default value,
they are not passed around.
They are just initialized.
From that perspective,
this is nice because often as a client,
I have no idea about if the object
that I have is good, is a good value
to be initialized.
So like that, this is the responsibility
of the object.
The builder is responsible to initialize
well the things and to be cautious.
The cons is that what you see is
that sometimes the message order
can be important.
And then in that case,
you will have to pay attention.
Maybe you can use configuration
with more than one argument and
things like that.
And there is really this need.
Often there is this need for a closing
message because else the builder
does not know, oh, do I need to
wait for an extra optional argument
or that my client will use or not?
So the builder need to know,
okay, now I can proceed.
I can take the configuration and
do something.
But for us, this is really just
the pay to price and the result
is much better.
So as a conclusion, what you see
is that in a fluid API,
you have three kinds of messages.
You have an object from that
perspective.
You have the container creator,
the setters that will let your client
configure your creator and a closer
that will say, okay, now I can do
something.
So fluid API are really nice when
you have many optional exclusive
parameters.
So I think that they are not used
enough and people don't know them.
So that's why we decided to include
this lecture in this MOOC.