Hello, in this lecture,
we will discuss about delegation
and inheritance.
So the goal of this lecture is to
analyze different designs of the
same system, some based on inheritance
and some based on delegation.
And the idea is to compare those
designs, given some criteria or hints,
to analyze which one is the best one.
So the exercise setup that we will
use is imagine that we want to design
a text editor with different algorithms
to format the text.
So how can we do that?
So perhaps we have some text formatting
for teX, or text formatting that is fast,
another text formatting that is
slow but very precise,
etc.
The agenda of this lecture will
be the following: we will do a first
design based on inheritance,
another design based on conditionals,
then we will define some criteria
to compare those solutions,
and we will then see a third solution
based on delegation and we will
evaluate.
So let's start with an inheritance
based solution.
So we will create a ‘TextEditor‘
class there, and this ‘TextEditor‘
will display the text that is stored
in this instance variable,
and we will have a format method there,
which is abstract in this case,
and we will have one subclass per
text formatting algorithm.
So for example, we could have
SlowFormattingTextEditor there,
and here we can implement it in
a separate method, and we can have
the FastFormattingTextEditor and
the NullFormattingTextEditor, for
example.
So it means that we can have different
‘TextEditors‘, each one specialized
in a specific algorithm.
Another solution using only one
class is the following:
so here we still have one ‘TextEditor‘
with a text to display in an instance
variable, but given a currentSelection
which stores a key, for example
here this is slow, given this key,
we will test, and we will directly
execute the right formatting algorithm.
For example,
FormatSlowButPreciseColoring, and
we give the text as a parameter.
We could even, with this single
class scenario, use meta-programming.
For example, if I want to avoid testing,
because now you know that explicit
(texting) in the clients is usually
not the best solution,
the idea is to have a list of formatters
here, and then I will store for each,
this is a dictionary,
and for each key I can store the
name of the selector that I should
apply to correctly format the text,
and in this format, I will perform,
so perform, this is the meta-programming
method, I will give the name of
the selector that I want to invoke,
and the parameter that I want to pass.
But this is exactly the same solution
as before.
So now, what are the criteria to
compare this kind of solution?
So first, the addition,
what is the cost of defining a new
formatting algorithm?
Is it easy?
Can I package different algorithms
in separate packages,
like that I can load them afterwards,
like plugins or something like that?
And finally, is it easy to dynamically
switch to another formatting algorithm?
So let's review the different solutions
given those criteria.
For example, the inheritance-based
solution: on the pro side,
this is easy to add a new formatting
algorithm because I just need to
add a new subclass, and this is
easy to package them separately,
so it means I can take one of those
classes, put it in a separate package,
and I can load it afterwards.
On the cons side, this is more difficult
to dynamically switch to another
formatting algorithm,
because if I instantiated my
‘TextEditor‘ at the beginning,
when I open it, it means that then,
when I want to change the formatting
algorithm, perhaps I will need to
close it and to recreate the instance.
So this is not convenient at all.
And another point here,
this is the addition.
So it was a pro, but it is also a con,
because there is a combinatorial
explosion that we will explain in
the next slide.
So here, if I have a lot of concerns
in my ‘TextEditor‘, for example,
I have a Single-Pane,
Multi-Pane ‘TextEditor‘,
I must take care of completion,
grammatical verification,
compilation, etc.
It means that I may end up with
a hierarchy like that.
So it means I will have the
SlowFormattingTextEditor, like before,
but then I need to have a subclass
for the single pane
SlowFormattingTextEditor.
And then I will have the
MultiPaneSlowFormattingTextEditor.
But I also have the
SpellMultiPaneSlowFormattingTextEditor.
And then you can see now the explosion.
So I will have a lot of subclasses
for each different concern that
I want to combine.
Moreover, the API of the text editor,
if I want to have a uniform API
for my clients, it means that it
may be not clear because everything
will be mixed up inside the text
editor class.
Now let's evaluate the
conditionals-based solution with
a single class.
On the pro side, it is really easy
to dynamically switch between one
formatting algorithm to another one.
But on the con side, this is more
difficult to add a new formatting
algorithm because I need to recompile
to edit and recompile the code that
is already written in a class.
And of course, since there is only
one class, this is difficult to
package them separately.
So now you can take one minute to
imagine a new solution using a
delegation.
So it means that inside your text
editor, you will delegate the formatting
algorithm to another object,
a formatter.
So here the solution is based on
the delegation.
So it means that in the format method
there, I will send the format message
to a formatter object.
And the formatter object,
now I have a setter in myEditor.
You can see it there.
And I can say, OK, the formatter
will be a FastFormatter.
And here you have a hierarchy.
There, this hierarchy,
that can be as complex as I want
of formatters.
And all those formatters are
polymorphic.
They all understand the format method.
So it means that now I can dynamically
change the formatter on myEditor.
And I just need to send the format
message to myEditor.
And myEditor will forward this message
to the formatter.
So now I have an extensible solution
by delegation.
So if I evaluate this solution,
so now the addition is easy.
It's just a matter of adding a new
subclass of the formatter.
Packaging is easy because I can
take some formatter class and put
it in a separate package.
This is easy to dynamically switch
to another formatting algorithm
because it's just a matter of using
the setter on my text editor.
And there is a uniform API between
the editors and the formatters.
This is the format message.
On the con side, the formatter should
access the state of the ‘TextEditor‘.
So it means that the text,
the position, and everything that
it contains in the ‘TextEditor‘
might be useful to the formatter
to correctly show the formatting text.
The API of the ‘TextEditor‘ should
be opened to support it.
So it means that it breaks a little
bit the encapsulation of the
‘TextEditor‘.
And this design is a perfect typical
example of the Strategy Design Pattern.
So as a conclusion, inheritance
is about incremental and static
definition.
It can lead to static design and
it helps defining abstractions.
But delegation on the other hand
brings runtime flexibility and
modularity.
But there is nothing such as a free
lunch.
So it means that both of them have
pro and cons.
And it means that you need to evaluate
what is best in your design.