- Hello, welcome to this presentation.
In this presentation,
we are going to see an application
of the Command Design Pattern.
The goals for this presentation
is to see the command design pattern
in action and see a specific framework
of Pharo that we use to implement
a more complex command design pattern.
Let's start with this example.
Well, we have Commander.
Commander is a framework of Pharo
that allows us to create actions
and commands for the user,
for our application.
It can produce toolbars and menus
and it has the ability to show our
actions in the UI, in the user
interface.
But this user interface is performed
in a way that is decoupled from
the command itself.
It's using decorators.
This is a good example of combining
two or more design patterns to get
a better solution.
As we can see, we will represent,
as it says in Command,
our operations with objects.
In this case, we are going to create
a new object of the class.
Add a contact in this simple example
where we have a phone book.
We are going to create two operations
where we can add a new contact or
remove it.
And basically, what we are going
to do is create a new command of
this class.
We are going to have a class for
each of these commands and we are
going to create it in a given context.
In this case, we are going to create
it in the context of aPresenter.
aPresenter, basically you can see
it as the context of the whole window
with the information inside,
with the widgets and the information
that is inside.
Once we have the object,
we can directly execute it.
But this way of using is not normally
what we are going to do.
We are not going to create the object
and directly execute it.
But we are going to create the command
and give it to the framework to
execute it when the user clicks
on the given option in the menu.
This execute is delayed from the
creation of the command.
We can see here a class diagram
of how Commander is structured.
We have a common abstract class
for all our commands that has the
common behavior and so we can reuse
the behavior.
All the commands can understand
a class method to create them,
call it for context, that receives
the context of execution.
It's important to see the API exposed
by the abstract superclass.
In this case, we have a method to
execute.
That is basically what we have in
all command design patterns.
But also, we can see that it has
the responsibility to know if it
can be executed in a given context.
For example, in the previous example,
we cannot remove the element from
the phone book if there is no one
that is selected.
So the command knows that is only
applicable when there is a valid
selection.
Then we have here a subclass,
a concrete subclass that we are
going to create to represent our
command.
Also, there is a useful helper class
that allows us to create easy commands
from blocks directly,
passing two blocks.
One block that is the block that
will be executed when this command
is executed, and another block that
will be evaluated when we ask the
operation if it can be executed
in the given code.
Usually, this is done for easy creating
commands.
But normally, what we want to do
is to create our commands as subclasses
of CmCommand because like that,
we can create our objects and add
instance variables and add the state
required for performing the action.
Also, we can see that we have two
parts in this diagram.
On the left, we have all the elements
that are proper to the command,
and on the right, we have a hierarchy
of decorators that allows us to
add more functionality to the previous
command.
For example, adding the ability
to have an icon or a shortcut key
when these commands are exposed
in a menu or in a toolbar.
Like this, we can see the two
responsibilities that we can have
in Commander and how we can compose
two different design patterns to
get to a complex solution,
to solve a complex problem,
not only to have a complex solution.
In this case, let's see our
AddContactCommand, what it will do.
Well, one of the properties that
we have in Commander is that we
want to have that all the commands
can describe themselves.
So each of them will have a name
and a description.
This information is important to
build the UI, so the user knows
what operations are there and how
to use them and what they are doing.
And this is provided by the framework.
Each of them will just give the
name and the description and the
framework will create the required
element in the user interface.
For example, that each of the menu
options will have a describing text
saying what it's doing and what
are the icon or the shortcut,
if it has.
As we can see, AddContactCommand
will have its execute method that
is what it's doing and it will perform
the action on the target object.
In this case, on the contact book,
on the phone book.
One important thing about Commander
is that we can extend it to have
specific requirements for each of
the commands.
We can have commands in this case,
in this little example,
we have commands that has been extended
to be part of a spec.
A spec is our framework to implement
the applications in top of Pharo
to implement the user interface
of applications.
And we can extend the commands in
a way just extending and adding
a new class that when we implement
applications in a spec,
they will instantiate,
will create classes extending from
StCommand.
As we see, we see here the extensibility
of this solution and how we can
extend the command design pattern
just adding new subclasses to the
abstract or to the concrete command
class.
The same happens with the decorator
part.
We can start adding a new decorator
that will take one of the commands
and will wrap it and will be able
to create the buttons in the toolbar.
Like this, we can see that the original
framework does not know about the
existence of spec, but this is added
through the points of extension.
Now we can see that we have added
to command a way to create it as
a spec command and we are going
to do that taking exactly the existing
command and just decorating them
with SpCommand.
And in this case, it will add the
idea of having an icon and having
a shortcut to execute it.
This is an interesting way of extending
the commands that we have with new
functionality, adding in this case
a default icon and a default shortcut.
Let's see how we implement one of
these commands with all the flavors.
Well, basically we do exactly the
same because the extension is
transparent to it and the command
still only knows how to execute
in a given context.
They have a really simple execute
command.
That is what we want to have,
a simple and a well-distributed
responsibility.
Coming back from all these ideas,
we can say that commands are first
class actions.
Remember that we want to take our
actions and create objects that
represent them.
So we can manipulate them and delay
the execution and perform undo,
replay, optimization,
show them in a list or render them
through the UI.
The commands are elements in our
system and we want to handle them.
This is important also that you
check the lecture about the command
design pattern to see the consequences
of using it and when we want and
when we don't want to use it.