Stéphane Ducasse - Welcome everybody.
So in this little lecture,
I would like to discuss with you
some aspects of design on form
validation and what it means in
terms of tree traversal or object
traversal, accumulator,
how we can distribute the knowledge
of the validation of a system.
So this is not a design pattern.
This is not a coding medium.
This is more a discussion around
variation and a design point.
So the objective, this is to think
of object, of course,
but also about structure traversal
and distribution of behavior,
as well as to look at as object
as accumulator in the sense of,
okay, I can have an object that
is a basket in which other object
plays a result.
So what you see is that here on
the screen, this is a screenshot
of the Iceberg Git support in Pharo
and you can select different ways
of cloning or accessing your code.
And then here, each of these selections
will bring a different form.
Basically, behind the scene,
you don't see it, but there is an
option pane that will contain different
fields.
And then the question,
this is how can I help the user
not introducing mistake?
So this means that the form should
validate the input.
Now, the question that we can ask
ourselves, this is who is responsible
for doing the validation?
Is it a single field or is it this
group that should manage the semantic?
And when I report, should I report
here at this level?
And when I press OK, what should I do?
So this is what I would like to
discuss and how to model these kinds
of things.
So basically, to answer this question,
we should think about how do we
navigate a tree of instance?
Can we get children that decide
that they don't care or yes,
this is my report?
What do we report also?
For example, what is the validation?
What the validation should report?
Should it report a yes,
no?
So the yes is easy because everything
works well, but the no is less easy
because if a user mistypes something,
we would like to give a good feedback
to the user.
We would like to say to the user,
okay, the file that you entered
is not valid.
It should end up with dot an extension,
the correct extension or these kinds
of things.
So basically, what we see from that
perspective is that
yes/no cannot really work because we
want to have a more semantic of
the mistake.
So when I said that we have a tree,
you have the option pane and it
contains other widgets,
in fact several other widgets.
So we already have a tree and it
can be a lot more complex than that.
Now, in a form design,
what we could have is that we could say,
any presenter, so the elementary
widget in the tree can be responsible
to validate its contents.
So we could have, for example,
a method that is called isValidate
where by default it returns true
and a report like that.
We could say, the widget could say,
oh, was my input correct?
Yes, no.
Or and then what should we do in
terms of mistake and by sending
a report and by default,
the report could be okay,
I am the 'OkReport' like a neutral
operation in math, a bit in the same idea.
And then, for example,
the input field that will be specialized
for the path could say,
oh, you know, I already find the
method is valid by checking is my
input field: contents is really ending
with the right extension,
for example.
And then, the report in that case
would be okay, if there is something
wrong, then I create a report and
I said I was expecting a git and
you give me something that doesn't
terminate.
So please fix it.
With that kind of report,
the user interface could be a special
another user interface that would
display the error to the user in
a nice way.
And what we could do also is that
the OptionPresenter, the one that
contains the other fields, in that case,
could said, oh, you know,
I am valid if all my children are valid.
The all satisfied means all the
children should be valid and the
report the OptionPresenter could decide,
okay, I create a report.
I iterate over my children and I
will collect basically their reports.
I said, okay, if a child is not valid,
then please add the report to the
report.
Like that at the end,
we would have a report with all
the mistakes done in the form,
because usually on long form you
get a lot of mistakes.
So what you see that the flow is
basically like that.
It goes from the option pane,
the container to each of his children.
And during this flow,
to have a report, we need to know
if the validation failed or not.
We ask, okay, okay, okay.
The question we could ask ourselves,
oh, maybe isValid could have written
a report.
We don't know.
And what is clear is that isValid
returns the report, then in that case,
we should have a okay or not okay
report and things like that.
By the way, this is a design like
that that is done to validate the
Pharo books.
We want to know if a book is correct
from a Pharo version.
We execute all the tests and then
we have a kind of okay or fail test
and they accumulate over the execution.
This is a bit in the same way.
Now what you see that graphically,
by the way, during the flow,
I will always ask, is it okay?
Give me a report.
Is it okay?
And now, we could have also another
design, which is okay,
I will navigate the element structure
and pass a basket.
That is basically I said,
hey, you know, if you have a report,
please add it to this basket.
And like that, we don't have to ask.
We just said, can you validate yourself
into that? An element that does not
have a problem, does not have to
say if it is valid or not.
If it does not add a report,
then it is valid.
And if it has a report,
then there is a problem.
This design would be like that.
We could say, okay, validate into
a report and by default do nothing.
And then, for containers and if,
the PathPresenter will just say,
okay, in the report, please add
this for self path.
And probably, you should say that
this is a mistake on self and probably
not said path, but on self,
so that the user interface can pinpoint
and put in red the right field.
Then what the OptionPresenter would
do is that the OptionPresenter get
a report and he just pass it to
these children.
If he want to do it via the children,
he could also say, no,
I decide to do it in another way.
So I wanted with this little
presentation to show example where
we can question interrogative form
and we can play with different design.
We can let the user decide if he
wants to join a process or so.
And we can also potentially have
double dispatch between the report
and the container.
And in this lecture what I like
is that nothing is black and white.
You know, we have some lecture where
we said, okay, this design is bad
or not good and this one is much better.
Here, this is unclear.
So this is a really important aspect
of object-oriented design is that
you should model things and you
should see what is your client and
and how does it fit, how your design
fit with the client that you have
and the problem that you have.
So that's why this is important
to explore design.
So we don't have a predefined way
to solve the problem that I show.
But I really like the idea that,
in fact, we can ask the receiver
to get a value or we can also do
not care of the value,
but pass a container in which the
value get accumulated.
And this is interesting to see that
sometimes, especially on recursive
structure, passing a container to
collect information can be a good
design.