Pablo Tesone - Hello,
welcome to this lecture.
In this lecture, we are going to
talk About Null Check and how it
is used in the case of Lazy
Initialization.
We are going to think about the
initialization of an object,
what happens when we create a new
object.
We are going to present the idea
of lazy initialization and this
lecture is a complement to 'Avoid
Nil' lecture.
It's suggested that you can review
also this lecture to get the whole
idea and the whole picture of the
subjects that we are presenting.
What is the problem that we are
attacking today?
Well, we need to reduce the startup
time or the time that we take to
create a new instance of an object.
What can have this impact in the
startup time?
When we initialize a lot of instance
variables and we need to do a lot
of calculations and allocate a lot
of objects that are referred from
our object, we can take a lot of
time and we can take a lot of memory.
And there is another situation is
that we are forced from the beginning
to initialize all the object,
all the state of our instance when
we create it.
So what is the solution?
We want to see how we can do less
of this work in the beginning,
in the initialization.
Our solution or the idea that we
are presenting in this lecture is
only to perform the initialization
of the state that we are going to use.
We are going to only calculate this
new state or this state that we
are going to initialize when we use it.
And this will produce that it will
only be used, it will only be calculated
when we are using it without needing
to do it before.
So we are delaying the initialization
of our objects until it's really needed.
So this is the general strategy
that we are going to do.
We are going to instantiate our
object and let all the instance
variables that are difficult to
initialize in nil.
And then, when we are going to use
this instance variable,
we want to give it a value.
How do we do so?
Well, we are going to not access
the instance variable directly.
This is important.
It's an important thing that we
will have to have in mind.
We are not going to use the variable
directly, but we are going to use
an accessor method to access them.
Also an important thing is that
in the initialization time,
we are not going to do anything
in the initialization time because
it's what we want really to do.
In our accessors, we are going to
do some kind of little work extra
that we don't usually.
Usually, when we write an accessor,
a method that access the value of
a given instance variable,
we just implement this part,
returning the value.
In this case, we are going also
to check if the instance variable
is nil and if it's nil,
we are going to give to it a default
value like in this case.
This is a really small example,
but we are going to see that this
can get more and more complex and
when it's getting complex is where
it gets more and more powerful.
For example, in this other example,
we have a better use of the lazy
initialization.
Basically, we have a complex calculation
to get the value of our instance
variable.
As we can see, it's sending messages,
it's doing arithmetic operations
and this can take time to execute
and time to calculate.
So we want to really do it only
if we really need it.
So we see the same pattern of our
accessor in our lazy accessor,
we have the normal accessor to the
variable, but if it is nil,
we do the assignation with the value
that we are calculating.
In this way, we only execute the
complex and expensive calculation
when we really need it.
Other thing to have in clear is
that we are storing this value in
the instance variable.
So the second time that we access
the instance variable through the
accessor, we already have the value
calculated.
This idea of using lazy initialization
can allow us to defer the initialization
and store the results.
In this way, we delay the execution
of expensive code to calculate the
values and also we cache them to
be used later.
One big problem or one big constraint
of this solution is that we never
should access directly the instance
variable.
We always need to use the accessor.
If we are not doing so,
we are in the risk of exposing a
nil value and we will break all
the idea of having lazy initialization.
So the good thing about lazy
initialization is that we can cache
the values and defer the initialization
until we need it, but the cost is
that we use always the lazy accessor.
What are the good things of this?
Well, as I said before,
we can avoid the creation or the
calculation of a complex object
until the time we really need it.
But there is always a trade off.
So if we use lazy initialization,
we will perform a check for nil
every time that we access the instance
variable through the lazy accessor.
As a conclusion, we can say that
lazy initialization is another tool
that we have to have in our toolbox,
but we don't have to overuse it.
It's good when we are having objects
that have some instance variables
that we don't use all the time,
but also they are complex or expensive
to calculate.
So we can defer the initialization
until the moment we use it.