Hello, in this lecture,
we will discuss a specific point,
the ‘DieHandle‘ new vs ‘self‘ class new,
and the fact that you should never
hardcode class name in your code.
Before starting, let's have a look,
let's remember that ‘self‘ always
represents the receiver of the message,
and classes are regular objects
in Pharo and you can send them messages
too.
So in this example, we are using
a plus message that we send to a
‘DieHandle‘ object, and this message
is important because it allows us
to sum objects, dice in fact.
And you have the implementation
of this method here, and now let's
analyze what happens if we do a
subclass of ‘DieHandle‘.
If I do a ‘MemoDieHandle‘,
which is a subclass of ‘DieHandle‘,
and then I send the plus message
to an instance of this subclass,
in fact what happens is that we
will get back a ‘DieHandle‘ instance,
instead of a ‘MemoDieHandle‘.
This is because the plus method
that is selected by the lookup is
the one inherited from ‘DieHandle‘,
the superclass, and it always returns
a ‘DieHandle‘ object,
because the name of the class is
hardcoded in the code of the plus
method.
So what we can do about that is
that we can extract this code in
a hook method like we saw in a previous
lecture.
So here, we extract it in a
‘handleClass‘ method,
and we implement it like that,
return ‘DieHandle‘.
And the good thing about that is
that it means that in a subclass,
‘MemoDieHandle‘, now we can redefine
this method and we can directly
return a ‘MemoDieHandle‘.
So now it means that if I send the
message plus to a ‘MemoDieHandle‘,
I will get back a ‘MemoDieHandle‘.
So now it's correct.
So from the extensibility point of view,
this is a really nice solution because
now I can provide new subclasses,
I can redefine this hook,
and I can specify which kind of
instance should be returned.
But the drawback is that if a
subclass is defined but does not
redefine this hook, if the developer
forgets about it, it means that
it will be the wrong instance that
will be returned.
So we can do better.
And a better solution is this one.
Instead of hardcoding directly the
name of the class inside the handle
class method, it means that I can
return the ‘self‘ class,
the class of the receiver.
And it means that now it will be
always the class of the receiver
that is returned.
And it is dynamic.
It means that according to the receiver,
it will be the class of the receiver
that will be returned.
So it means that it is the same
kind of the receiver that will be
treated automatically with one
implementation in the ‘DieHandle‘ class.
It will behave correctly for all
subclasses.
So as a summary, first of all,
do not hardcode class names in your
code, never.
At least, provide a hook, like that
subclasses can redefine it and
specify which kind of instances
they want.
But a better solution,
if your language supports it,
such as Pharo, is to directly provide
a good default implementation by
returning the class of the receiver
using ‘self‘ class.
Like that, you will directly get
the right instances in subclasses.
And this is an extensible solution
by default.