Hi, in this lecture, we are going
to revisit `super` to see if you
really understood in the previous
lectures.
So we will revisit `super`,
we will also review message lookup
and we are going to see really briefly
what are class methods.
So let's start with a little puzzle.
So we have the Die class.
It's a class method that is redefining
new.
And this method is calling `super new`,
getting some instance here and then
calling the initialize method.
So sending the message initialize
on the instance.
Now we execute the Die new expression.
Some questions: what is `inst` in here?
What is `super` and what is `super new`?
Take a couple of minutes,
try to understand this scenario
and try to write down the answers
to these questions.
We are going to visit them in a
couple of seconds.
Put pause to the video.
So some hints: `super` is not the
superclass.
Remember that before,
when we saw `super`, `super` was
never the superclass of the object,
and it was never the `superclass`
of anything, It's neither the instance
of a superclass or the instance
of the superclass of whatever.
Also remember that `super` is the
message receiver.
So that means that somehow,
`super` and self are the same object.
They reference the same object.
Remember also that the message that
we are sending, we are activating,
is `Die new`.
So think about that.
What is the selector that we're sending?
What is the message and what is
a receiver of this message?
So in this case, the receiver is
the class Die.
So we are not sending the message
to a normal object, a common object,
we're sending a message to a class
which is a special object in the
language.
Remember how method lookup works.
So if we have an object,
in this case aColoredRectangle,
and we send a message,
like in this case area.
First what we're going to do is
the lookup.
So step number one, here,
if we take the receiver,
which is aColoredRectangle,
and take its class, which is the
ColoredRectangle class,
we're going to start the lookup from
there.
So starting from the class,
we're going to go up in the hierarchy
looking for the method that corresponds
with the expected selector.
So here, we are looking for area.
So ColoredRectangle doesn't define
area but Rectangle does.
So it doesn't find it in
the ColoredRectangle subclass,
it will go up and find it in the
Rectangle class.
It will take that method and then
the second step of the message send
is to execute that method on the
receiver.
So we are going to take area and
execute width multiplied by height
on the colored rectangle,
our instance that is down here.
So in here, what happens again is that
we're going to take this message
and really it's a two-step.
So the method lookup is first taking
the class and then going up.
So it's super important to understand
that it's first taking the class
then going up the hierarchy looking
for the method, and then the final
step of the message send,
after the lookup is done in these
two steps is executing the method
on the instance.
So the solution of the previous
puzzle is that here, `super` is,
of course, the same object as `self`.
So if self was the Die class,
the class Die, `super` is also the
Die class.
So `super` and self are the same
and `super` is also the receiver.
What does `super new` do?
So `super new` will do a message
send to `super`, which in this case
is a Die class, but it will change
the method lookup.
If you remember, when we used `super`,
what happened was that the method
lookup was changed and the lookup
started from a different place.
In this case, actually every time,
it will start from the superclass
of the class where the current method
is defined.
So here in this case,
this method is defined in Die class.
So the method lookup,
it will start from the superclass.
It doesn't matter which one it is.
So it will always restart the lookup
from the superclass of the current
class.
So it doesn't matter if the object
is an instance of any other class,
any other subclass.
It will always start from the direct
superclass of `Die class`.
Now, once we find that method `super
new`, the new that is probably up
in the hierarchy, we're going to
apply it to the current instance.
So that means that we're going to
apply it to the current Die class.
Execute a new on a class will return
us a new instance of that class.
So once we have the Die class,
we're going to instantiate it and
that will create a Die instance.
That means that our instance variable
is going to point to a die object,
which is the one that will receive
the message initialize,
so we're going to send the message
initialize to this guy,
the die object, and, then we're
returning that instance.
With the drawing, what we see is
that actually, what happens here
is that we have a double hierarchy.
This happens in reflective languages
such as Pharo, Python or Ruby,
where we have our classes,
Dice, Object, and since classes
are also objects, they also have
their own classes.
So here, the Dice class has its
own class, which is a Dice meta class.
And the same happens with object
class. So every time that I'm going
to send a message to a dice object,
the lookup will look for the class,
which will be this one,
and then go up in the hierarchy.
In our case here, since we're sending
the message to the Dice class,
we are going to look for its class
and then go up its hierarchy.
It's just the same mechanism as before.
The only thing is that we are thinking
about classes and the classes of
classes instead of just the classes
of normal objects.
In summary, sending a message,
again, is always looking up the
correct method and then applying
it to the receiver.
That never changes.
Now, when we use `super` instead
of any other message send,
what happens is that the method
lookup will start in a different place.
It will start from the superclass
of the class where the current method
or the current expression is declared.
You should also remember that `super`
and self are the same object.
Both represent the receiver of the
current message. And the only thing
that changes is the method lookup,
where it starts.
Before leaving you, I leave you
with this challenge: take a couple
of minutes and challenge yourself.
So imagine that you have this,
you have a method `a foo` in the class A,
and you do super class equals self class.
Remember that class is just a message
that eventually will return the
class of the receiver and equals
equals is the identity,
so you will compare if the two compared
objects are the same object.
Not if they're equals,
but they are actually the same object.
So what does this return,
true or false?
I leave you with that.