- Hello everybody.
So welcome to this new lecture.
So in this lecture, this is an analysis
of a case study of a change that
we really put in production in Pharo.
And the idea is to show how we introduce
delegation of behavior to obtain
a more modular system.
So what we will see in this lecture,
we will look at the class definition
printer, check the design in Pharo,
and it will help us also to think
modular.
So let's look at the context and
the challenges that we faced.
One of the key questions in Pharo
was how to support various class
definition formats and in a modular way.
But this means without having to
check everywhere, everything.
So when I said various formats,
in fact, we have the old Squeak
syntax format, the old Pharo definition
and the Fluid syntax that we saw
in the fluid lecture.
In addition, so we have various formats,
but we have also various objects.
So this means that we have class,
metaclass, traits, the class side
of traits.
And the key question now,
this is how do we control this
complexity?
Because, for example,
a slot first class instance variable
should not be displayed in Old Pharo
nor in Squeak, but they should be
displayed in the Fluid syntax.
And the point of all this,
this is how can we do that without
having checks everywhere?
And in addition, can we have a modular
system where we can remove one
definition at any time?
So let's see how it was done before.
So in Pharo 7 or 8, in fact,
there was a first introduction of
slots and it was hacked basically,
it was working, but it was a bit
hackish.
So you see, so for example,
in the definition of the class
description, so class description
in the superclass of class and
metaclass, we had a method that
was called definition.
And then, it was checking,
oh, do I need to have a slot?
And should I show the slot?
If this is the case, then I will
have a definition with slot.
Else, I have a definition without slot.
And guess what?
The same in metaclass,
we have checks there.
And as you can imagine,
we have also checks inside,
for example, the classTemplate.
So this means that when you were
defining a new class,
the system would do again this condition
to produce the correct one here
with slot and the other one with
instance variable names.
So this means that you imagine that
plus fluid in the middle,
okay, it was not working,
it was not scaling.
So now, what I suggest is that take
five minutes, press Pause on this video,
take five minutes to see how you
would solve it.
So what is the solution?
So what you saw is that at the beginning
of the lecture, we already said
that sending a message is making
a choice, but to be able to send
a message, we need class so that
we could have instance of different
classes where we could send messages
and those messages would select
different methods.
So this is what we will do here.
In fact, we will create class hierarchy
of printers where we have,
for example, the
FluidClassDefinitionPrinter, the
LegacyClassDefinitionPrinter, and
the OldPharoClassDefinitionPrinter.
And basically, this is a kind of
strategy and the class will delegate
to the printer for its own printing.
So we will have a system where we
have the class, or you will see
this is a bit more complex,
but let's think that this is simple
like that now, where we have this
hierarchy of printer here,
and then we delegate and at runtime,
depending on the printer that we select,
we will get the correct one.
So let's go a bit in details.
What is it?
So if you imagine, so a tool,
for example, here will send a message
and we will execute this method,
definitionString.
So what the definitionString will
do is that it will create an adequate
printer, an instance of these three
classes, and then it will ask,
oh, can you give me the
definitionString?
And each of these class will return,
oh yes, for example, the
LegacyDefinitionPrinter knows how
to define, how to print a class,
how to print a metaclass,
how to print a trait,
the same way the
FluidClassDefinitionPrinter knows
how to print a class,
a metaclass, a trait,
and so on.
And what you see that here,
basically the definitionString is
first creating a printer.
So this printer will return one
of these instances, and then we
send the definitionString.
The definitionString,
this is not written on the diagram,
will call the corresponding string
methods that we have here.
We will see that in a moment.
So basically, this is what I just said.
So we have two methods here,
the definitionString method that
will return the actual string.
And to do that, it will first create
an instance of a printer calling
these methods.
And these methods basically said,
okay, given this entity,
I want to have a printer for this
entity.
Since class description is the root
of hierarchy, you will see that
we will have here potentially self
is a class or a metaclass.
It's also a trait.
So this is a variation point that
we will see later.
And once I have this printer,
I just send the printer,
the definitionString to this printer.
So let's step back.
A printer knows how to print a class,
a metaclass, a trait.
So let's look at this to make it
more concrete.
For example, the fluid class printer
will know how to print a class like
that, a metaclass like this.
And here you see, for example,
the class definition.
It create a stream and then he will
check if this is a new superclass.
It will put nil then after he will
compose the message like that.
And then, it will check in the slots
and things.
And finally create the package.
For the metaclass definition,
this is the same logic,
but to really produce a different,
a different setup.
For example, what is interesting
is that in Old Pharo format,
we don't want to display slots.
We decided that they should not
be displayed to simplify the system.
And here this means that this is
this printer that encapsulates this
logic.
So here it said, okay,
given a class that I should print,
I will ask the class,
do you need a slot definition?
If you don't need it,
I will just print a basic definition.
If you do it, then I will create
a different printer and ask this
different printer for the definition.
So this means that here,
this is this printer that,
that encapsulates and controls the
logic and not the tools or anything.
So now, what we see is that for
the classTemplate, the logic is
much simpler.
We said, okay, I want a class
definition.
I want to have a compact,
the compact template,
for example.
And that's it.
And I give the name and I get the
printer depending on in which format
I am.
I don't have to do checks here.
So if we see we have one format,
one printer, the printer can support
multiple related features.
So like expansion.
So I did not explain what is expansion,
but if you have a partial class
definition and you want to see all
the parameters that you want,
you could say, oh, please class
definition, can you expand and show
me all the possible variation that
I have the template, the template
that you see in the debugger and
the actual class printing.
And there is a support also of reuse
within the hierarchy of the printer
and the possibility to have a default
way of managing printers.
For example, if I have a problem,
the legacy will just say,
no, I don't know how to do it,
you have to use a free printer and
like that we will support also the
evolution of the domain and the
language from that perspective.
So, but there is more.
In fact, we have more challenges
than that.
So this means that for now we have
multiple printer, but in fact,
we should support different entities
printed by different printers.
So at the end, we will have class
description, which has metaclass,
class and potentially traits.
I don't remember exactly if this is that,
but I think that this is like that
and the printer.
So here I have another hierarchy
of printer here.
And the question this is,
I want, for example, to be able
to print a class in the Old format
or a class in the Fluid format or
a trait in the old format,
so I have all the combination.
So how do we do that?
I think that normally you should
have really an idea now.
This is like if we need to select
one method based on two things.
So the solution here,
this is double dispatch.
Let's look at it.
So, so you remember, so the
definitionString was basically called
and what we see is that here definition
string will ask, we said,
oh, in fact, I will not decide.
I will just ask the class,
hey class, can you give me the
definition string for myself because
I am a printer.
So if I am fluid, because each
printer knows how to print things.
So this printer, they know how to
print metaclass, class,
traits, class, metaclass,
traits, and so on.
But I don't know when to invoke
these methods.
So now what I do. I just said,
okay, can you just, I ask the class
or the entity because this entity
can be a class, a metaclass or a trait.
I said entity or for class here.
Can you give me the correct one?
And then, I will have this dispatch.
So when I am a class,
I will have the class,
oh, display me as a class.
When this is a metaclass,
I would say the printer,
oh there is a bug here.
This is metaclass should say metaclass.
And when this is a trait,
print me as a trait.
So what you see is that we have
a double dispatch.
And in fact, this is exactly the
same as in the visitor design pattern.
So we should think that this is
a visitor, for example.
So this means that I am the object
knowing how to do things.
And here class description with
my hierarchy.
This is a bit like my composite.
It's not really the idea of the
composite, but in the visitor design
pattern that we presented with the
composite.
So this means that this visitor
will visit this structure using
double dispatch.
And the key point, this is in this
method where you see,
so this is not the argument that
we dispatch on, but we dispatch
on an instance variable that has
been set before.
So here you have all the code basically.
And you see, okay, I will select
the correct definition each time.
You see here, I even showed a
traitedMetaclass because this is
the one case that I didn't show you,
but this is exactly the same all
the time the same design.
The printer, the entity is requested
and it has the print,
he said to the printer,
yes, I want to be displayed as a class,
as a trait or as a traitedMetaclass.
But there is more.
In fact, we don't want to have direct
references to printer in all the code.
Why?
Because we want to be able to remove
printers.
In fact, in Pharo, we don't want
to have a 20 different class definitions.
We want to have one that is fluid.
We just want to make sure that we
have package that can be loaded
by our client, so that they can
manage all code if they want.
So the idea, this is really that
it should be optional.
So the design here, and you saw
it a bit in the previous slide,
this is that we only reference the
superclass that acts as a factory.
So let's look at it.
So I have the ClassDefinitionPrinter,
which is the root of the hierarchy.
You see it has an instance variable
for the knowing on what class it
should print and some sharedVariable
to be able to know what we should
show or not, depending on the system.
And then the new here,
the new method will check,
oh, if I am configured to display
information in fluid,
then I will return an instance of
my subclass that is the
FluidClassDefinitionPrinter.
Else, I will return the oldPharo
version.
So this means that basically what
you have is that you have your
hierarchy.
All the clients here will only refer
to this guy and never to the instance.
But this guy here, the
ClassDefinitionPrinter will create
instances of each subclass,
either this one or that one,
or even when we ask the legacy,
it will return an instance of the
legacy.
And this means that like that,
I can just plug or unplug,
for example, I can remove the legacy
if I want from the system.
So for example, how this is done,
the oldDefinition, I would say,
okay, ClassDefinitionPrinter legacy
for self class DefinitionString.
It will return me the definition
of the class as in the old version.
But this means that I can remove
these methods and I have no problem.
So as a conclusion, this is another
example of how we can dispatch an
object to avoid condition and what
it adds, it adds also the idea of
how do we manage the creation of
the correct object.
If you want to know more,
what I suggest is that you really
look at the Pharo code because this
is in production and it took us
some time to really get it nicely done.
And this is nice because it already
supports these three different class
definitions and it is helping us
to migrate where we want over the
different versions of Pharo.