Welcome to this lecture about builder
API variations.
We are going to analyze how to build
a nice API for our builders.
The goal for this lecture is to
identify and understand the different
variations that we can have in our
builder API and what are the
consequences of choosing one way
or another.
Let's start with our example of
Microdown.
Microdown is a markdown language,
is a compact subset of it and it
has more extensions or is more
extensible.
We can add specific extensions to
Microdown to allow us for representing
more elements than markdown.
We use it in Pharo for documenting
a lot of elements, especially for
class `comments`, but also is used
outside to generate slides,
books, documentation in general.
As an example here of the writing,
we can see that this is an evolution
of a markdown with some little
additions.
We can see the text.
It generates a text that has a
list that has definitions for slides,
bullets, and so on.
So it's a nice extension to markdown
and we use it in Pharo for generating
our class `comments`.
Like that, we can put rich text
in our class `comments`,
like for example, code blocks or
having a style for our selectors
or having links to other classes,
to other elements.
We have a way of creating default
class `comment`.
We can generate this class `comment`
from the analysis of the class,
for example, showing which are the
messages it understands,
how it is created.
And also we have a way of extending
that and specializing it for some
specific classes.
In this case, we are analyzing the
`comment` of the ButtonPresenter
that is one of the elements of a spec,
our UI framework, and in this one
we are provided different parts
when generating this markdown `comment`.
These `comments` are generated by
our code and it's nice to have different
elements.
In this case, for example,
we have a code block,
we have links, we have examples
and so on that is generated from
the metadata in the class.
Another example, when we have a
baseline that is a description of
our projects, we render the `comment`
in a different way, showing different
information.
This Microdown is generated
programmatically, but with a lot
of nice features.
One of the best features is that
we don't care about doing concatenation
of strings.
Concatenating strings is always
a problem, it's complex to maintain,
it's complex to handle and we always
have issues with syntax and if the
syntax changes in the future,
it's always worse.
And also, when we want the users
to use Microdown, we don't want
them to learn all the syntactic
quirks and the syntactic usage of
Microdown.
So it's better to provide a nice
builder API.
Why?
Because we want to abstract the
users from the details of what is
building and to support future change.
Also, we want to have a way of extending
this so anybody that is implementing
a new hierarchy in Pharo can extend
that, a new class in Pharo can extend
the method build Microdown using
`comment` colon to add a new ways
of generating these `comments`,
this documentation.
We can see that this hook is used
when we want to render a `comment`,
we delegate to the class or the
package and we send the message
to generate this `comment` and then
it is rendered by Microdown to show
it in the tools in Pharo.
The default implementation just
takes the builder, creates a header,
with the class, string class colon,
string and the name of the class.
And then, each puts a horizontal
line and the `comment` written by
the programmer of the class.
This is the basic implementation.
Again, anybody can extend this.
In this example, we are seeing the
extension done by spec,
our UI framework that basically
will do the same that is done in
the superclass, the same that is
done in the base case,
but then it starts adding its own
section.
It will have a section with the
code for the examples,
a section with how to create these
objects and then it has extra sections
and it allows to describe all the
elements that we want in our
documentation.
We see the same is done in the case
of the baseline.
In the baseline, we want to print
the dependencies and it's exactly
the same idea.
We are overriding this method and
adding the specific behavior to
create the documentation that we want.
This builder API for Microdown is
always based in the concepts that
the user wants from a Microdown,
talks about `text`, talks about
the styles, talks about `anchors`,
`codeblocks`, `comments`,
etc.
These concepts are the concepts
that are important for the user
and a concept that are important
to generate the Microdown page.
When we are generating the leaf
element in our document like a text
or a new line or a horizontal line,
we are just passing the argument
and we are just taking the simple
order in which they are created.
We are just accumulating the text
one after the other.
For example, if we do execute in
this order, first in the document
will appear the text `bold` and
then the new line.
The `codeblocks`, of course,
they are also a leaf element and
we can create them directly talking
to the builder.
We want a `codeblock` and we pass
the Pharo code that we want to show.
The most interesting part of the
builder is when we start having
composite and nested elements because
one of the natures of a Microdown
document is that it's a nested model.
We will have a style that is applied
to another style that is applied
to a text or a heading that has
a text inside or a list that has
elements inside and each element
can have text and so on.
So there is a nature of nested elements.
So how does it work, the API of
Microdown of this?
Well, it uses blocks to support
the wrapping of elements,
to support the nesting of elements.
In this case, as we see,
the API is easy to understand that
we are creating an element that
will give the style `bold` and this
`bold` will be applied to all the
content of this block.
In this case, will be applied to
the text that we have inside.
The same happens when we have two
levels of nesting.
We have a `bold` element that will wrap
an italic element that will wrap
the text producing that our text
at the end is in `bold` and `italic`.
This pattern is also used when we
have headers, when we have titles
because we want to put in the title
a text that maybe has `bold` content
and we see in this example,
that is the same idea.
The header will wrap everything
that is inside our block.
We have here a really nice example
again, where we have a cell.
A cell in our table will contain
everything that is in our block.
And in the creation of this cell,
we are going to create a cell wrapping
a text and a ceiling of that will
be a `bold` element wrapping another
text.
And as we see, it generates the text,
but we don't care.
We don't care what is the Microdown
string generated.
For the users, we care about how
to talk to the builder.
How to talk just in the elements,
in the sense that we want to present
to the users.
Let's see two alternative designs
that we can use in this kind of APIs,
this kind of API for builder.
In this case, we have the same idea
in the two examples, but take a
minute to understand what is the
difference.
In this one, we can see that the
difference between one and the other
is the presence or not of a builder
argument in the block.
Let's analyze the one when we don't
have this builder parameter and
we use exactly the same builder.
As we see, this way of writing is
more compact.
So we are really having an easier
way of writing this API for the user.
That is a really good point.
And the other consequence is that
we are reusing the same builder
object inside and outside the block.
So in this case, if we want to have
specific operations that are only
valid inside a header,
we need to put it always there.
All this builder should understand
all the possible messages that we
can send to it.
Continuing with more detail about
this implementation, if we see how
it works, basically in this
API it's easy when we have `bold`
receiving a block in this case,
remember we have something like
our builder, `bold`, our block.
And then, we have here,
for example, `text`.
In this case, what we are going
to do to wrap it in the correct
generation, we are going to execute
the start of the `BoldMarkup`.
Then we are going to evaluate the
block and execute the content of it.
And then finally, we are going to
finish the block body.
So in this way, the builder is who
is responsible of executing the
content of the block when it's needed,
to evaluate the block when it's
needed in the correct moment.
And the good thing of this is that
it really compacts the syntax,
but as an implication,
there is only one builder.
It's exactly the same builder in
the two parts.
Let's see what happen when we have
a parameter, the builder as parameter
of our blocks.
One first consequence is that we
have to write a little more for
the users have to write a little more,
but the nice part of it is that
we can have two different instances
of builder.
One builder that is the general
builder and one builder that is
only applicable when we are inside
a header.
We can have a header element builder,
for example.
So like this, we can have a hierarchy
of builders and each builder can
have a more refined API that is
only applied in this context.
As I said before, this is more verbose
and for the user requires to write
it more.
If you see how does it work,
it works in the same way.
We are going to do whatever we need
to do before the block.
And then, we are going to evaluate
the block that we receive,
but in this case with a different
builder that we are using and this
special builder will have a special
API depending on the context that
we have.
So like that we can have a hierarchy
of builder and each one can be
specialized for a given task.
Let's analyze a little this,
this variation in the API.
When we can do an explicit argument
builder, when we pass the argument,
the builder as argument,
we can have subclasses and we can
have a more specific APIs in the
subclass.
Also, it allows us to write in a
DSL fashion in a way that the user
cannot produce invalid calls.
Imagine in the Microdown example,
that a list `item` should be always
inside a list, if we are creating
a builder for each context,
we can validate that,
in the case of having it in a single
builder implementation,
we will need to put a more conditional
code and check if we are in the
correct context.
It works in this way,
we can have specific builders to
provide us with more and more features.
For example, we can have specific
builders for some part of the document,
or we can extend them for some part
of the document, like for example,
to generate a table of contents.
And it feels more like a visitor
and we will have different behavior.
The consequences of this design
having the explicit argument is
that we need to write more code
and we have to add an extra parameter
to all the wrapping blocks and the
wrapping APIs.
As a conclusion of this,
none of the solution is better.
It depends on the problem that we
are challenging and we need to decide
which one to use.
As always, the design is a task
that requires to take a trade-off,
that requires to analyze advantages
and disadvantages of a solution.
And we also need to always think
about the extensibility points that
our solution will provide.