Hello, welcome to this lecture.
In this lecture, we are going to
analyze the builder design pattern.
We are going to present how to
encapsulate object creation in our
builder object.
The goals for this lecture is to
present a little motivation example,
then we are going to describe the
builder design pattern and we are
going to see some uses and which
is the power of the builder design
pattern in action.
Well, what is the objective of the
builder pattern?
The idea is that we are going to
create an object, our builder,
that will help us to create a complex
set of objects.
Usually, creating objects start
to get more and more complex when
we have more and more interaction
between these objects.
When we create a graph of objects
and these objects start having reference
between each other, it's more and
more complex.
It's easy when we create a single
object.
But for a given task,
we are going to start having a more
and more complex graph of objects
of different type with different
configurations and with different
values for all of them.
Creating this graph of an object
can take a lot of time.
Also, we want to encapsulate this
creation from the user.
So later, we can modify this graph
of objects, adding new objects or
adding variations in this graph
without modifying the clients.
So we want to modify this graph
of objects without affecting the client.
We want to change it under the users'
feet.
Also, we want to expose an API that
is closer to the client of our code
that express what the client is
waiting and not what the objects
we need to create or how they are
created or have the relationship
between each of them.
So we need to provide an API that
is closer to what the user wants to use.
If we read the motivation of the
builder design pattern in the
Gang of Four book, in the design pattern
book, we see that the idea is that
we want to separate the construction
of complex objects, of complex graphs
of objects from the user and encapsulate
the internal representation of them,
how they are built, how they are
connected between each other,
what are their relationship,
their internal values,
and we can have with it different
representation because,
for example, we can expose using
the same builder API two different
representations of the same objects
or two different representations
of objects to do the same task.
For the user, this will be all
transparent.
The idea is that we are going to
reify the construction of a complex
graph of objects in an object.
As we say, the builder has the specific
idea of representing the building
of the other objects,
the creation of other objects,
encapsulates this creation logic,
ensures that the objects that we
are creating are well created,
that all the values are well set,
that all the references are well set,
and that we are always having a
good graph of objects that we can
use for the given task that we want.
This decoupling of the creation
of the procedure of creation and
the client allows us to have different
back-ends, what is called different
back-ends, that basically is to
have different kinds of objects
as a result.
The idea of this is that our client
will talk always with our builder
and the builder can produce a set
of representation or another
representation completely different.
But to the client it will be completely
transparent because this is encapsulated
into the builder.
For example, we can analyze the
idea of creating settings in Pharo.
In Pharo, we have a nice settings
framework that allows us to configure
different parts of the system,
but the idea is that the user does
not know how to create this complex
setting object.
They are just asking what are the
elements that they want to set.
In this case, we are going to set
the instance variable
'microdownAndcomments', and we are
going to establish 'Enable',
a default value, and which is the
object that holds that instance
variable.
As we see, the builder in this case,
the most important part is that
the API talks about what the client
is wanting to do, in this case,
exposing a setting to the setting
configuration and does not say,
is not caring about this.
When we produce it, when we execute it,
it will generate a checkbox with
the label that we pass,
and when we click on it,
it will set this instance value
to the right value.
All this behavior is hidden from
the client.
The client only describes what it wants,
and the builder creates all the
complex elements behind.
As we see, the 'SettingNodeBuilder',
that is what we were analyzing before,
just understand messages to be
configured.
In this case, to give a default
value to the setting,
to have a category for it.
If we have different possible values,
we can give a domain value.
And in this case, it will produce
a dropdown list with the different
values, if we want to give an icon,
if we want to give a label,
we are configuring what we want
and not how it is created.
This setting builder has a really
nice feature is that the first is
that we can express what we want
as in a DSL.
The users of the settings builder
don't care how this is implemented,
but just how to demand things to
the builder.
We don't need to have all the creations
of setting objects, hardcoded,
all in our code, all in our domain.
We only use the builder.
The builder will guarantee that
what we create is really nice and
well done, so we don't need to care
to have problems because we put
one object inside another that it
was not intended to.
And all this creation is completely
encapsulated from the user.
And like that, the user can have
the attention in other parts of
the code and it's the setting builder
who has all the creation logic.
We can see another example,
another example of a builder that
we have in Pharo is the use of
Microdown.
Microdown allows us to create
documentation pages or text pages
with a rich text model when we can
have different elements like for
example, code blocks,
or we can have lists, or we can have
links, and titles, so it allows
us to create a rich text model.
Of course, this rich text model
is backed up by a graph of objects behind,
but we don't want to create them by hand.
So Microdown exposes a builder API
that works in the same sense.
In this case, the builder API talks
about the elements that the user
of the builder want to talk,
talks about code blocks,
talks about comments,
talks about if the text is in italic
or not, if it's an anchor,
if it's bold, so it talks about
the elements, talks about the concepts
that the user wants to set in the API,
does not talk about the objects
that is created inside,
that is completely hidden.
If we see an example of how to use
this in this really little example,
we see that when we are creating
the text object, the Microdown text
object, we are using the builder
and we are talking to the builder
in the terms that we know about,
in this case, about the Microdown text.
We don't care about what objects
are used to create it or what is
the final result of the string that
we have in our text test.
So for the user, it's better to
use these messages to talk in the
sense of what we want,
and then the builder is at the end
generating the text and that this
Microdown text representation.
As I said before, it's important
to see that the API of a builder
is the most important part in the
case of Microdown builder,
the high-level API encapsulates
all the complexity of the Microdown
itself.
The users are directly using it
without needing to do any extreme
manipulation and talks in the sense,
in the terms that are implemented
by Microdown.
And also, one important thing is
that how Microdown is implemented
inside is completely transparent
to the user.
The user only talks to the high-level
API.
Let's see another example,
because we want to really put effort
in understanding the importance
of the builder API.
We have Seaside.
Seaside is our web framework that
allows us to produce nice web examples
using a really beautiful builder API.
It will generate an HTML page without
having to do any kind of extreme
manipulation, not having to care
about the correct structure.
Because as you might know,
HTML pages require to be correctly
structured and correctly created
to be correctly rendered in the browser.
So in the Seaside builder,
again, if we see the messages that
we send to it, we see that we are
talking in the cells,
in the terms that are understandable
for the user.
In this case, we are talking about
headings, paragraph, list items.
We are creating an orderedList here.
So all these elements are completely
understandable for somebody that
wants to generate an HTML page and
also provides a way of easily generating
them without caring about extreme
manipulation.
Moreover, this Seaside builder provides
us with a way of structuring elements
that should be inside another,
all the listItem elements should
be inside an orderedList element.
And the API of the builder provides
us with a way of correctly ordering
them.
This DSL like syntax makes that
our builder is clear to understand.
And we can see clearly that this
list item that we are created is
inside the order list that we are
generating.
When to apply the builder design
pattern?
Well, we want to apply the builder
design pattern when we have some
kind of a regular object creation.
We have some regularity in the object
creation, and we want to use it
in different places of our application,
or we have different users of it.
As for example, in the Seaside example,
we will have many applications
generating HTML using the builder.
So we want to use a builder to hide
the complexity.
The builders give us a single entry
point to the creation of objects.
So it is a really nice feature of
a builder, so we can create complex
objects in a single way,
and if we need to change it in the
future, we control this single entry
point.
Also, the builder has a clear API
that is used by the users.
So this API gives us a stable point
where we can implement an evolving
solution without changing the API.
As I said before, the builder
encapsulates the implementation.
So it hides the real implementation
from the user.
So we can always evolve the
implementation without affecting
our users.
As a conclusion, the builder represents
and controls the creations of objects.
It encapsulates this creation logic.
We are always sure that we have
a well-created graph of objects,
and we have a decoupling between
what the user asked to the builder
and what are the real objects that
are instantiated at the end.
And this gives us a way of decoupling
evolution because we can evolve
always the implementation without
affecting the users of it.