Hi, today, we are going to see hooks
again, in particular in the context
of instance hooks and classes for
the case of instantiation.
So we are going to discuss and think
about hooks.
What are the granularity of hooks?
So there are big hooks,
small hooks, so they will allow
us to do different things.
We will put in practice hooks in
the case of instance creation to
understand in particularly factory
methods.
And we are going to talk about how
do we customize instance creation
and if we do it or not.
So let's start with an example.
So here we have a piece of code.
This piece of code is in the case
of a visitor.
Actually, that is anecdotal here.
But what here is happening is that
every time that we are going to
visit something, we are going to
instantiate a new scope,
store it, use it, and then do something
with it, return it or not.
Now let's imagine that I want to
change the kind of scope I want
to instantiate here.
So what are the different solutions
that I have?
One possible thing to do is to extract
the class into its own method.
So instead of hard-coding the class
there and sending new to the direct
class, I can make a method that
returns the class that I am going
to use and send new to the result
of this message.
So of course, this can only be done
in languages where classes are first
class objects like Pharo,
Python, Ruby.
You are not going to be able to
do it in Java.
But this solution is already something
very good and we can already work
on this.
So the first clear conclusion of
this solution is that we can create
subclasses of our class,
like for example we can have
CHInterpreter2, that can redefine
that method and use a different class.
So now we are able to extend our
implementation by just redefining
our class and redefining just one
little method.
One alternative solution to that
is instead of redefining that class
using a message or using actually
a subclass, is to store that class
into an instance variable.
Like that every time that we create
an interpreter, we can tell it what
is the ScopeClass it's going to use.
And then every time that we are
going to access the class that we
want to instantiate, we just need
to use this variable.
This design will allow us to change
the kind of scope we are going to
use per instance and not per class.
So this is actually much more flexible.
Now what happens if we want to have
a more complex instantiation?
For example, actually what happens
here is that we are taking the class
and we are sending a message new.
So this message new is going to
instantiate the class and configure
it with default values of its instance
variables.
But what happens if for example
this instance is actually a really
complex object and we wanted to
instantiate and configure a really
complex graph of objects inside
the scope?
So actually what happens here is
that maybe instead of new,
what we wanted to do is to send
a different message with parameters
or something like that.
But here, we cannot actually do
it because maybe one of the scope
actually doesn't need all that and
another scope, yes, it does need that.
So that means that actually the
hook at this level is not enough,
it's really too small.
So maybe we can do better.
Another solution is to instead of
actually just extracting the class
that we are going to use,
we can extract the entire creation
of the scope and like that we just
extracted the creation of the object
to a separate method,
but now this method becomes
overwriteable and then a subclass
can decide to exchange this object
instantiation and configuration
by a completely different
implementation.
Now if you can only pass a class,
if we only keep the original hook,
the problem is that we cannot customize
object instantiation.
Languages where classes are first
class objects we can do really strange
tricks to do it, yes it is possible,
but actually the solution at the
end is not very nice.
So the last solution that I showed
you helps you to customize and access
different protocols depending on
the kind of scope that you want
to instantiate.
Now a different variation,
a final variation for this pattern
is that we can also extend this
hook with parameters.
So we can add a parameter to the hook,
like that we can send arguments
here and then each subclass can
redefine this and use the argument
as it pleases.
In conclusion, having class hooks
is nice because they help us redefine
instantiation of objects,
but it's important to think about
the granularity of those hooks.
So the bigger the hook,
it's probably the more difficult
to reuse code, but also it is easier
to redefine some part of the system
that are more complicated.