Hello!
In this lecture, we'll discuss class
methods and how to use them.
What you will learn, basically,
is that in Pharo, class methods
are normal virtual methods.
It means that you can send messages
to classes and the method lookup
will work normally, like regular
objects.
Most class methods are usually used
to create new instances,
but sometimes they can do other
things and we will see that it can
be really useful.
Let's have a look at this case study.
Imagine that we want to parse this
string.
This is a string representation
of a document.
Here, we have a title,
a list of items, and maybe a paragraph
there, and we want to create a parser
for this piece of text.
Here, we have a design of this system.
We have a Parser class,
and we have a superclass here,
`DocumentItem`, with subclasses
that represent the node elements
of the text that we want to parse.
The interesting point is that in
this design, each `DocumentItem`
subclass knows if it can parse a line.
So, the `canParse:` method there
is implemented in all subclasses,
and this is a class-side method.
It means that if I give it a piece
of text, it can answer a Boolean
if it can parse this text or not.
And then, the second point is that
each class knows how to create an
instance of itself using this piece
of text.
Given that, the parser is implemented
like this, we have two methods in
the parser: the documentClasses
that computes the collection of
all classes that can parse a piece
of text.
Here, in this expression,
we will query the system to get
all subclasses of the `DocumentItem`
class dynamically.
Then, we will order these subclasses
by priority.
Now that we have a collection of
classes, we can iterate over it,
over this collection,
and using the `canParse` message,
we can find the first one that can
parse a specific line of text.
This is a really useful pattern
because it means that I can easily
add new subclasses and it works
perfectly.
This pattern is also used in the
command line interface.
Let's have a look at another example.
For example, here, I have a command
line - this is a Pharo virtual machine
- I have the Pharo image,
and this part of the command line
is handled by the `CommandLineHandler`.
And we have specific classes in
the system that can handle those
commands.
And we have a lot of different commands
that are supported by this system.
Here, this is an eval command.
This is a keyword that defines the
kind of command that can evaluate
the expression that is right after.
So, it means that each class or
each application in the system can
introduce its own `CommandLineHandler`.
This is an extensible solution.
How is it done?
This is exactly the same pattern.
In the `CommandLineHandler`,
we will first query the system to
detect all handlers in the system.
This is done there.
It means that it will detect all
subclasses, and I will exclude those
that are abstract.
And then, I will select the one
that is responsible for a particular
command.
How is it implemented?
There is a default implementation
in the `CommandLineHandler` class.
It is responsible for arguments,
I will pass the arguments,
and it will answer a Boolean if
this class can deal with this kind
of command.
Then, here I am in the subclass
EvaluateCommandLineHandler, and
I have a hook method there,
self commandName, that is redefined
in the subclass
EvaluateCommandLineHandler, that
just returns the eval.
So, it means that all commands that
start with the eval keyword will
be handled by this class,
EvaluateCommandLineHandler.
This design is completely extensible
by adding new subclasses of the
`CommandLineHandler`.
This design, as we said,
is completely modular.
This is extensible by construction,
but there are some cons.
Checking all subclasses all the
time is really costly.
Each time you ask a class for all
its subclasses, this is a costly
operation because all classes usually
know their superclass,
but they don't know their subclasses,
so it means that you need to iterate
over all classes of the system to
get the subclasses.
And then, you probably don't need
such a dynamic behavior.
Sometimes it is useful,
but sometimes this is not so important
to query the system each time.
In conclusion, classes are regular
objects, and we can send them messages.
The method lookup is exactly the
same as for regular objects.
It goes to the class of the receiver,
and it follows the inheritance chain.
Pharo makes it very easy to iterate
over subclasses and it allows for
really modular and extensible design,
as we saw.
But the problem is that it is really
costly.
This is something that we will address
in the next lecture on Registration.