Welcome to this little lecture,
where I want to stress the difference
between object-oriented programming
and class-oriented programming.
You will wonder what is it,
and I will show you what is
class-oriented programming and that
you should not do it.
So the idea, this is really to think
again what is object-oriented
programming and that sometimes,
you may think that you are programming
in an object-oriented way,
but you are doing it more in a class
way and this is not very nice.
What you see is that sometimes,
you get class-based programming
design where class are used as data
holder in the sense that instance
of such a class would share the
same data.
So this means that all your instances
will have the same values.
So in that case, you say okay,
why do I need a class that normally
generates instances, different instances
if now I generate instances,
but they are all the same data.
And in this design, often what you
will see is that you have to write
a new class to represent a new instance
and this is really a big red sign
you should not.
So in such design, what you see
is that you have no real instance
specific state.
I did a sketch of that.
So imagine the following hierarchy,
you have a class changer that has
different methods.
It has the method 'commandClass',
it has the method 'order' and
'multiFormClass'.
And for example, a subclass
PositionChanger will implement these
three methods and background will
implement the three methods and
identifier will implement the three
methods.
And for example, (the commandClass
will return the commandPattern as
the commandClass associated
commandPosition).
The multiFormClass will return FormPoint
and for example, the order will return 2.
And then, we see that in all the
classes the same so background will
return the command that is the
CommandBackground.
The multiForm will return the FormColor
and here the order 10 and the same
for this identifier.
What we see from this design is
that of course I can have an instance
here.
Let's call it aIdentifierChanger.
I can have another one,
no problem, I can have multiple of them.
But they all share this,
they all share that and they all
share that.
So this means that each time I will
send a message order here,
I will get one here, order I will
get one.
So you can these classes can have
multiple instance but they all have
the same state.
The same, these classes can have
instances and it will have all the
same state.
So and now if I want to create a
new instance, basically what I am
forced to do, I am forced to create
a new subclass.
So here, we'll have a new subclass,
here with a commandClass that will
return something and order that
will return I don't know 42,
why not.
And there is something fishy,
so let's analyze it a bit.
So when I see such kind of class,
I know that they are data oriented,
they are really static.
They are static in the sense that
I have to create a new classes for
each new instance.
And a class in fact represent only
one instance even if I can create
multiple of them, I cannot do much
with them because I can only do
the same and they will reply to
in the exactly same state.
So what we should see is that a
class should describe instance shape
not values.
And that's a key difference.
Each instance can potentially have
a different state.
Maybe it is initialized by default one,
but we can change it.
In the design that I showed you
previously, this is impossible.
You can always get the same design.
Let's compare now with the equivalent
of the previous one with a simple
single class.
In that design, what I will do is
that I will define instance variable
and some setters and getters.
So here I have the getters.
Each of these getters will return
the value that are stored in this
variable for each object.
So here for example I will have
a changer that is configured as
the identifier that we saw on the
previous slide.
And here, this one will have the
same information, but configured
as the background and the position.
And these three instances have different
states and they will behave differently.
When I send the message order to
this one, I will get a result that
is different from that one and I
will get access to the state of
this object.
So with this design we just create
instances.
They can represent multiple and
different configurations of the
same values and potentially we could
decorate them.
So this means that we could say,
oh, you are an instance and I wrap
you in another object or I do something
else with you.
And to create one, we just specify
what we want.
Here, I said, I would like to have
a new one with I don't know something
else than before.
And here, I will specify okay this
is the new value.
So with subclass what we can also
do is that we can potentially if
this is important for us,
we can create a new subclass that's
inherited from the previous one
where it has a specific initialized
method where I define some default
values and I can have multiple instances
here, but that would be a position
too because this is about position
but I could change.
For example, I could say,
I want to put a different command.
So I could say commandClass:
or please use this one because I
have an extension.
So I would say, CommandPosition2
and then this means that this instance
will have a different state from
this one, but still I encapsulate
here some knowledge that apparently
is better.
So what you should see also is that
from that perspective,
this design need a discovery mechanism
or you have to store your instance
variable somewhere while in the
previous one you just add the class.
So you know okay there is one single
entry point because this is the class.
So if I write a ChangerPosition,
there is only class there is one
class ChangerPosition in the system,
so it was providing a single access
point.
Now, if we use instances,
it means that we can have multiple
instances with different states.
And in that case, we should explicitly
register, so maybe we can have at
the class level some annotation
or something that will have a dictionary
to store them with an ID or something
like that.
But this is much better in any way,
in any case.
So the conclusion is that when you
need to define a new class to represent
a new instance, this is fishy,
run away, change.
A class describes the shape of its
instances, not the value.
Sometimes for some values,
you want to share them and you know
that they will not change,
that's okay.
But it cannot be a general like that.
So it means that there is something
wrong.
So in general, favor instance over
classes because that classes are
static so you cannot create dynamically.
So this means that if you need the
compiler basically to really define
an instance, there is something
strange.