Hi, in this lecture we are going
to discuss about coupling and
encapsulation.
The goals of this lecture is to
think about coupling and how coupling
affects different entities in our
system.
We are going to present the Law
of Demeter, which is one of the
principles that can guide your design.
We are going to discuss about the
move behavior closer to data pattern.
It's a reengineering pattern from
the Reengineering Pattern book and
we are going to discuss about some
of the trade-offs of this Law of
Demeter, which can have benefits
and some drawbacks.
Now, have you ever found yourself
in one of these situations?
Telling yourself, I cannot reuse
this component in this other
application, no, because it is blah,
blah, blah, blah, blah,
or I cannot easily substitute this
part of the system with another one,
even if it does similar stuff.
Or, ah, look, when something happens
in this part of the system,
I get impacted here.
So or finally, ah, no,
this part I cannot test,
no, no, it's too complicated.
Actually, most of these things,
or all of them, are symptoms of
a coupling problem.
So there is a coupling in some way
in the system, and that is so strong
that is preventing us evolving our
system in some way, either by reusing,
substituting, changing,
or even test our system.
So to illustrate this problem,
we have this example here where
actually we have to read it from
right to left.
So here we have some class here
that defines this 'do()' method,
which is the most important thing
right now in our example,
and it has a reference to a 'dependent'
object, and this dependent object
has a reference to another 'IndirectDependent'
object, so we have a chain
of objects.
And then, this 'IndirectDependent'
has a method 'doSomething:'.
Finally, what happens in the 'do'
method is that the source is telling
the 'dependent' to give it the 'IndirectDependent'
and to do the 'doSomething'.
So actually, the source is actually
taking the dependent,
asking the dependent,
and talking directly to the indirect
dependent.
So if you know what is Feature Envy,
the Feature Envy code smell,
this is related to that,
I invite you to look up that online.
Now what happens if we want to change
some part of this application?
Changes are natural, so it's common
that we are going to change stuff.
So the question is when we want
to change something, how are we
going to be impacted?
Yeah.
So in particular here,
if we want to change something here
in the indirect dependent,
what are the possible impacts that
we're going to get in the rest of
the system?
In this particular case,
what we're going to get is what
we call waves or chains of effects
or changes.
So here, what happens is that every
time that we change something,
that is going to impact the direct
users, but also if we don't control it,
it can make waves on other more
indirect users.
So here in this case,
if we want to, for example,
remove this 'doSomething' method,
we have to go and change this do
method because it is calling it.
So all these chain reactions or waves,
they are evil.
They actually create,
they are actually created when we
have leaks.
So there is a reference to an object
that is flowing from some place
to another place it should not flow.
So we have an indirect reference
where it should not.
So what we say is that we are violating
encapsulation.
So one of the key aspects,
objects and object orientation is
that an object will encapsulate
and it will hide its implementation.
So if we are leaking the reference
of an object to another object,
we are giving the other objects
some pointer to our own implementation.
So the question is, how can we limit
this leaking?
One of the answers to this problem
is to use the Law of Demeter.
The Law of Demeter is just a principle,
a design principle that will give
us some guidance in how we can avoid
that.
So the Law of Demeter says that
we can only send messages to arguments,
instance variables, an object that
we are creating, self,
super and our own class,
and that we should avoid global
variables and objects returning
from messages in general,
others and sent to self.
So how does it work in a real example?
So here, for example,
this is a method that shows different
examples of things that we can do.
So if we have a method and we put
ourselves in the skin of the object
in the receiver, so we have a parameter,
so we can send the message self foo,
because the receiver is self,
so we can send the message to ourselves.
Why is that?
Because if we change,
we only have to change ourselves.
So that's okay.
Here we have a message sent to super,
so that means that this,
if you remember the super lecture,
will restart the method lookup from
the superclass of this method,
of the class where this method is.
So if this method is in A and it
has a superclass B, it's going to
restart the lookup in B.
So again, here we have somehow some
dependency to a superclass.
If the superclass changes,
we are going to get impacted,
but we are still in the same hierarchy,
so still this is a controllable change.
Now here we are sending a message
self to self to get the current class.
And that, of course, should get
us the current class,
the class of the current object,
and we are sending a message to
our own class.
So that's okay.
And that is allowed by the Law of
Demeter.
We can also send messages to instance
variables.
So to object references by instance
variables, here we are sending a
message to 'instVarOne' that is referenced
to some object, and we also allow
messages sent to instance variable
accessed by a getter method.
So here, this is the equivalent
of a getter method that returns
the value of 'instVarOne'.
We can also send a message to parameters
and then we can instantiate objects
and since we just instantiated it,
we can actually send it a message.
So what this law will enforce is
that we are not going to be able
to send messages to far away objects.
So we don't have to skip intermediate
objects.
So our source object knows this
dependence and the dependence will
know the intermediate dependence,
the indirect dependence.
So what the Law of Demeter tries
to do is to avoid that this guy
here sends a message here.
So this is forbidden and this is
forbidden too.
Like that, if we avoid these far
away messages, we are going to avoid
dependencies and we are going to
avoid the chain of changes if we
change here.
What the Law of Demeter will actually
force us to do is that the source
here will only be able to send messages
here and here.
So its action will be constrained
to this part of the system.
So that means that here we are
constraining the changes we are
going to do.
If we change the dependent here,
that is probably going to affect
the source, but it's not going to
affect anything else in the system.
In the same way, we are going to
constrain the messages to indirect
dependent to the dependent and like
that, if something changes in here,
it should only affect the dependent
here and not the source.
This Law of Demeter, of course,
can be applied in a systematic way
following, for example,
here, the design pattern that is
called move behavior close to data,
which has a subjective to move the
behavior that is being applied to
objects close to where those objects
are.
The idea is to strengthen the
encapsulation.
So to actually refactor step by
step the code that we saw at the
beginning and make it closer to
what we saw later.
So here, for example,
if you see this example like this,
here we are in the original code
where we have a car that is using
an engine and the engine is using
a carburetor and then the engine
wants to increase the speed and
to increase the speed it is taking
the carburetor and then changing
a flag that is here far away to true.
So step by step, if we wanted to
fix that in a refactoring,
we would first move this behavior
to the engine and like that the
car should, since the car should
only talk to the Engine,
we are going to transform this whole
expression to 'engine.speedUp()'.
So we're going to add behavior,
move behavior close to the data here.
And like that, we move the inner
expression into here.
Like that now in this first step,
the car doesn't depend anymore on
the carburetor.
Now the car only depends on the engine.
But now the problem, we just push
the problem to the engine.
The engine now depends on the carburetor
that is actually really coupled
with implementation of the carburetor.
If we decide tomorrow to change
the implementation of the carburetor
and make that flag instead of a flag,
an integer that will impact also
the engine, so we can also apply
this in a second step and to hide
those by moving this behavior to
the carburetor.
So now in the final refactoring,
what happens is that the engine
will tell the carburetor to open
the fuel valve and then the carburetor
can do whatever it wants in its
implementation.
In this case, it will only set the
`Boolean` as true, the flag as true.
In this final version,
what happens is that the car only
has a dependency to the engine and
the engine has a slight dependency
to the API of the carburetor.
All these dependencies are actually
based not on implementations,
but on APIs, so they will force
that our engine depends on the message,
open fuel valve and the car depends
on the message speed up as well.
For another real case,
so here we have an example taken
from Pharo, from the morphic UI
framework, which is actually managing
the resolution change.
So every time that we change the
resolution of the Pharo window,
this is the code that was being
executed before, so this was fixed
at the mean time, but it was a good
example for the slides.
So what happened here is that we
had this morphic word that represents
the window, and when we were resizing
the window, we were actually taking
the state of the world,
taking the render of the world from
the worldstate and taking the actual
window from the renderer,
asking it the backend window,
which actually represents the physical
window from the operating system,
asking it its renderer and finally
destroying it.
So this is actually not satisfying
the Law of Demeter.
So the same thing happened actually
in the lines below, all up to the end.
So what actually happens here is
that if any of these method changes
or any of this implementation changes
here in this chain of methods,
then this method will be broken too.
Resolution of this is,
of course, to follow the Law of
Demeter to some degree,
to refactor step by step and to
delegate only to the object that
we know directly.
So here, for example,
what happens is that this is the
original code that was refactored.
Now, every time that we visit the
ResolutionChangeEvent, we are taking
the world state, so here we are
not a 100% following the Law of Demeter,
but we are actually cutting many,
many steps.
And we are telling it to update
to the new resolution.
This update new resolution will
do the main three steps that we
were doing before, but it was kind
of hidden in implementation detail
because it was difficult to read.
So it is doing a full repaint followed
by an update to resolution and checking
the screen size.
And this 'UpdateToNewResolution' is
executing the destroy,
validate and update all that we
saw before.
One of the funny things,
one of the important things of this
example is that now we can easily
change the renderer to implement
a null object, for example,
here is NullWorldRenderer that can
implement an empty update to new
resolution.
So now that we are not coupled to
the implementations, we can change
part of the implementations,
but other kind of implementation.
So finally, what you see is that
the big method was kind of a factor
to a simple method in the right place,
doing the right three things in
a more readable way.
Now it's important to understand
that Law of Demeter, as I said,
is heuristic or it's just a principle.
So you should not follow it blindly.
So if you just do it too strictly,
actually this can lead to problems
like a bloated class API.
So it can actually create them by
the APIs for your clients.
For example, I will show you later
that encapsulating collections can
produce large interfaces that are
complex to follow and to maintain.
So it is important to understand
what is reasonable to leak,
when it is important to apply the
Law of Demeter and when it is important
to break it too.
So here, for example,
in this case, what we have is a method,
a class that will wrap a collection
that is called senders.
And in this case, somebody decided
to expose all the collection API
in this class.
So here that means that then we
have the method do that will expose
the do method of the sender and
the method collect that will expose
collect and so on for all the other
methods on collections.
So that means that the bigger the
API of collections, the bigger the
API that needs to be exposed by
this object.
So in this sense, maybe the hiding
the actual collection was not the
right decision in this case,
and maybe it would have been easier
to just expose the collection to
the user.
As a conclusion, think about the
impact of changes.
Think about the dependencies and
think about what happens when you
change messages and change access
to variables, moreover.
Remember that the Law of Demeter
is heuristic.
So it doesn't work in all cases.
You must use it whenever it actually
pays off.
So it has benefits, but it can also
have drawbacks if it is used wrongly
and think about the move behavior
close to data reengineering pattern,
which is a good way to move from
a bad design to the good design
using the Law of Demeter.