Hello.
In this lecture, we will revisit
the notion of registration that
we already discussed in a previous
lecture using class methods.
So the idea is to analyze what are
the alternatives to class-based
method registration and to see if
we can design something that is
as dynamic, but less expensive.
So if you remember, before starting,
a class is a regular object.
We can send messages to classes
and each class can answer specifically.
We can add new methods and classes.
For example, if I do object
allSubclasses, I will get allSubclasses
of the object and I can collect
all classes that can answer to the
foo message.
And of course, it means that I need
to define the `foo` method on the
classes or it should be inherited
to make it work.
And if you remember correctly,
in a previous lecture,
we already spoke about an extensible
design by iterating over subclasses.
For example, in the `PillarParser`,
we were able to compute dynamically
the document classes that represent
the nodes of a document.
And then to parse a line,
we were able to dynamically select
the right node that can parse a
specific line.
So this mechanism is a kind of
pre-registration mechanism based
on class methods.
So it means that each time a new
class is loaded in the system,
a new subclass of document item,
it will be taken into account for free.
You have nothing to do as a programmer.
But the cons is that each time you
need to query the system.
You need to query the system to
get all nodes that can parse a line,
all document item subclasses.
And this is really costly.
You need to do it all the time for
nothing and this is an expensive
mechanism.
So what can we do to improve this
situation?
Solution one, we could pre-compute
the list of classes and write it
directly in the code.
So here in the code, we replaced
the document item or subclasses
by a fixed collection of classes,
section, list, and paragraph.
And then, we can sort them by priority.
We can even do better.
We can directly order the list correctly
and that the priority is directly
embedded inside the collection.
So now the evaluation of this solution
is that we do not have to query
the classes all the time.
So this is a good point.
But the cons is that you have to
keep the list up to date.
So it means that each time you will
load a new class in the system,
you need to revisit the list,
change the code, recompile the method.
So this is an explicit list that
is written in the code.
And this is not really extensible
by design.
The next solution is to have an
explicit registration mechanism.
So it means that now in the
`PillarParser`, we will store in
a class variable a dictionary or
collection of classes that can represent
an item, a document item.
And of course, I need to add a way
for classes to register themselves.
So I will provide a method,
registerClass, like that a new class
in the system can register itself
in the `PillarParser` saying,
okay, now I can handle those elements
in a document.
For example, if I have a section
class and I load it, when I initialize
a class, it will register itself
directly in the `PillarParser`.
The same for a paragraph.
So this new mechanism is very
interesting.
There is no need to maintain the
list of classes manually,
so the developer is free to do it.
It's not written explicitly in the code.
It's completely dynamic.
It means each time I will load a
new class, the class can itself
register itself in the parser.
The registration could support purity
and external classes can also register.
This is not mandatory that classes
that register are part of the same
package as the `PillarParser`.
So here we have an example of that.
The extra class that could be packaged
in another package can register
itself in the `PillarParser`.
And the really good point is that
the extra class could be packaged
in a separate package from the
`PillarParser` and also the dependency
is reversed.
It means that there is a dependency
between the extra class and the
`PillarParser` and not between the
`PillarParser` and the extra class.
So this is really better from the
dependency point of view.
But with an explicit registration
mechanism, also we need an
unregistration mechanism.
So it means that now this is a developer
should provide an explicit way for
unregistering document item.
And for that, the pillar parser
will provide a method to unregister
a class.
And of course, this is the
responsibility of each class to
unregister itself when it is unloaded,
for example.
As a conclusion, the pattern using
all subclasses is a very nice pattern,
but it is costly.
So you need to know it.
And usually, it's much better to
use an explicit registration mechanism,
but it's not free.
It means that you need to implement
it and you need to provide a way
to unregister it, to unregister
elements, etc.
So it means that it's always about
trade-off, can I use the free mechanism
or should I use an explicit one
and code it completely?