Hello, welcome to this lecture.
In this lecture, we are going to
talk about an example of a monolithic
application and what are the impacts
of it.
The goals for this lecture is first
to think about how we can customize
our elements, how we can customize
our application.
We are going to talk a lot about
modularity and we are going to analyze
an example, a real example from
Squeak and its implementation in Pharo.
We are going to analyze how we handle
`Preferences` and optional configuration
in Pharo and in Squeak.
We have, in both cases,
we want to have a way of configuring
our system, configuring our tools
to work in the way that we want.
So in both cases, we have a setting
browser where we can set all the
customizations, all the settings
that we want for our tools.
For example, the colors,
the direction of the text,
the fonts that we are using,
the size of those fonts and all
these settings are applied on our tools.
So, what we want to do is basically
to have a way that we can configure
our application to work in the way
our `Preferences` say it and we
want to have only one way of handling
this dependency in all the systems.
So we give a single entry point
to the user how to configure the system,
but also how to use it from the
developer point of view,
how to use the setting system.
So we want a modular definition
of the `Preferences` so we have
them in a single point.
We also want that our objects,
our domain object, does not have
a dependency with the `Preferences`
because every time that we modify
the preference or modify our objects
will affect on another part of the
system and that is not desirable.
So, how we can do this idea of having
a detached mode, a detached preference
module and also still having the
ability to change the behavior of
our application.
Let's look at the first solution
that we have to analyze.
In Squeak 3.8, there was already
a solution to this problem.
There was an object that called
`Preferences` that was basically
a Facade for managing these
`Preferences`.
This is a bad design pattern,
but we are going to describe it
now why it is.
Basically, this object `Preferences`
was referenced by other elements
in the system in a total of 617 times.
So all over the system was using
this `Preferences` class.
So it ended being a really huge
dependency of everybody.
Everybody, doesn't matter what you
are doing, we’re using this
`Preferences` class.
If you are reading a PNG or compiling
a method, you are using the
`Preferences` class.
All the subsystems were basically
having a dependency to this
`Preferences` class.
For example, if we have a morph
that represents a morph is a graphic
element in Pharo and in Squeak,
but let's say a graphic element
that represents a menu.
Well, does this menu have round
corners or not?
Well, that is a preference.
So if we were using or not round
corners was delegating this question
to the `Preferences` class.
Other part, a button.
A button that we have and it should
or not use a standard font or have
a specific font.
Which is the font to use?
Well, again we ask to the `Preferences`.
This is, you can tell me,
okay, in this kind of problem we
have the UI elements asking to the
`Preferences`.
We have a dependency between the
UI elements and the `Preferences`.
It can be good, but this also pass,
this also happens in a core part
of the system.
For example, when we were printing
the template for creating a new
subclass of a given class,
we had also a reference to the
`Preferences` class asking if we
are using a type of syntax or an
alternative one.
Another example, in this case,
the input sensor.
The input sensor is the object that
takes care of handling the events
of keyboards and mouse and in this
time was asking if we have to swap
or not the Alt key.
And look again, we have a dependency
with the `Preferences` class.
So a lot of part of the system were
pointing to this `Preferences` class.
So we have basically that a lot
of modules of the system,
we have our UI modules,
but our compiler, our input handlers,
everything was passing through the
`Preferences`.
We have that this preference class
was referenced all over the system.
If I have to add a new preference,
a new alternative of configuration,
I have to touch the same `Preferences`
class.
As we see, all the components in
the system were using,
were depending on this `Preferences`
class.
So we have a dependency of mostly
everybody on `Preferences`.
We cannot remove this class.
We cannot remove the `Preferences`
system because it's not optional.
Everybody depends on it at this point.
If everybody depends on it,
we have to have it always.
And every time we add a new dependency
on it, we made that this new component
also depends in all the other components
in the system because remember that
if we have one component,
the UI, and this one has a dependency
on the `Preferences`.
And we modify the preference to
add a new value.
For example, now that it will be
used by the proxy, the HTTP proxy,
we add a new thing here.
Now we have added also a dependency
to our HTTP proxy.
The proxy.
So in an indirect way,
we end up having a dependency between
these two models that does not have
nothing to do one with the other.
Clearly, we are in a really bad
situation and we end with a really
heavy, heavy monolithic system.
So in this example, we can see clearly
that the combination of Facade and
singleton are really bad for having
a modular system.
Usually, we should say that a Facade
should basically never be used or
rarely if we are nice enough.
Because it's a good idea that proposes
a single point of entry,
but this idea is only applicable
in little scenarios.
Also, a Facade is always disguised
as a global variable,
and we already have talked in this
MOOC what is the impact of having
global variables and how they are
bad for modularity, the ability
to write tests for it,
and a global variable is usually
not recommended.
You can see also the lectures about
Singleton to see more and understand
when is correctly to use this and
when is correctly to use the idea
of global variable.
But in mostly of the scenarios,
we are with a smell, a code smell,
what we say, because this shows
a potential problem.
So what is an alternative to this?
Well, what we want to do is that
the modules or the components that
have parts that we can customize,
that we can set by settings,
we'll expose them via methods in
its own declaration.
We will see this more clearly with
an example.
The class of the component that
we are configuring will declare
which are these points of customization.
Then with this declaration,
we can generate the UI for the user.
And once the UI is modified by the user,
we can configure the resulting objects.
What is the idea?
The idea is that, for example,
if we need to have in our previous
example of the MenuMorph,
we have to have the option to have
or not round corners.
What we are going to do is add a
class instance variable or a shared
variable with this value stored.
So we don't need to ask here the
`Preferences`.
The same for the basic button to
get its own standard font.
It will ask it to itself or it will
ask it to its class, but always
inside the module.
The MenuMorph will use a shared
variable or an instance variable
that is defined inside the MenuMorph.
This sounds really obvious and it's
sounds that is the really great
idea to do, but in the beginning
it's not so evident.
So an object we have to design it
to be customizable.
We need to put the points of extension
that we want and we need to think
when these are modified and what
are the states that we can customize.
And of course, this state should
be always internal to the object.
As I said before, for example,
in the case of the MenuMorph,
the variable should be in the class
MenuMorph or really close to the
class MenuMorph.
Let's see an example of how to implement
it more correctly.
We have a show progress bar.
Morph is a UI component that shows
a progress bar.
Basically, it's a square that has
a label and a bar that gets filled
as long as we are finishing the
task that we are finishing.
It's a progress bar.
We have an option in this progress
bar that affects all the progress
bar that can be interruptible or not.
We can interrupt this process.
Basically, we have a flag.
We want a flag to have a button
here to cancel the action that we
are doing.
Okay.
This is something that we want to
configure because depending on the
system, the application that we
are building, we want it to have
it or to not have it the boot.
So how we do this?
Well, in the class side of the
ShowProgressBarMorph, we are going
to add a new shared variable that
is called `IsInterruptible`.
We are going to give it with the
lazy initialization a default value.
Then, of course, we are going to
add to be accessible a nice accessor
`IsInterruptible`.
And also, we are going to add an
instance side element to access
the same accessor.
Now, when we want to decide or not
to draw the button, the interruption
button, we are going to ask directly
to self.
As we see, the configuration is
doing what we asked is inside the
ShowProgressBarMorph in this time
is in the class side,
but is in the same class and we
are using it accessing directly
with self.
So it's local to our class.
Once we do that, we have to declare
that we have a point of extension.
How we do that?
Well, we are going to add a new
method in our class side that will
have the name that we want,
but it's important that receives
and a new argument that is the builder,
the setting builder.
This setting builder is what we
are going to use to configure how
we want to present it to the user.
The idea is that we want to present
it to the user with a checkbox.
So we have to give to this checkbox
the text that we are going to have,
the description that is the text
that will appear when the user put
the mouse on top of it.
And what is the value that we are
going to change when it's clicked or not.
This is done by this builder of
settings.
As you see, we are talking about
the property isInterruptable.
We are giving a default value.
We are giving the description and
the label.
So in this way, the class
ShowProgressBarMorph is describing
to the settings how to expose the
settings and this code is only called,
this message is only sent when the
settings needs to create the window.
If we don't have a setting window
in the system, if we remove the
settings package from the system
or the module, this message will
never be called.
This message will never be sent
and this method will never execute
and we don't have now a dependency.
We have a really slight dependency.
This is, once we describe it,
how to present the setting to the user,
we can see that now the setting
browser can take that information
and generate in the correct place
that is where we describe it the
checkbox, so the user can set or
not the value.
As we see, let's see a little more
about the architecture that we have.
We have a really layered architecture
where we have split the
responsibilities.
In one way, we have a setting browser
that is our UI.
This setting browser will collect
all the methods that in this case
we collected using a technique using
this pragma, but this is anecdotic,
but it will collect all the methods
that describes the settings and
will send this message to each of
them to get the description of the
setting to show.
The domain we see here is clearly
separated and the domain will use
its internal customization hooks.
It will use its internal state to
customize itself and it will declare
these customization hooks to the
settings.
So we have a really smaller dependency
between these two components.
We have simplified the dependency.
So it's important that we see two
different concepts in this.
One is that we want that our modules
have a layered dependency.
We don't want all the domain depends
on a specific tool or in this case,
the setting framework.
We want our domain of application,
our solution to the business problem
not to depend on the setting framework
because we are not mixing layers.
So also the settings,
the descriptions of the settings
should not depend on how they are
presented.
We have a division as we said before
between the UI and how the settings
are modeled.
Other thing that we really want
to stress is that we have a real
modular system where the parts of
the system can be loaded independently
and we don't have dependencies that
are unneeded.
We don't want our system to depend
on the settings if it's not extremely
required.
We want the model, the domain to
just depend on other things of the
domain.
We have to recall also that to have
a nice level of customization we
have to design our component.
We have to design our objects to
be customizable.
We don't need to let it add to the
last moment because we have to think
all the points of customization
and extension in advance.
Also all this customization,
all the logic should be internal
and we should be able to expose
the minimal possible.
Of course we don't want to have
this logic tied to a preference
object and we want to be able to
set them from outside.
As a conclusion, a good architecture
should not use extensively global
variables.
We have to avoid global variables
because they are complex to maintain
and complex to test.
We also need to avoid Singleton
and Facade because they are patterns
that usually are used wrong.
And our theory, our position is
that the Facade is really useful
for problems that look like the
compiler, when we want to have a
single entry point to a place but
maybe it should not be singlet.
And, of course, the last point that
we talk is that all the customizations
should be internal first and then
we should have a way of exposing,
but all the questions and all the
conditional code about customization
should be done internally to the
class and the whole.