Hello.
In this lecture, we are going to
see one of our case studies,
which is a Sokoban implementation.
So the goal of this lecture is to
think about how to model,
in this case, a Sokoban,
how to think about games also,
and in particular, how do we use
our knowledge on messages and conditions
that we saw before.
For this, we're going to study a
Sokoban game.
So a Sokoban game, for those that
don't know it, it's a game where
there's a `Player` that has to `Push`
`Boxes`, so like these `Boxes`,
into squares that have a `Target`.
So the goal of the game is to `Push`
all the `Boxes` into each of the
`Targets`.
So it's a puzzle game.
In this lecture, we are going to
study an open source implementation
made by students of the Ivan Franko
University in Lviv, in Ukraine.
So thank you so much for your
implementation that will serve us
to study.
So in this game, as you can see,
we have the typical concerns of Sokoban.
So we will have squares that are
`Walls` that we cannot cross with
our `Robot`.
So we have a `Robot` that we will
move around.
The `Robot` will be able to `Push`
`Boxes` into these `Targets`,
and all these free places,
we are going to be able to walk
around with the `Robot`.
So we'll check the different classes
implemented in the implementation
we have.
These are the main classes that we see.
So we have `Blocks`, we have
`EmptyBlocks`, and `Walls` that
are subclasses of `Blocks`.
We have a `GameModel`,
a `Block`, a `Maze`, we have a
`MazeTemplate`, we have a `MoveResult`,
and then we have `Moves` with subclasses
like `Push`, and then we have also
a `NoMove`.
So let's take a step back before
going back to that design and think
about what is the design that we
would like to have in that Sokoban.
Yeah, so let's use, for example,
here one of the patterns in the
object oriented reengineering book.
So of course, you don't need to
read the book to use this pattern,
but of course, this book has a lot
of other patterns that are interesting
to see, and they talk about how
do we take a look at an application
that we don't know and how can we
reengineer it or even understand
it without previous knowledge about it.
So in this case, this pattern is
a speculate about design,
and the objective is to think about
the model, think about the problem
that we are working on,
and what is the possible design
that is going to fit this problem
without actually looking at
implementation.
Yeah, so that is to use our expertise
and our previous knowledge to try
to come up with ideas on the possible
design that we are going to have.
Let's forget a bit about what I
showed you before.
We are going to compare it later,
but take some minutes to try to
understand what are the different
classes that you are going to have
in this game.
So maybe you arrive to a list like this.
So we have `Walls` that will be
representing these squares that
the `Robot` cannot trespass.
We will have the `Floor` that are
the squares that the `Robot` is
going to be able to walk on.
We are going to have `Boxes`,
maybe, like these `Boxes`,
the `Boxes` that we are going to move.
Then we are going to have the `Robot`.
Of course, if we are going to move
it and draw it, probably a `Robot`
is a good object to have in this model.
We are going to have the `Targets`,
or maybe you chose another name for it,
but these little crosses here is
the place where we have to put the
`Boxes`.
And then maybe you arrive to the
conclusion that we need to model
also the `Board` for the entire game.
Of course, maybe there is also the
possibility, since I already influenced
you with the previous model,
that maybe we want to model also
the `Levels` or having `Templates`
to be able to edit `Levels` more easily.
And of course, if we want to not
only model the static part of the
system, we also want to model how
it works, maybe we want to model
the `Moves`.
If we go back to what we saw before,
what we can see is that here we
have three groups of model objects.
So here we have, on the bottom we
have everything that is related
to `Moves`.
So it's the dynamic part of the system.
Then we have these four different
things that are representing the game.
So like the big `Board` of the game.
So there is a model, there is a state,
there is a `Maze`, there is a
`Template`, but all of them will
represent similar things about the
entire `Board`.
And then, the smallest part of the
system is representing actually
the richest part of the system,
which is the `Robot`,
the `Walls`, the `Boxes`,
and all that.
So if we take a look at this,
what we can see is that this model
is a bit shallow.
So it doesn't represent the entire
things or all the objects that we
saw in our model.
So that means that we are going
to have probably different cases.
So when a `Robot` wants to move
on a `Wall`, when a `Robot` wants
to actually `Push` a `Box`,
when the `Robot` is going to reach
a `Target`, for example,
so we are going to have different
cases there.
And if we don't have them modeled
as classes, we're going to have
them as tricky conditionals.
So remember that the basis of
object-oriented programming is to
have different classes,
to have different cases because
then we can use messages and classes
to dispatch conditions.
So instead of having a fat class
that does a lot of things using
conditionals, we're going to use
a lot of small classes like these.
And then, it's going to be the dispatch,
the message send that is going to
decide what is the operation that
we're going to execute.
Remember the lecture,
for example, of implemented or not
in `Booleans.` So if we go a bit
deeper and we check the API of these
classes, particularly the API of
the `Boxes`, we see that it has
a lot of methods that are going
to return conditionals.
So these are testing methods.
So they are, for example,
they are the methods for asking
if a `Block` is empty,
if there is a `Wall`,
if the `Block` has a `Player` on
top of it, if it has a `Target`
and if it has `Blocks`.
And if we check how this API is used,
we find methods like this one.
So this is the method that will
draw one `Block` in the screen.
So it has to check all the potential
combinations of the state of our
model to be able to know how to
draw it properly.
So here, for example,
it says if it is just a `Wall`,
then it will draw a `Wall`.
Otherwise, it has to check if it
is an `emptyBlock`.
So if there's nothing on top of it.
In that case, it will draw,
it has to check if it is empty but
has a `Target`.
And then, if it's empty and it has
a `Target`, it has to draw a `Target`.
Otherwise, it draws an empty `Block`.
On the other way, it will check
if it has a `Player` or a `Box`.
And if it has a `Player` and a `Target`,
it has to draw a `Player`.
Otherwise, it has to draw a `Target`
and so on.
So it is a pretty complicated code
and it's fairly easy to make a mistake
here.
So if we analyze it a bit,
so in a more higher `Level`,
what we see is that our model only
defines `emptyBlocks` and `Walls`,
but there are no `Players`,
no `Target`, no `Boxes`.
But those are important things for
drawing and for us to actually to
implement the behavior of our game.
So that means that there will be
too much logic in the `emptyBlock`
because the `emptyBlock` is the
one that actually is representing
the `Targets`, the `Players` and
the `Boxes`.
And this is also following a bad
pattern, which is asking too many
questions to the model.
So here we would like to follow
this directive.
So tell don't ask.
So instead of asking an object,
okay, are you like this,
are you like that.
So I can take the decision.
Let's better tell the object to
take the decision because the object
has all the information it needs
to take that decision.
So let's think, okay,
what would be a better model?
Maybe we could have an abstract
superclass like `Tile`.
Yeah, so we could have a `Tile`.
And then, we could have subclasses of it.
Here we could see, for example,
we could have a `Box`.
We could have a `Box` in a `Target`
that, for example, we are going
to use it to draw it with a different
color because once the `Box` is
on a `Target`, we know that that
`Box` is already matching the result
of the puzzle.
Then we could have, for example,
an `emptyBlock` that is going to
represent a place where actually
the `Robot` can walk on.
We can have `Player` and we can
have `Wall`.
Yeah, so at the end, the game is
just a collection of `Tiles`.
And then, once we have a model reached
like this, we can just send messages
to these objects and then each of
these objects, they are going to
do the right thing.
If we want to replace this all and
trick implementation, one way to
do it is to use our nicer model
and to use delegation on the new
classes that we are using.
So we are just going to delegate
to tell the objects to do something.
So since now we have `Boxes` or
`Blocks` here that are going to
be of different kinds,
of different classes,
so what we can do is to tell each
`Block`, draw yourself in this canvas.
And then, I don't know who you are,
but you know who you are,
so you know how to draw yourself.
So then, for example,
if we have a `Wall`, the `Wall`
will have all the drawing of the
`Wall` here.
And if we have an `emptyBlock`,
we will have all the code that draws
an `emptyBlock` in here.
That will lead to actually simpler
code in each part.
And if we want to later replace
one part of the system or even add
a new kind of `Blocks`,
we are going to be able to do it
more easily.
So that solution not only supports
different kind of `Blocks`,
it also supports multiple canvases.
So before, what we saw is that the
application was being drawn in a
Cairo canvas, which is a 2D API
to do games.
But instead, we could replace that
with different canvases,
like, for example, Morphic in Pharo
or even an HTML canvas.
So to do that, one thing that we
can do is to not only tell the `Block`
to draw on a canvas, so we can send
extra parameters.
So here, for example,
we can say the `Block` draw on this
canvas, but I am going to send you
the view.
Like that, you can take more decisions.
And here, for example,
the `Wall` can tell the canvas,
the view, okay, view,
draw a `Wall` in this canvas.
In this way, what we have is a lot
of different `Blocks`,
as we saw before, and each of these
will understand, drawOnfor,
and then they're going to send a
message to aCanvas, to a view,
actually, to aView, that will understand
how to draw each of the elements.
Draw X, draw Y, and then the `Block`
is going to delegate the actual
drawing to the view.
And this will allow us to have different
kind of views.
So, for example, we can have a Cairo
view or we can have an HTML view page.
So what we have seen here is an
implementation of double dispatch.
So that means that the decision
of how to draw a `Block`,
in particular, is not only
responsibility of the `Block`,
is the responsibility of both the
`Block` and the canvas or the view.
So that is why it is a double dispatch
because the decision is taken by
two different objects.
So this shows how sending messages
is powerful and modular because
we can add now new kind of canvases
and new kind of `Blocks` by simply
just extending the existing hierarchies.
Now, let's take a step back and
let's look again at these testing
methods.
So here, we had this `isWall` and
`isWall` method, both in `Wall`
and `emptyBlock`, that were returning
true and false in one case and another.
So take a couple of minutes to think,
okay, what do you think about these
methods?
Are they good?
Are they not good?
Are they useful?
And so on.
So every time that we see one of
these methods, you could think that
you are actually hiding some
implementation details.
So here, actually, this is`Wall`
is just a hidden way to write isKindOf
or isInstanceOf in Java,
which is actually a bad practice.
One of the bad parts of this is that,
of course, now this code that requires
that the `Block` is an instance
of a `Wall`, now it cannot work
with other kind of `Walls`.
So all the `Walls` that we implement,
they need to be inheriting from `Wall`.
Otherwise, we cannot add new kind
of `Walls` that are not part of
the same hierarchy.
Otherwise, this test will be false.
Now, if we go back to the model
and we take a look at the other part,
the dynamic part of the system,
which represent all the `Moves`,
what we see is these objects that
represent the actions that we're
going to do.
So we're going to move something.
So we're going to move the `Robots` up,
down, left, or right.
We're going to `Push` a `Box` if
we move in some direction and there
is a `Box` in that direction.
We're going to actually `NoMove`
at all if we are trying to go in
a direction where there is a `Wall`.
And then, there is a result that,
so actually, all these are the result
of trying to move.
So I'm trying to go up and then going up,
if there is a `Wall`,
I'm going to have `NoMove`.
If there was a `Box`,
I'm going to have `Push`.
And if there was nothing,
I'm going to have a move.
So these are representations or
reifications of the actions of the
`Player`.
And having them as a subject,
they are not only good to be able
to manipulate them, but also because
we can store them, for example,
for to be able to record them later
and replay the game automatically.
If we take a look at the API of
these `Moves`, we see the same kind
of pattern again.
So we check, okay, so all the `Moves`
understand if they are move,
if they are `Push`, or if they are
`NoMove`.
So we are probably smelling that
here we are going to see the same
kind of pattern of nested condition,
which at the end are the same thing
as asking, oh, is the class of this
move this class or not?
If we actually take a look at how
they are used, what we see is that
the game states is requested to
move the `Robot` to a direction.
The direction is moving up,
down, left or right.
And then the `Maze`, which is the
model behind, is going to give us,
okay, if you want to move in this
direction, this is the result.
So here inside the move by,
it is checking if in the direction
that we want to move,
we find a `Wall`, a `Box` or nothing.
And then, what we are going to do
is to here we are checking if the
move is a move or a `Push` or something
else.
And then we count the count in the
number of `Moves` and the number
of `Pushes`.
And then we add it to a collection.
So what is the problem of this?
So here the main problem is that
if we want to add a new kind of
move or a new kind of `Block` that
has a different behavior,
we are not going to be able to extend
it easily.
So how can we do it better?
Of course, the same solution as
before is applicable in here.
What we can do is to tell the objects
to do something and not to ask them
what they are.
So instead of asking the move if
they are a move or a `Push` or something
else, what we can do is to tell the move,
update`Block`.
You know who you are,
so please tell the `Block` what
it should do.
And then we send the `GameState` as
parameter.
So here, for example,
a move, it will just increment the
number of `Moves`.
So the move will ask,
will tell actually the `GameState` to
increment the `Moves`.
However, the `Push`, we have a different
implementation.
It will do the same thing as its
superclass.
Remember that 'move' is a superclass
of a `Push` here.
And then, the super will actually
execute the one in the superclass.
And besides incrementing the `Moves`,
because this one will execute this one,
this message send will execute that
method, it will also increase the
number of `Pushes`.
And then, if we have a `NoMove`,
that means that we couldn't do anything
because there was a `Wall`.
We are just going to do nothing.
So this is what this method does.
As a conclusion, try to think about
the classes that you are going to
use in your model.
Remember that little class hierarchies
are good because they help you to
do dispatch.
So the dispatch and the message
is actually the most powerful thing
that you are going to see here.
So it is also in this same sense,
it is better to have many small
classes than a big one,
because many small classes they
will help you doing dispatch.
They will make it natural.
Also, challenge these kind of testing
methods.
Every time that you see an is,
is, is, isX, isY ask yourself if
there was a better solution for that.
And check their use, maybe you will
find a nest of worms.